<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Mala Knyzhka (Taras Shevchenko)</string>
    <string name="book">"Mala Knyzhka" by T. H. Shevchenko, 1846–1850</string>
    <string name="en">English</string>
    <string name="uk">Ukrainian</string>
    <string name="app_language">App Language: %1$s</string>
    <string name="change_lang">Change Language</string>
    <string name="logo_description">Mala Knyzhka</string>
    <string name="privacy_policy_ukr_eng">Privacy Policy (Політика конфіденційності)</string>
    <string name="privacy_policy">Privacy Policy</string>
    <string name="menu">Menu</string>
    <string name="support_ukr_eng">Support (Підтримка)</string>
    <string name="about_app_little_book">About App «Mala Knyzhka (Taras Shevchenko)»</string>


    <string name="about_app_description_part1">This application is more than just an e-book. It allows readers to see the handwritten version of Taras Shevchenko's collection "Mala Knyzhka" alongside the printed text. For the first time, you can explore what the Ukrainian language looked like in its original literary form, preserved by the author himself.</string>
    <string name="about_app_description_part2">This is the first known attempt to create a tool where Shevchenko's original handwriting is combined with recognized text in a user-friendly format for reading, without the need for a constant internet connection.</string>
    <string name="about_app_no_alternatives">There are no similar applications - neither online nor offline. Previously, users had to search for each poem separately in different sources. Here, they are collected together, structured, and convenient.</string>
    <string name="about_app_ai_translation_info">The English translation of the poems was generated using artificial intelligence. This not only conveys the meaning but also preserves the mood of the poetry and its artistic style, making Shevchenko\'s works accessible and emotionally resonant for those who do not speak Ukrainian. This is a new, unique way to immerse oneself in Ukrainian culture.</string>

    <string name="about_app_target_audience">This application is a tool for researchers, students, teachers, and anyone interested in the evolution of the Ukrainian language, the history of literature, and manuscript heritage.</string>

    <string name="about_app_thank_you_message">Thank you for your interest in "Mala Knyzhka". Your support helps preserve the cultural heritage of Ukraine.</string>

    <string name="support">Support</string>
    <string name="about_app">About</string>
    <string name="app_overview">App Overview</string>
    <string name="how_to_use">How to Use</string>

    <string name="cover_description">Drawer background cover</string>

    <string name="developer_support_page">• Contact the developer (support form): </string>

    <string name="turn_pages">- Turning pages using the "&lt;" and "&gt;" buttons.</string>

    <string name="back_button_description">Back</string>
    <string name="size_changing">- Changing page size is available only for handwritten pages.</string>

    <string name="page_saving">- The application automatically saves the last viewed page.</string>
    <string name="we_appreciate">We appreciate your feedback and we are constantly improving the application!</string>

    <string name="faq">FAQ</string>
    <string name="can_change_font_size">- Can change font size? No, it is fixed.</string>
    <string name="app_allows">- The application "Mala Knyzhka (Taras Shevchenko)" allows you to view the digitized version of the manuscript and its printed text.</string>
    <string name="has_bookmarks">- Can add bookmarks? The application automatically saves the last viewed page.</string>
    <string name="is_maintained">- Is it maintained? Yes, we are constantly improving the functionality.</string>
    <string name="thanks_for_using">Thank you for using the "Mala Knyzhka (Taras Shevchenko)" application!</string>
    <string name="if_you_have_questions">If you have any questions, suggestions, or issues, please contact the following channels:</string>
    <string name="portrait_description">Portrait of Taras Shevchenko</string>
    <string name="email_option">• Email Address: </string>
    <string name="chat_option">• For questions and suggestions, please use our Telegram chat: </string>
    <string name="title">Mala Knyzhka</string>
    <string name="subtitle">Original Manuscript by Taras Shevchenko</string>
    <string name="read_now">Start Reading Now</string>
    <string name="privacy">
        <![CDATA[
This privacy policy applies to the Мала Книжка (Тарас Шевченко) app (hereby referred to as "Application") for mobile devices that was created by Dmytro Turskyi (hereby referred to as "Service Provider") as a Free service. This service is intended for use "AS IS".

Information Collection and Use

The Application collects information when you download and use it. This information may include information such as:
• Your device's Internet Protocol address (e.g. IP address);
• The pages of the Application that you visit, the time and date of your visit, the time spent on those pages;
• The time spent on the Application;
• The operating system you use on your mobile device.

The Application does not gather precise information about the location of your mobile device.

The Application collects your device's location, which helps the Service Provider determine your approximate geographical location and make use of in below ways:
1. Analytics and Improvements: Aggregated and anonymized location data helps the Service Provider to analyze user behavior, identify trends, and improve the overall performance and functionality of the Application.
2. Third-Party Services: Periodically, the Service Provider may transmit anonymized location data to external services. These services assist them in enhancing the Application and optimizing their offerings.

The Service Provider may use the information you provided to contact you from time to time to provide you with important information, required notices and marketing promotions.

For a better experience, while using the Application, the Service Provider may require you to provide us with certain personally identifiable information. The information that the Service Provider request will be retained by them and used as described in this privacy policy.

Third Party Access

Only aggregated, anonymized data is periodically transmitted to external services to aid the Service Provider in improving the Application and their service. The Service Provider may share your information with third parties in the ways that are described in this privacy statement.

Please note that the Application utilizes third-party services that have their own Privacy Policy about handling data. Below are the links to the Privacy Policy of the third-party service providers used by the Application:
• Google Play Services
• Google Analytics for Firebase
• Firebase Crashlytics

The Service Provider may disclose User Provided and Automatically Collected Information:
• as required by law, such as to comply with a subpoena, or similar legal process;
• when they believe in good faith that disclosure is necessary to protect their rights, protect your safety or the safety of others, investigate fraud, or respond to a government request;
• with their trusted services providers who work on their behalf, do not have an independent use of the information we disclose to them, and have agreed to adhere to the rules set forth in this privacy statement.

Opt-Out Rights

You can stop all collection of information by the Application easily by uninstalling it. You may use the standard uninstall processes as may be available as part of your mobile device or via the mobile application marketplace or network.

Data Retention Policy

The Service Provider will retain User Provided data for as long as you use the Application and for a reasonable time thereafter. If you'd like them to delete User Provided Data that you have provided via the Application, please contact them at dmytro@turskyi.com and they will respond in a reasonable time.

Children

The Service Provider does not use the Application to knowingly solicit data from or market to children under the age of 6.

The Application does not address anyone under the age of 6. The Service Provider does not knowingly collect personally identifiable information from children under 6 years of age. In the case the Service Provider discover that a child under 6 has provided personal information, the Service Provider will immediately delete this from their servers. If you are a parent or guardian and you are aware that your child has provided us with personal information, please contact the Service Provider (dmytro@turskyi.com) so that they will be able to take the necessary actions.

Security

The Service Provider is concerned about safeguarding the confidentiality of your information. The Service Provider provides physical, electronic, and procedural safeguards to protect information the Service Provider processes and maintains.

Changes

This Privacy Policy may be updated from time to time for any reason. The Service Provider will notify you of any changes to the Privacy Policy by updating this page with the new Privacy Policy. You are advised to consult this Privacy Policy regularly for any changes, as continued use is deemed approval of all changes.

This privacy policy is effective as of 2025-06-15.

Your Consent

By using the Application, you are consenting to the processing of your information as set forth in this Privacy Policy now and as amended by us.

Contact Us

If you have any questions regarding privacy while using the Application, or have questions about the practices, please contact the Service Provider via email at dmytro@turskyi.com.
]]>
    </string>
    <string name="privacy_ukr_eng">
        <![CDATA[
Privacy Policy (English)

This privacy policy applies to the Мала Книжка (Тарас Шевченко) app (hereby referred to as "Application") for mobile devices that was created by Dmytro Turskyi (hereby referred to as "Service Provider") as a Free service. This service is intended for use "AS IS".

Information Collection and Use

The Application collects information when you download and use it. This information may include information such as:
• Your device's Internet Protocol address (e.g. IP address);
• The pages of the Application that you visit, the time and date of your visit, the time spent on those pages;
• The time spent on the Application;
• The operating system you use on your mobile device.

The Application does not gather precise information about the location of your mobile device.

The Application collects your device's location, which helps the Service Provider determine your approximate geographical location and make use of in below ways:
1. Analytics and Improvements: Aggregated and anonymized location data helps the Service Provider to analyze user behavior, identify trends, and improve the overall performance and functionality of the Application.
2. Third-Party Services: Periodically, the Service Provider may transmit anonymized location data to external services. These services assist them in enhancing the Application and optimizing their offerings.

The Service Provider may use the information you provided to contact you from time to time to provide you with important information, required notices and marketing promotions.

For a better experience, while using the Application, the Service Provider may require you to provide us with certain personally identifiable information. The information that the Service Provider request will be retained by them and used as described in this privacy policy.

Third Party Access

Only aggregated, anonymized data is periodically transmitted to external services to aid the Service Provider in improving the Application and their service. The Service Provider may share your information with third parties in the ways that are described in this privacy statement.

Please note that the Application utilizes third-party services that have their own Privacy Policy about handling data. Below are the links to the Privacy Policy of the third-party service providers used by the Application:
• Google Play Services
• Google Analytics for Firebase
• Firebase Crashlytics

The Service Provider may disclose User Provided and Automatically Collected Information:
• as required by law, such as to comply with a subpoena, or similar legal process;
• when they believe in good faith that disclosure is necessary to protect their rights, protect your safety or the safety of others, investigate fraud, or respond to a government request;
• with their trusted services providers who work on their behalf, do not have an independent use of the information we disclose to them, and have agreed to adhere to the rules set forth in this privacy statement.

Opt-Out Rights

You can stop all collection of information by the Application easily by uninstalling it. You may use the standard uninstall processes as may be available as part of your mobile device or via the mobile application marketplace or network.

Data Retention Policy

The Service Provider will retain User Provided data for as long as you use the Application and for a reasonable time thereafter. If you'd like them to delete User Provided Data that you have provided via the Application, please contact them at dmytro@turskyi.com and they will respond in a reasonable time.

Children

The Service Provider does not use the Application to knowingly solicit data from or market to children under the age of 6.

The Application does not address anyone under the age of 6. The Service Provider does not knowingly collect personally identifiable information from children under 6 years of age. In the case the Service Provider discover that a child under 6 has provided personal information, the Service Provider will immediately delete this from their servers. If you are a parent or guardian and you are aware that your child has provided us with personal information, please contact the Service Provider (dmytro@turskyi.com) so that they will be able to take the necessary actions.

Security

The Service Provider is concerned about safeguarding the confidentiality of your information. The Service Provider provides physical, electronic, and procedural safeguards to protect information the Service Provider processes and maintains.

Changes

This Privacy Policy may be updated from time to time for any reason. The Service Provider will notify you of any changes to the Privacy Policy by updating this page with the new Privacy Policy. You are advised to consult this Privacy Policy regularly for any changes, as continued use is deemed approval of all changes.

This privacy policy is effective as of 2025-01-09.

Your Consent

By using the Application, you are consenting to the processing of your information as set forth in this Privacy Policy now and as amended by us.

Contact Us

If you have any questions regarding privacy while using the Application, or have questions about the practices, please contact the Service Provider via email at dmytro@turskyi.com.

Політика конфіденційності (українською мовою)

Ця політика конфіденційності застосовується до додатка “Мала Книжка (Тарас Шевченко)” (надалі “Додаток”) для мобільних пристроїв, який створив Дмитро Турський (надалі “Постачальник послуг”) як безкоштовний сервіс. Цей сервіс надається для використання “як є”.

Збір та використання інформації

Додаток збирає інформацію під час завантаження та використання. Ця інформація може включати:
• IP-адресу вашого пристрою (наприклад, IP-адреса);
• Сторінки Додатка, які ви відвідуєте, час і дата відвідування, час, проведений на цих сторінках;
• Час використання Додатка;
• Операційну систему вашого мобільного пристрою.

Додаток не збирає точну інформацію про місцезнаходження вашого мобільного пристрою.

Додаток може збирати дані про ваше приблизне географічне місцезнаходження, які використовуються в наступних цілях:
1. Аналітика та поліпшення: Агреговані та анонімні дані використовуються для аналізу поведінки користувачів, визначення тенденцій і покращення роботи Додатка.
2. Сторонні сервіси: Час від часу анонімні дані можуть передаватися зовнішнім сервісам для покращення функціональності Додатка.

Постачальник послуг може використовувати надану вами інформацію для спілкування з вами, надання важливої інформації, повідомлень та маркетингових пропозицій.

Для кращого досвіду використання Додатка Постачальник послуг може запросити вас надати певну інформацію, яка буде зберігатися відповідно до цієї політики конфіденційності.

Доступ третіх сторін

Агреговані та анонімні дані періодично передаються зовнішнім сервісам для покращення Додатка. Постачальник послуг може ділитися вашою інформацією з третіми сторонами у випадках, зазначених у цій політиці.

Сторонні сервіси, які використовує Додаток:
• Google Play Services
• Google Analytics for Firebase
• Firebase Crashlytics

Постачальник послуг може розкрити зібрану інформацію в таких випадках:
• Вимога закону, наприклад, судовий запит.
• Захист прав, безпеки користувачів або інших осіб.
• Співпраця з надійними постачальниками, які дотримуються цієї політики.

Права відмови

Ви можете припинити збір даних, видаливши Додаток зі свого пристрою. Для цього скористайтеся стандартними методами видалення, доступними у вашому пристрої чи маркетплейсі.

Політика зберігання даних

Постачальник послуг зберігатиме надані дані до моменту використання Додатка або протягом розумного періоду після цього. Якщо ви бажаєте видалити свої дані, надішліть запит на адресу електронної пошти: dmytro@turskyi.com.

Діти
Додаток не адресований особам молодше 6 років. Постачальник послуг не збирає даних у дітей до 6 років. У разі виявлення таких даних вони будуть негайно видалені. Якщо ви — батько чи опікун і знаєте, що ваша дитина надала особисту інформацію, зв’яжіться з нами.

Безпека

Постачальник послуг вживає фізичних, електронних і процедурних заходів для захисту вашої інформації.

Зміни

Ця політика конфіденційності може оновлюватися час від часу. Постачальник послуг рекомендує регулярно перевіряти цю сторінку на наявність змін.

Згода

Використовуючи Додаток, ви погоджуєтесь із цією Політикою конфіденційності.

Контакти

Якщо у вас виникли питання щодо цієї Політики конфіденційності, зв’яжіться з нами за адресою dmytro@turskyi.com.
]]>
    </string>
    <string name="001">
        1847.
    </string>
    <string name="002">
My thoughts, my thoughts,
You are all I have,
Do not abandon me
In my hour of need.
Fly to me, blue-winged doves,
My gentle little doves,
From beyond the wide Dnipro
Come roam the steppe
With the poor Kirghiz,
They are already poor,
Already naked… but in freedom
Still pray to God.
Come to me, my dear ones,
With your quiet words
I’ll greet you as my children,
And weep along with you.
    </string>
    <string name="003">
O evening star, my shining one,
Rise above the hill,
Let us speak in foreign lands
Softly, you and I.
Tell me how beyond the hill
The sun is setting down,
How by the Dnipro, a rainbow
Borrows water for its crown,
How the broad-leaved poplar
Spreads its branches wide…
And by the water’s very edge
A willow leans aside;
Its green branches trailing
Across the water’s face,
And on those branches swinging
Unbaptized children’s grace.
How in the field, upon a mound,
A werewolf spends the night,
And in the woods, or on a roof,
An owl foretells our plight.
How dream-grass by the valley
Blooms at night in secret flight…
        </string>
    <string name="004">
Don’t speak to me about people—
I know them all too well.
But I’ll whisper you a little
Just before I sleep tonight.
And you, tomorrow, in the dawn-light,
Tell it all to God.

A village! And the heart finds rest:
A village in our Ukraine—
Like a painted Easter egg it lies,
Green groves its leafy dress.
The gardens bloom, the houses white,
And on the hill, a palace bright—
A marvel, standing proud. Around,
Tall poplars with their sweeping sound,
And farther still, a forest grand,
Then fields, then hills across the land—
The Dnipro shining blue.
God Himself floats above that view.

The village! Homes with joy alight!
The palace too—a gleaming sight,
A merry hilltop edifice…
May thorn and bramble overrun it,
So no one finds a trace or sign,
Nor even thinks to seek or wonder.

In that very same village,
Yes, that very same land
Of our proud Ukraine—
Where did they even come from?—
A wandering prince once settled.
There was a princess too.
They were young,
Lived alone,
And rich.
Their palace high upon the slope,
A pond below,
A garden bright with verdant green,
With willows, poplars,
Windmills turning on the fields,
And down the valley stretched the village
Beside the water’s thread.

There once was joy!
In summer’s heat or winter’s cold
The music played, the wine would pour
Like rivers for the hungry guests…
    </string>
    <string name="005">
And the prince, flushed blue with drink,
Still poured for the meek and quiet,
Shouting out a bold “Vivat!”
He reveled, as did all his guests—
They rolled about the wooden floors…

And the next day, it lived again—
Drinking, feasting, joy without end.
Day by day, it never ceased—
While peasant souls cried out beneath.

The judges begged for mercy’s grace…
But drunks just shouted in their place:
“A patriot! A friend to poor men!
A philosopher! A second Socrates!”
Yes, Socrates, poor man’s friend,
Steals a peasant’s calf and child—
And God? Perhaps He sees,
But only watches silently.

The princess sits alone, locked in.
Our Socrates won’t let her pass
Beyond the hallway’s wooden skin—
His own Xanthippe. What a fate!

She fled at last and took her vow,
Though father, mother cried aloud:
“Don’t climb so high! He’s not your place.”
But no—she wed the prince. And now:
Behold your title, princess fair!
Behold your uniform to wear!

You’ll perish, dearest, you’ll be lost—
Like blooming thyme in springtime frost.
You’ll dry and never even know
How God is praised, how people glow
With love while living.

Oh, to live!
To love—if just for one short hour—
To glimpse the world,
To praise its power…
But it was not to be.

And yet she had it all—
The mother’s aged hands had made
Her like an icon on the wall.
One could have prayed before her face
As if she were a saint in place…

O beauty, youthful, blazing bright!
My beauty, with your quiet pain—
You longed to live,
To bless His name,
To do some good,
To bring delight
With Heaven’s charm
In mortal sight.
    </string>
    <string name="006">
But no.
Not so that youthful eyes,
Dark-browed and shining,
Would fade in lonely shadow…

Perhaps this is God’s will?

Oh Lord! You give us mind and soul,
A heart that’s pure, a form that’s whole,
But still—You do not give us life.
You don’t allow our joy to rise,
To see Your world in gleaming light,
To worship You, to breathe it in…

It’s bitter, Lord, to walk this earth
With no one here to share your mirth.
So it was for her—alone,
My princess, young and on her own—
Her beauty fading like a bloom,
Her heart enclosed in silent gloom.
She wept and prayed in hope to live,
For now, at last, she had someone to love.

She walked with pride—a mother now—
And God allowed her joy somehow.
She held her child, her only one,
And kissed it in the morning sun.
She heard the first cry echo loud…

Oh children! Children! Heaven’s gift!
Yet sorrow comes and will not lift—
It robs our peace,
Our joy turns dim.

The princess was not the same within.
She smiled again,
As if reborn—
She laughed and played
Without the scorn.

She sewed small shirts for her young girl,
Embroidered sleeves with silk and pearl,
She bathed her, rocked her, sang at night—
She fed her with her own delight.
For princesses are only taught
To bring a child forth—
But love? They’re not.
    </string>
    <string name="007">
To nurse and tend with careful hand—
That’s not what princesses understand.
And later comes a mournful sigh:
“My Paul… my Phil… forgot me! Why?”

Why would they remember you—
For birthing them alone?
But mine—she nursed her child alone.
And barred the drunken prince from home.
The child, like apples in the shade,
Grew in love,
And words she made.
The princess taught her just one name—
“Mother”—that’s all she was to say.
She never taught her “father” sound…

She bought her books with pictures bright
In Romny’s market, brought delight.
She played with her, she sang with her,
She taught her prayers,
Taught her her letters,
Day by day—
She bathed her, laid her down to sleep,
Then like a dove above her stayed,
Hovered, watched,
All night she’d weep
With joy and awe and quiet grace
Upon her daughter’s sleeping face.

And then she dreamed of marriage too,
Of braiding hair for something new.
She wept, and still she smiled through tears,
Unbraiding braids of girlhood years.

She even thought of that poor prince
In uniform—a flash, a wince.
She thought of him… then closed the page.

And to the child, it seemed a dream,
As if her lips would try to say:
“Don’t weep, mama,
Don’t comb my hair—
They’ll cut it anyway…”

And day by day, joy found its way.
    </string>
    <string name="008">
To my happy mother.
Her daughter, lovely,
Grows like a poplar,
A wonder to her mother.
She grows… but will not long
Bring joy and laughter—
For God will strike
The princess in this world.
And why? People wonder,
For they do not know
Why the good must die,
While evil walks again—
Evil rises again!

The princess fell ill,
And the prince came to his senses.
Drunken, he dashed through villages
Summoning doctors.
They gathered, they toiled,
They treated and treated—
Till at last, the poor soul
Was laid in the ground.

No more the unfortunate princess,
And the fiddles play again.
But her orphaned child,
Her only daughter,
Wanders the village like a broken branch,
Barefoot, hungry, in rags.
Scorched by the sun,
She eats dock leaves, dams up ponds,
Splashing with children in the ravine.

Wash yourself, dear heart!
Your mother watches
And cannot recognize
Her child among the others.
She thinks you are gone…
Wash, dear soul,
So she may know you—
Her only one—
And bless the Lord
For your good fortune.

She washed, and kind folk
Dressed her and took her
To Kyiv.
    </string>
    <string name="009">
To the institute. What comes next,
We’ll see. Fiddles played again,
The prince caroused, the guests rejoiced,
The palace echoed with their feast—
While hunger moaned throughout the land.

Oh, how it moaned! Across Ukraine
It raged like God’s own scourge.
Thousands perished,
While hayricks rotted
And the lords sold chaff to Jews.
They welcomed the hunger,
Prayed to God for one more year
Without a harvest—
Then even in Paris
Our farmhand kin could thrive.

And God?… No, He must not know.
For it would be a wonder
To see and hear such sorrow
And still not punish it.
Or perhaps He is too patient…
“Believe, and perish!” cry the prophets.
But how to believe
With eyes shut tight?
I would believe—oh, how I would!—
But my heart will not.

Years pass. People die.
Famine grips Ukraine,
Even the prince’s village.
His grain stacks rot away,
But the prince drinks,
Laughs, and looks out
For a Jew with money.

No Jews. The wheat has sprouted.
The people rejoice,
Praise God.
And then from Kyiv
She returns—
The princess.

A sun has risen
Over the plundered village.
Dark-browed, hazel-eyed,
As tall as her mother,
But quiet, sorrowful.
Why sorrow?

Maybe it’s just her nature.
Maybe in Kyiv—
Or worse, in foolish love—
She gave her heart away?
No… she had grown joyful.
But she saw her homeland—
Saw the famine.
That’s why she does not smile.
    </string>
    <string name="010">
She never met her drunken father.
She flew through the village
Like a songbird, visited all,
And joy returned to every home.

Here—she offered words of warmth,
There—she gave food.
Each day, she walked the village,
Helping all she could.

Orphans came
Into her rooms
As to their own mother—
And called her saint.

The whole village did.
The whole village prayed…
But meanwhile,
Jews returned to the village,
Bringing money.

The prince rejoiced,
Sold grain mixed with chaff,
Drove the starving peasants
To thresh.
Then called for a drinking feast.

They drank, they sang—
Even in the grove—
Because his daughter
Was asleep indoors.

Racket and raving in the woods,
Shameful songs,
Women’s laughter,
And the master’s slurred cry:
“Drink on, while our daughter sleeps!”

But the princess sat alone
In her quiet chamber,
Watching the blood-red moon
Climb above the hill.

It rose from clouds,
And it seemed the hills
Came to life—
Dark wonders drifted from the woods,
And an owl flew into the village.

Oh, look, young eyes!
While the stars rise—
While the moon burns red—
Look, while it warms you,
And sleep not—
Let the stars keep you awake.
    </string>
    <string name="011">
Her young head bowed
Into her hands,
She stared at the stars
Past midnight, sorrowful.

She gazed… and gazed…
Then tears began to fall.
Perhaps some silent grief
Whispered to her heart?
I don’t know—
She wept,
Wiped her face, smiled,
Prayed,
And went to sleep.

And all around—
In the orchard—
Guests and harem lay where they dropped.
Only the master still stood,
Draining the last glass.
He rose, steady—
And walked indoors.

Foul creature! Where are you going?
Stop!
Awaken, pure one!
Wake—
Kill the serpent before he strikes!
Kill—God won’t punish you for it!

But she did not wake.
She slept.
And God, though watching,
Was silent still—
Letting the great sin pass.

Time passed…
Then shouts were heard
From the palace—
And then, silence.

The hayricks and the barn
Caught fire—
Not a sound,
No voice, no cry.

The nobles lay still in the orchard.
The peasants watched the smoke
Spiral into the clouds.

By morning, the guests awoke
To disaster.
They left their prince—
Calmly, quietly.

And so shall we leave him.
And so shall God.
    </string>
    <string name="012">
That such vile beasts may never tread Upon our Ukraine’s land.
And where is she, defiled before? Her footsteps lost in sand.

Orphans, widows search in vain For mother who had cared.
Only silence greets their cries, No presence to be shared.

The village stands in sorrow's grip,
Upon the hill a palace bare,
Blackened walls, a weary prince,
No laughter lingers there.

None to comfort, none to call,
No soul peeks through the gate,
The sick and sinful sit alone,
Their homes in wretched state.

The people groan, oppressed and lost,
Yet pray to God above — That she, their holy princess,
Return to them with love.

But she is gone, and nevermore Will grace their humble plain.
Where has she fled? To mighty Kyiv— A nun in solemn chain.

So it was, and so shall be— In sin and sorrow we are born.
    </string>
    <string name="013">
Tell me, wise and knowing hearts, What praise does God receive
— From lives where love was meant to bloom, Yet anguish fills the eves?

To scatter beauty, light divine, Among the lost and frail,
To bring forth kindness, hands so pure, Yet sorrow tells the tale.

No joy remains for heaven’s gaze, No peace for one once proud.
Seeking ruins of the past, She roamed a country cowed.

To Chyhyryn, a monastery poor, I ventured on my way.
The mighty rise, the voices speak, Their words the mountains sway.

And through the dust of history grim,
The echoes cry aloud:
To live is bliss—until the heart No love has left to vow.

A nun revealed the whispered truth: A sister rests within their keep.
A princess from beyond the waves, A soul resigned to weep.

Two years ago, she came alone, Returned from distant lands.
Her wealth was great, her journey wide— To God’s own shrine she ran.

Yet fate had turned, misfortune fell, Her path grew heavy, cold.
For how can she, so young and bright, Roam beggars’ roads untold?

Her beauty faded, sun’s harsh kiss Had burned its tender grace.
She lay, confessed her every grief, And left for God’s embrace.
    </string>
    <string name="014">
In holy cities far and wide, She wandered, seeking light.
Then pointed to a solemn grave— Here rests her weary might.

Remember, brothers, hold this truth, That sorrow never strays.
As once we stood with eager eyes, Behind our iron cage.

We dreamt, we hoped, we thought aloud, Of peaceful talk, of quiet days.
Would we once more embrace as one, Upon these withered plains?

Nevermore, my brothers, never, Shall we drink from Dnipro’s stream.
We part, we scatter, lost we go, To forests deep unseen.

We whisper still of fleeting hope, Yet soon shall cease to dream.
And then, among our fellow men, We live as they have been.

But until that moment comes,
    </string>
    <string name="015">
Love each other, brothers mine, Let Ukraine fill your soul.
Pray for her, so sorrowed deep, And ask for God’s control.

Forget the past, forgive the pain, Let anger fade away.
And in this bitter bondage dark, Remember me some day.

Alone I stand, one trembling reed, Upon the field so wide.
No fortune granted, nor a joy, No happiness beside.

One gift was given, eyes so bright — That time stole like a thief,
For tears had washed their spark away, And left me lost in grief.

No brother’s hand, no sister’s grace, Strangers I called my kin.
They raised me, yet within their walls, No love could bloom within.

Where are they now, those kindred souls,
Who once could call me dear? They are gone, I stand alone— And none will reappear.
    </string>
    <string name="016">
Beyond the ravine – another,
Then steppes, and a burial mound.
From the grave a grey old Cossack
Rises without a sound.
He rises in the night alone,
Walks the steppe and sings a moan:
– We heaped up earth and went away,
And none remembers to this day.
Three hundred comrades here lie low!
The earth itself won’t take us so.
The hetman sold us into chains,
Sent us to chase our kin in vain.
Upon our land, in brother's blood
We waded deep, we choked in mud,
We killed each other, cursed and damned,
And here we rot beneath the sand. –
He fell silent, sorrowed deep,
Bent upon his spear to weep.
He stood atop the burial ground,
And gazed at Dnipro, sobbing loud;
The blue waves moaned in mournful flow.
From across the river's glow
Came the rustle of a wood,
Came the roosters' call for good.
The ghost sank down without a word,
The ravine shuddered where it stirred,
And the grave gave a mournful groan.

It is all one to me, whether
I live in Ukraine or not.
Whether anyone remembers
Or forgets me, it matters not —
It’s all the same to me.
I grew in bondage 'midst the foe.
    </string>
    <string name="017">
Unwept by kin, in tears I'll go
To die in slavery and despair,
And leave behind no memory there—
No trace at all on Ukraine’s field,
Our glorious but unclaimed land.
No father shall his young son teach:
“Pray, son, for Ukraine, kneel and reach —
For he was tortured, crushed and banned.”
It matters not if one will pray…
But one thing does — and this I say:
It matters deeply, bitterly,
If sly and evil men will lull
My Ukraine in a burning sleep,
Then rouse her, robbed and shamed and dull…
Oh, this — I cannot bear to see.

“They said: ‘Don’t leave your mother,’
But you fled and left her lone.
She searched — and finding nothing,
Stopped. She died, weeping on her own.
The place where once you played is still.
The house — a window’s shattered out,
The dog has wandered off at will…
By day, lambs graze in shadows deep,
At night, the owls and nightbirds weep
And let no neighbor sleep nearby.
Your periwinkle, once so spry,
Is choked with thistle, waiting still
For your return. The garden pond,
Where once you bathed, is nearly gone,
The grove is silent, bowed with grief,
No birdsong gives it sweet relief.
You took it with you when you left.
The well in the ravine collapsed,
The willow dried and bent away,
And where you walked — a thorny path.
    </string>
    <string name="018">
Where did you vanish? Where’d you fly?
To whom did you now give your smile?
In foreign land, in stranger’s kin,
Whom do you love? To whom belong?
My heart foretells — you live in halls,
You dwell in splendor, without wrong,
And feel no sorrow for the home
You left in silence, left alone.
I pray to God, may grief not wake
You from that sleep; may you not find
That God is cruel or unkind,
Nor curse your mother for her ache.

"Why do you go there — to the grave?" —
Her mother asked, with voice so strained.
"Why do you cry when walking by?
Why don’t you sleep throughout the night,
My tender dove, so pale and shy?"
"Yes, mother… yes." — And still she came,
While mother wept, and watched the same.
Not dream-grass on the grave that grows
And blossoms in the moonlight’s glow —
A betrothed girl plants a bough
Of guelder rose and kneels to pray:
That God might send a gentle rain,
And morning dew to bless the sprout,
So it may bloom and branch about.
"Perhaps a bird he’ll turn to be,
My love, and come again to me.
I'll weave a nest for him to lie,
And I will come and join him nigh.
We’ll chirp and whisper through the day,
Fly to the other world and stay —
Each morning rise and soar away."
    </string>
    <string name="019">
The guelder rose took root and grew,
Spread out its branches, broad and true.
Three years the girl came to the mound,
The fourth... not dream-grass blooming round.
But there she stands — in midnight hush —
And weeps and speaks beneath the bush:
"O guelder rose, so wide and high,
Not by water you were blessed
At sunrise, but with tears expressed —
Great rivers poured from both my eyes,
And people praised them — spreading lies!
Now friends despise me, all around,
Despise my guelder rose so proud.
O bind my head, and bathe my face,
And shield me with your leafy grace
From morning sun. For when they see
Me there at dawn, they'll mock at me.
Your branches wide, their hands will tear,
The village children playing there." —
At dawn, a bird was softly singing
In the guelder rose’s shade.
And there beneath it — the girl sleeping.
She didn’t rise. Her soul had stayed.
The tender youth was tired and done —
She went to sleep forevermore.
The sun rose slowly from the grave,
And people woke with joy once more.
But mother hadn’t slept all night.
She waited for her child at door,
And wept in silence, as before.
    </string>
    <string name="020">
Three wide roads together met,
And there the brothers parted—
Each one to foreign lands had set,
From Ukraine's heart departed.
They left behind their mother old,
One left his wife and daughter,
The youngest—he had just been told—
Left his betrothed in sorrow.

The mother planted in the field
Three ash trees, high and slender.
The wife—a poplar did she yield,
Tall, waving in the weather.
Three maples by the quiet stream
The sister sadly planted,
And red viburnum in a dream
The girl, love’s promise granted.

The ashes withered, would not grow,
The poplar drooped in dying,
The maples shriveled long ago,
The kalyna stopped blooming.
The brothers never have returned,
The mother weeps and prays,
The wife sits cold in rooms unburned
With children in a daze.
The sister walks abroad to find
Her brothers, lost and gone—
The betrothed girl they now must bind
In a coffin made of stone.
They roam the world, the brothers three,
And thorn o’ergrows the road’s decree.

The merry sun was hiding low
In clouds of spring’s delight.
The fettered guests were served below
With tea through bars of night.
The guards in blue took up their post,
New shifts replaced the old,
And keys turned doors behind the host—
Barred windows grim and cold.
    </string>
    <string name="021">
I’d grown accustomed to the cell,
To tears of past distress—
Those bloodied tears that once would well
I’d long since laid to rest.
They soaked the ground and nothing grew—
No rue, no bloom, no blade.
In dreams, my native place I knew,
My village long decayed.
Whom did I leave, and when, and why?
My father, mother—gone.
And with the thought, my heart went dry:
None left to grieve alone.

I see—your mother, brother mine,
Dark as the earth she treads,
As though just taken from the cross,
A living shade of dread.
I pray! O Lord, I give Thee praise!
I'll share my chains with none—
This prison and these iron days
Are mine and mine alone.

The cherry orchard by the cot,
Beetles buzz above the trees.
The ploughmen march through fields sun-hot,
And girls sing on the breeze.
The mothers wait with evening food,
And stars in dusk arise.
The daughter serves, the night is good—
The nightingale denies
The mother’s wish to teach and speak—
So sweet the bird does call.
She lays the children down to sleep,
And slumbers with them all.
The world is still, no sound repeats,
Save girls—and birdsong beats.
    </string>
    <string name="022">
I could not sleep—the night like sea
(Though not in autumn, still it felt
That way in prison). Silently
I lay, no words to pain had dealt,
No dreams of childhood came to me.
I tossed and turned, awaited dawn,
Beyond the door two guards went on
To talk about their soldier’s fate—
The low and broken, cruel state:

**1**
“She wasn’t pretty, but she gave
Herself like one who begged to live.
The master saw, and off I went—
They caught me, shaved me, made me slave,
To Kaluga I was sent.”

**2**
“And I—God help me when I tell—
I joined the ranks, I walked away.
I loved a girl, the village knew,
And with her widowed mother too,
We asked her hand. The lord, the brute,
Said, ‘She’s too young, I won't permit.’
Yet still I’d go to see Hanuśa—
She was so dear, I wouldn’t quit.

Next year again I dared to plead—
He said, ‘It’s not enough. You need
Five hundred—give it, and she’s yours.’
What could I do? I left our doors
To earn that sum… by foot, by steed
I wandered far beyond the Don,
For two long years the roads dragged on,
Bought gifts of gold and velvet thread,
Came home to claim my bride… instead—
I found her mother dying slow,
And empty house with roof laid low.”
    </string>
    <string name="023">
        42
        43
    </string>
    <string name="024">
I struck a flame and ran to her—
She smelled already of the earth.
She did not know me anymore…
I ran for priest, for neighbor’s word,
Brought priest—but he had come too late—
She’d passed, my love, my soul, my fate.
I asked the neighbor what had been.
He sighed, “You’ve not heard yet, I see?
Hanuśa’s gone to Siberia.

She used to meet the master's son,
Then bore his child. One early dawn
She threw it in the well, and fled…”
A burning horror seized my head.
I left the hut, the light was dim,
My heart was mad—I rushed to him,
With knife in hand, through mist and gate,
To kill or end my wretched fate.
But he’d been sent to Kyiv school.
That saved him… and perhaps this fool.

My parents stayed. I walked away,
Became a soldier in dismay.
Still shivers take me when I say—
I thought to burn his house that day,
Or take my life—yet God forbade.

**1**
“So now he’s stationed here again?”

**2**
“Yes, transferred. Army men.”

**1**
“Well, let it be. God sees our cries.
Perhaps someday it fades, it dies.”
They talked for long into the night,
While I half-dreamed before first light.
Those noble sons came back to me,
And robbed me of my sleep, you see.

New recruits at dawn’s first hue
Marched beyond the town anew.
And a girl behind them came,
Softly walking, none to blame.
    </string>
    <string name="025">
An old mother saw her child
In the field, and caught her mild—
She led her back, and wept, and stayed,
And talked until in earth she laid
The girl to rest—and then she roamed,
A beggar with no kin or home.

Years went by—the village still
Remained unchanged, the sloping hill
Still bore one hut, alone and bare,
Its roof now sagging in despair.
Beside it limped a crippled guard,
On crutches watching, breathing hard,
He looked toward the garden gate,
Peeked into that empty state.

In vain, my brother—none appears
From that old house, no voice he hears.
No mother calls from within walls
To dine when evening softly falls.
And yet—remember? Long ago
She wove the towels white as snow,
Embroidered scarves with silk and care—
He dreamed of life, and love, and prayer.

But fate was cruel—there’s no one left
To lean on now, alone, bereft.
He sits beside the silent home,
Twilight falling, all alone.
And in the window—like an omen—
An owl looks out, old and solemn.

It’s hard in chains, though freedom’s fate
Was never mine to contemplate.
But still, one lived—though far from kind,
Upon strange fields, with strangers’ minds.
But now, this bitter fate I meet
I wait for like I’d wait for God.
I watch, I hope, I curse my thought
That let me drown my will, my feet
In muddy dreams of liberty.
    </string>
    <string name="026">
My heart turns cold when I recall
That I’ll not in Ukraine be buried,
That I won’t live in Ukraine’s hall,
To love both people and the Lord.
            12.
Shall we once more together meet?
Or have we parted for all time?
The word of love and truth we spread
Through steppe and forest, hill and clime.
Well, let it be. Though not our mother,
We had to learn to honor her.
It is the Lord’s will. So, obey!
Be humble, pray to God, and stay
In thought of one another, still.
Love your Ukraine — and love her well,
In times of wrath and storm and hell,
And in your final, painful hour,
For her to God send up your prayer.
         13.
Across the fields he goes,
Not mowing swaths — but hills he mows.
The earth it groans, the sea it cries,
The air is moaning, full of sighs.
Owls meet him through the night,
This reaper’s dreadful flight.
He cuts and never rests, nor heeds,
No prayer nor plea his fury leads.
Don’t ask, don’t plead,
He doesn’t stop to whet his blade.
Whether a town, a field, a land,
The old man shaves with ruthless hand
Whatever’s in his way:
The peasant, tavern-keeper, bard,
He sings and mows through night so hard —
Even the king won’t stay.
    </string>
    <string name="027">
Nor shall I be spared —
On foreign soil I’ll be struck down,
Behind the bars I’ll fade and drown,
No cross shall mark my place of rest,
And none will whisper me a prayer.

The sun sets down, the mountains blacken,
The birds grow still, the fields fall dumb.
Men rejoice in rest that’s come —
But I look on… my heart takes flight
To Ukraine’s orchard lost in night.
I soar again, my thoughts I ponder,
And feel my heart in stillness wander.
The field is black, the woods, the hill,
A star climbs up the heavens still…
O star, O star — and tears arise.
Have you already graced Ukraine?
Do dark eyes seek you in the skies?
Or have they ceased to call your name?
If they forget — let them not wake,
Let none recall my bitter fate.
    </string>
    <string name="028">
I pray, again I place my hope,
Again my tears begin to flow,
And all my heavy thoughts I pour
To silent walls that guard my woe.
Cry out with me! Break silence, speak!
Lament with me,
O dumb walls, weep
Over this human wrong,
This cruel fate so strong.
Cry out! And maybe, echoing,
My sleepless grief will start to sing,
Will smile at us through bitter fate,
And thank us as it lies in wait,
Will weep and pray, and fall asleep —
At peace at last, with sorrow deep.

This is my counsel, unknown brother:
Be meek before your Lord above.
Seek out a brother in the palace
Or in the cottage — give him love.
Prepare your grave with quiet hand,
And seek not fame across the land.
    </string>
    <string name="029">
For fame will not extend youth’s days,
Nor bring our spring back through time’s haze.
So pray, my friend — seek God, dear brother,
And in your prayers, remember me.

Around St. Nicholas in the fall,
In rags and tatters, nearly bare,
Along the Bender road at night
The gypsies walked in lantern-light…
Of course, the free folk sang their song.
They walked and walked, then paused along
The road, pitched tents beside the track,
Lit up a fire, poor and slack,
And sat around it, tired, worn,
Some with meat, and some — forlorn,
Yet free, like Cossacks once had been.
They sat and dozed in shadows dim.
Beyond the tent, a voice arose —
As if a drunken maiden goes
Homeward with her dowry chest,
Singing, spinning, quite possessed:
“O, in the new house
All went to bed —
And the young bride dreamed
Her mother went mad,
Her father-in-law drowned,
Her father remarried…”
And — hush…

The gypsies laughed to hear the sound:
— What kind of folks are here around?
That must be someone from the Dniester —
This land’s a steppe — a ghost! A specter!
They cried, they leapt, their sleep undone —
Before them stood the singing one…
A sight of pity, dread, and fright —
In tattered coat she stood upright.
Her hands and feet were stained with red —
From cold the blood had outward bled.
Her long hair tangled, full of burrs…
She stood a while, then came and stirred
The fire, warming her hands
On open flame and glowing brands.
    </string>
    <string name="030">
– So then,
The poor fool took a wife! –
She whispered, almost to herself,
And smiled — a terrible, twisted smile.
Gypsy
Where are you from, young woman?
Witch
Who, me?
When I was young — they kissed my face.
Now I’m old — I’d beg for grace
Of just one kiss, but none would dare.
Gypsy
A voice like that — so rich and rare!
To have a woman such as you,
And one with a bear, too!
Witch
I sing —
Whether I sit or roam or spin —
I always sing, I always sing…
I’ve even forgotten how to speak.
But once I spoke so well and clear.
Gypsy
Where were you then? What brought you here?
Witch
Who, me? Hush… hush…
The master lies with his own child,
The fire’s out, the moon climbs wild,
A werewolf grazes down the hollow…
I drank too much before my wedding —
And no one took me for the bedding.
It’s all those cursed lords’ misdeeds,
Who use young girls to sate their needs…
Another son — he must be wed,
Without me, they’ll be misled
And lay him in the grave instead.
Gypsy
Don’t go, poor soul — stay here with us.
We swear, with us life’s generous.
Witch
Do you have children?
Gypsy
None at all…
Witch
Then whom do you feed when the night falls?
Whom do you lay to sleep with care?
Whom do you rock when dreams are near,
When you lie down and rise again?
    </string>
    <string name="031">
Whom do you pray for? Oh — the children!
Always children, always children!
And I have nowhere to escape —
Wherever I go, they follow my shape.
They’ll eat me whole one day, I know.
Gypsy
Don’t cry, poor soul, don’t sink so low —
We’ve never had a child at all…
Witch
Then better to leap from a cliff and fall…
She wept, she wept with bitter wailing.

The gypsies watched her, long amazed,
Until they slept, where they had stayed.
But she — she neither wept nor slept.
She sat, her feet buried deep
In hot ash by the fire’s glow.
A crescent moon, chipped and low,
Peeked out beyond a burial mound
And stared upon the tent around
Until the clouds had cloaked the sky.

Why can’t the wealthy sleep at night —
Gray-haired, full-bellied, plush with pride?
Why can’t the poor old orphan sleep,
With nothing left in life to keep?
One schemes how best to buy the bell
To toll his name where sermons dwell.
Another hopes the time flies faster
To finish building up his castle.
“Then I shall rest!” — but in the grave.
The other — nowhere — finds his end,
Forgotten, not a thought to lend.
Both rest in sleep, so unaware,
No one remembers the poor man’s care.
And the rich man they still curse.

The old one cannot sleep in field or home —
But still must drag his days alone.
Beside the fire the old gypsy
Dozes, pipe between his teeth,
And stares at the stranger lost —
Is he perhaps lost in thought?
Gypsy
Why not lie down and get some rest?
The morning star is rising — look!
Witch
I look. You look. That is enough.
    </string>
    <string name="032">
Gypsy
At dawn we’ll move. If you’re not up…
Witch
I’ll never sleep again.
Never again will slumber come —
I’ll die like this, somewhere alone,
In weeds grown wild…
O forest deep, O forest dark,
O quiet Danube’s flowing spark,
Let me walk your hush awhile,
And in your waters cleanse my trial.
In greenest moss I’ll lie,
And rest a little by and by…
And maybe birth — though foul — some child,
It matters not, so long as wild
It runs and learns to curse my name.
There! — there! — do you see, on the grave
A kitten blinks its wicked eye —
That one is mine… Pussy… come nigh…
It won’t — the devil’s spawn won’t budge!
I’d let it drink, I’d let it gorge,
And by next year it’d know…
Kutia* waits upon the shelf,
While in the stove lie crying elves.
I bore them all, I raised them all,
But now have nowhere left to crawl.
Should I drown them?
Should I smother them in bed?
Sell them to a Jew for blood,
And drink away the price instead?
How well our kind take after me —
That’s what they say! But don’t you see?
Come — sit closer by the flame,
I’ll tell you more. You’ve heard my name?
I too lived in Wallachia!
I birthed twins in Bendery town,
In white Iasi I rocked them down,
In Dunavets I gave them baths,
In Turkey swaddled them in cloths,
Then carried them back home, to Kiev.
No incense, no priest’s holy weave —
Three coins I tossed for baptism,
Then drank the rest in drunken rhythm.
I drank… I drank,
And still I drink —
And sleep will never find me now.
For I have even lost the fear of God.
    </string>
    <string name="033">
I’m not ashamed before the world.
If only I could find my children—
Do you know, is there a war
Somewhere in Turkey?

Gypsy
There once was. No more.
The eldest officer has died.

Witch
I thought it was in Turkey—
But no, not even there.
Now listen, I’ll tell you
Whom I’m searching for.
I search for little Natalka
And my son Ivan,
But most of all I search
That cursed master…
To strangle him! For he took me
In my youth,
Shaved my hair like a boy’s,
Dragged me everywhere—
We were in Bender then,
With the soldiers. The soldiers
Were fighting the Turk.
Just before the Savior’s Day,
I bore twins.
And he, the damned, left me,
Didn’t step inside—
Went off with the troops.
And I, with bastard babes,
Returned to Ukraine
Barefoot, shaven. No matter.
I wandered, asking,
All the way to Kyiv…
And people laughed at me!
I nearly drowned myself,
But I couldn’t cast off
The twins. Somehow, somehow
I reached my homeland.
Rested… waited for dusk—
Then crept to the village,
Hoping no one would know.
</string>

    <string name="034">
I crept up to the cottage—
No light inside.
I thought my father slept…
But no, my father died.
No one to fold his arms!
I was struck with terror—
The house stank, empty.
I hid
My twins inside the granary,
Rushed into the room,
He was barely breathing.
I cried, “Father!
Father, it’s me! I’ve come!”
I grabbed his hands—
He took mine in his
And whispered, “I forgive you…
Forgive you… and…”
That was all I heard.
I think I fainted.
If only I had slept
Forever from that moment!

At midnight I awoke—
Something stirred in the dark…
Father gripped my hand.
“Father!” I screamed. “Father!”
But he was cold as ice—
I barely pulled free.
So, gypsy—
If you had such a daughter,
Would you forgive?

Gypsy
I would, by God.

Witch
Be quiet, lest I forget.
I prayed to God…
No, I didn’t—
I fed the children,
Hid them in the bin,
I even padded my headdress
So they wouldn’t see I was shaven.
I dressed up, walked around
While the people built a coffin
In the yard.
They finished, laid him in,
Carried him off, and buried him…
</string>

    <string name="035">
And I alone, like a finger,
Was left in this world.
I crossed the ravine,
Carried water,
Kneaded the bread myself,
Gave away my daughter,
Married off my son!
And… Hu…

Gypsy
Don’t moan—you’ll wake them all!

Witch
I’m not moaning, devil!

Gypsy
Fine, fine—what happened next?
Go on, tell the rest.

Witch
What will you give me?
Will you cook some mamalyga tomorrow?
I’ll bring corn…
Wait, let me recall.
He lay with my daughter!
Took my son as a lackey…
They drove me out—
Yes, yes, I remember.
I teased dogs
With beggars outside windows,
Carried my twins
On my back—to get them used to it.
Then the master came.
That’s when the whole village
Made a fuss
So I wouldn’t be cast out
Of my father’s home.
He took me with the twins
To his manor house.

The twins grew up,
And I rejoiced.
And again I loved
That venomous snake.
Loved him to ruin—
My son a lackey—
Destroyed… and with my daughter!
With his own!
Tell me, is that not sin?
Is this how your kind lives too?
</string>

    <string name="036">
He gave me a ruble
And sent me to Kyiv.
“Go pray to God,” he said—
And so I went,
And I prayed… No, gypsy,
I prayed in vain.
Do you have a God of some sort?
We do not!
The lords stole Him—
Locked Him in their caskets.

I came home—
The rooms were shut.
The lord had gone with my daughter,
As once he went with me.
And took my son too… Then… then…
God knows what happened.
I dreamed
I flew over ravines
Like an owl, seeking children…
No, don’t listen—I wasn’t
Looking for the children,
I sought the master.
But now there’s no need—
I’ll join the gypsies.
I’ve married off my son,
And my daughter—she’ll manage.
She’ll crawl by the fences
Until people trample her down.

Have you seen my son?
So handsome—
Like you. Ooh, it’s cold!
Lend me some money…
I’ll buy a fine necklace
And hang you with it.
Then I’ll go home…
Look—see that mouse?
She’s dragging her babies
To Kyiv. She won’t make it—
She’ll drown.
Or the master will take them!
Will I ever find my children,
Or perish in vain?

And she fell silent, like asleep.
The gypsies rose,
Took down their tent,
Set out on the road,
And marched into the steppe.
</string>
    <string name="037">
And the witch stood up,
And followed after them alone,
Singing as she roamed:
“They say a Judgment Day will come —
But judgment now is done,
For all the world has judged me here
Beneath this very sun.”

They wandered on, beyond the fields,
Through gardens, through the green,
And oddly, led behind them
A stray they’d somehow gleaned.
She sang and danced, yet never ate,
No drop passed through her lips —
As though death walked the earth itself
In Roma caravan's midst.

But then she came to life again,
Drank water, broke her fast,
Hid behind the tents to pray
And found her peace at last.
Old Mariula cured her soul
With herbs from secret troves,
And taught her every root and leaf
And what each potion drove.
How to brew, to heal with hands —
She learned with fervent care,
And even the stray followed suit
In prayer and in prayer.

Two summers thus they wandered on,
She learned the healing art,
And in the third, they journeyed home
Together at the heart.
She bowed to Mariula’s feet
In thanks for all she gave,
Bid farewell to the Romani,
To God her prayer she gave,
And headed home, her native land —
</string>

    <string name="038">
Joyful, cheerful, light of step,
Like a little child.
Where she passed through village paths,
She'd ask the sick and mild
What ailed them, then with healing herbs
She’d bring relief and rest.
That autumn, home at last she came
And lit her empty nest.
She plastered walls and swept the hearth,
Restored her ruined home,
And breathed with ease — as though in Heaven,
No more to drift or roam.

She had forgotten all the pain —
The sorrow, grief, and spite.
She loved all souls, forgave all wrongs,
Her heart was full of light.
She floated like a holy ghost
Above the village earth,
And in her modest, quiet home
She found a second birth.
The neighbors no longer shunned her,
The whole village adored her,
For day and night she walked the sick,
Asked nothing for her labor.
And if she took a coin, at most —
She’d give it to the poor,
Or light a candle on the eve
To Christ our Savior pure.
"For what do I need riches now?
Do I have children left?"
And saying this, she'd weep again,
Alone, with all bereft.

But girls would come to tend her house,
To cook and sweep and stay,
And never asked her spells or charms —
They loved her anyway.
Her little hut was clean and still —
</string>

    <string name="039">
So bright, it felt like Paradise.
The door would softly squeak —
And never once did folk pass by
Without a word to speak.
One would greet her with a smile,
One ask herbs to borrow,
One would bring a little loaf,
Another — cakes tomorrow.
She’d share with all her humble joys,
With love that had no end.
Thus she lived — warm, fed, and clothed —
And loved by every friend.
Respected too, yet all the same,
They still called her “witch,” in shame.

One spring they brought the master back —
With gout and cushions thick,
And German doctors — three or more —
To cure what made him sick.
But where were now his children? Lost!
His daughter for a hound was sold,
His son was lost in cards, we're told.
(Such things in life unfold —
But what are we to do with it?)

They tried to treat him, every way,
But still his soul would slip away.
They prayed, they wept, yet he would groan —
His sin too deep, his time was shown.
But mercy stirred her once again —
She brewed a holy healing tea,
And kindly walked from town to town
To offer her old enemy
A balm to ease his final breath.
She begged the doctors, pled and swore
He’d live! But they would not allow —
They cursed her from the door.
So she turned back with her small jar,
Recalling children gone afar...
</string>

    <string name="040">
She wept… and then she felt a pang
That she had failed to save him.

Spring chased winter from the fields,
And spread a carpet green.
From distant lands the cranes returned
In V-patterned flight serene.
And ox-drawn wagons crossed the steppe
To distant Don once more —
On land and sky, all seemed so bright,
What more could man implore?
Yet still that sinner, unforgiven,
Refused to die in peace.
They’d given him the sacrament,
Unroofed the home at least.
He lay on straw, with ceiling gone,
But could not meet his end!
And when a moment eased his pain,
He whispered: “Call her… send…”

He shook with fear. They led her in —
My witch — into the hall.
The doctors bowed, begged her to heal,
And help the master’s fall.
She knelt beside him silently
And prayed, beneath her breath,
“Forgive this man, O Lord,” she said,
“And bring him gentle death.”
The master stirred as from a dream
And glanced around the room,
Then saw her face — and screamed aloud:
“No! Don’t come! Not you!
Go! Wait… Don’t go — forgive me, please,
Have you not forgotten?”
Tears welled up, the very first
From eyes once proud and rotten.
She whispered, “I forgive you all…
Long ago I did…”
</string>

    <string name="041">
She placed a candle in his hands
And crossed him as he bid.
The sinner slept — as quiet, sweet
As children in a bed.
And for his soul, she stayed to pray
Though love and trust had fled.

She paid for prayers in every church,
To Kyiv she did go,
And begged the Lord to rest his soul
Who once had been her foe.
By autumn she returned again
To spend the winter there.
The village girls all welcomed her
With kindness, warmth, and care.
They came again at break of day
To help and sit nearby,
And served her well, like to a mom —
Not once would question why.

And she would teach them how to live,
How best to walk the land.
She told them of her girlhood days,
How love had turned her hand.
How she had loved a noble man
And bore his hidden shame,
How with her twins she wandered far
And no one knew her name.
How Mariula, wise and kind,
Taught her the healing trade.
She told them everything that was,
Each wound, each choice she made.
The girls would weep, then cross themselves
As if a ghost passed by,
But she would warn them tenderly:
“Don’t love the lords who lie!
For God will judge — and you will roam
Like I have done — alone.”
</string>
    <string name="042">
You’ll forsake your mother, father—
As I did, and lost them.
Your own children, shamed and mocked,
You’ll cast to wander,
Just as I... as I once did...
O my children! children!

That’s how she warned them.
The girls crossed themselves,
Cried, and dreamt at night
Of lords with horns and tails,
Who’d shear their braids,
Then bite and laugh and jeer,
And bare-headed,
Turn them into dogs or worse,
Dip them into pitch,
Then lead them through the village square
To draw a crowd and stare.
Such were their dreams—
Yet still they came at daybreak.

Then spring arrived, all green.
The old crone rose
And went into the fields for herbs—
But never came back.
The girls cooked dinner, supper too,
But did not know
Where their cruel foster mother went.
The village herdsmen said
That near a grave
In a puddle, devils crushed
The old witch dead.
They found her, buried her
Without a priest,
And drove a wooden aspen stake
Into her grave.
And the girls adorned it
With garlands of wildflowers.
</string>

    <string name="043">
And watered the aspen
With their tiny tears.
From the grave a cursed
Aspen tree grew tall.
That’s where the witch now lies.
Cross yourselves, girls!
Cross yourselves and never rush
To court a cunning lord—
You’ll perish mocked and scorned,
Bringing shame upon your name.

“For what, when I was growing,
Did people hate me so?
And why, once I had blossomed,
Did they strike the final blow?
Why now do they greet me
In palace halls,
Call me a princess,
And never drop their gaze
From my bloom? They marvel,
Don’t know where to place me!
Tell me, my dear brother,
O Flower of the Crown!”
“I do not know, dear sister.”
And the Flower of the Crown
Bowed his crimson-pink
Head toward the pale
And drooping face
</string>

    <string name="044">
Of Lileya.
And Lileya wept,
With tears like dewdrops…
She wept and spoke:
“My brother, though we’ve long
Loved one another,
I never told you—
I was once a human,
And suffered dearly.

My mother… why did she
Always look so sorrowful?
She stared and stared at me,
Her little child, and wept.
I never knew why,
Dear brother, only you!
Who brought her grief?
I was still just playing,
Just a child.
But she withered more each day,
And cursed our wicked master.
Then she died. And the master
Took me for his ward.
I grew up, was raised
In white palaces,
Never knowing I was a bastard,
His own child.
The master left and vanished.
He left me there alone.
The people cursed him,
Burned his house…
And me—why, I do not know—
They did not kill.
They only cut my long hair off,
Covered my shorn head
With rags—and laughed.
Even the unclean Jews
Spat at me.
That was my life, my brother.
My brief, young life—
They did not let me live it.
</string>

    <string name="045">
People of this world! I died
One winter, by a fence,
And bloomed again in spring
By the valley’s edge,
A flower white as snow—
So white, the woods rejoiced.
In winter, people… O my God!
Wouldn’t let me in their home.
But in spring, as if amazed,
They came to gaze at me.
Girls made wreaths of me
And started calling me
Lileya, Snow-Blossom;
And I began to bloom
In groves, in greenhouses,
And in palace halls.
So tell me, my dear brother,
O Flower of the Crown,
Why did God make me bloom
In this cruel world?
To bring joy to those same people
Who once killed
Me—and Mother? Merciful
Holy Lord above!”
And Lileya wept,
And the Flower of the Crown
Bowed down his crimson head
Upon her pale
And drooping face.
</string>

    <string name="046">
“My mother gave me birth
In lofty palace halls—
And in the dead of night
She took me to the Dnipro's waters.
While bathing me, she whispered:
‘Float, float, my daughter,
Down the river's flow.
And rise a rusalka
Tomorrow night.
I’ll walk with him then—
You’ll tickle him to death!
Tickle him, my heart,
Let him no longer mock
Me, a young wife.
Let him drink and drink
Not my blood-tears,
But Dnipro’s blue water—
Let him live with his new daughter.
So float, my only one!
Waves—my waves!
Welcome the little rusalka…’”
She wailed and fled.
And I—floated on downstream,
Until my sisters found me,
And took me in their fold.
It’s been a week now—
We roam the midnight fields.
But from the palace,
I still search for Father.
Has he perhaps made peace
With the master of the house?
Is my sinful mother
Once more basking in luxury?”
So spoke the little rusalka—
Then vanished in the Dnipro,
Like a silver minnow.
And the willow branch
Swayed gently in the breeze.
</string>
    <string name="047">
    A mother went out for a stroll,
    No sleep in the palace halls for her.
    Master Yan was not at home,
    There was no one to talk with her.
    And when she came to the riverbank,
    She then remembered her daughter,
    And recalled how she had bathed her,
    And the words she had murmured.
    But no matter. She went on her way
    To the palace, to sleep.
    But she did not make it, she had
    To spend the night in the Dnieper.
    And she did not notice, how they met her,
    The Dnieper maidens –
    They came to her, seized her,
    And began to play with her,
    Overjoyed that they had caught her,
    They played, they tickled,
    Until into a fish-trap they shoved her…
    And then they burst out laughing.
    Only one little mermaid
    Did not laugh.

    I was thirteen.
    I was herding the lambs beyond the village.
    Was it the sun that shone so brightly,
    Or was it something else with me?
    I felt so lovely, so lovely,
    As if I were with God... . . . . . .
    They had already called us to share the meal,
    But there I was in the weeds
    Praying to God... And I do not know,
    Why for me, a little one,
    It was so pleasant to pray then,
    Why there was so much joy.
    The Lord's sky, and the village,
    The lamb, it seemed, was joyful\!
    And the sun warmed, it did not burn\!
    But the sun did not warm for long,
    I did not pray for long...
    It began to burn, it turned red
    And set paradise on fire.
    </string>
    <string name="048">
    As if I awoke, I look:
    The village has turned black,
    God's blue sky
    Has also grown dim.
    I looked at the lambs –
    They are not my lambs\!
    I turned to the houses –
    I have no house\!
    God gave me nothing\!..
    And the tears gushed,
    Heavy tears\!.. And a girl
    Right by the road
    Not far from me
    Was gathering hemp,
    And she heard that I was crying.
    She came, she greeted me,
    She wiped my tears
    And kissed me...
    As if the sun had begun to shine,
    As if everything in the world had become
    Mine... the meadows, the groves, the gardens\!..
    And we, joking, drove
    Someone else's lambs to the water.
    Nonsense\!.. And yet to this day, when I remember,
    My heart weeps and aches,
    Why the Lord did not let me live out
    My short life in that paradise.
    I would have died, plowing the field,
    I would have known nothing of the world.
    I would not have been a fool in the world.
    I would not have cursed people and ....
    </string>
    <string name="049">
The sun won’t warm on foreign ground,
Yet home’s a blaze too fierce to bear.
No joy I found, no ease was there,
Even on Ukraine’s glorious sound.
No one to love me, none to greet,
I leaned on none, my heart withdrew,
I wandered, prayed to God anew,
And cursed the lords with bitter heat.
I recalled the bitter, wretched years,
The grim, old days of cruel design,
When Christ was hung in Palestine,
And Mary’s son would find no tears.
No joy for me, no matter where,
And likely never shall there be,
Not here, good folk, in liberty,
Nor there, in exile’s cold despair.
I’d wish… but only this, no more:
That Moscow’s hands might cease to hew
Coffins from trees on foreign shore,
Or bring a pinch of earth, so true,
From my dear Dnipro’s holy bank,
Borne by sacred winds to me.
That’s all I’d ask. But why, good folk,
Dream dreams that never can abide?
Why trouble God when, by our yoke,
Things won’t turn out as we decide.
</string>
    <string name="050">
My mountains, lofty, rise in grace,
Not steep, but fair, serene, and wide,
So lovely, radiant, soft with pride,
Their azure gleams from distant space.
From old Pereiaslav’s storied mound,
From Vybla’s grave, more ancient still,
Like clouds that rest beyond the hill,
They sit where Dnipro’s waters sound.
I walk with quiet, measured tread,
And look—before my eyes unfold,
As if from dreams, wonders untold:
From misty veils they rise ahead,
High cliffs, green groves, and ravines deep;
White cottages peek through the green,
Like children in their shirts serene,
At hide-and-seek in valleys steep.
Below, our grizzled Cossack friend,
The Dnipro, sparkles with the plain.
And there, beyond, where hills ascend,
A tiny church, like chapel’s reign,
A Cossack shrine in humble state.
</string>
    <string name="051">
A cross leans low, its shadow worn,
It stands and waits, through time forlorn,
For Zaporozhets from the plain…
It speaks with Dnipro, soft refrain,
To ease the heart’s unyielding pain.
With ancient banks, like eyes of green,
A corpse that from its grave has seen,
It gazes on the world’s wide scope.
Do you await revival’s hope?
Dream not of glory’s fleeting flame!
Your people, robbed, bear loss and shame,
While cunning lords… why should they heed
The Cossack glory’s mighty creed?
And Trakhtemyriv, piled on high,
Its ragged huts strewn ‘neath the sky,
Like bags a drunken beggar spills.
And there, Monastyryshche’s hills,
Once Cossack village, bold and free—
Was it the same in history?
All lost to tsars in cruel delight:
Zaporizhzhia, village bright,
The holy cloister, treasure’s store—
All plundered by the greedy core!
And you, O hills, gave way, gave all!
May cursed eyes ne’er see your fall!
No, not you cursed… but hetmans’ greed,
Foul Poles, usurpers’ wretched breed!
Forgive me, lofty ones, I plead!
You highest, bluest, holy breed!
The finest in the world’s wide span!
Forgive! I’ll kneel to God’s command…
So deep I love my Ukraine’s plight,
I’d curse the holy God in sight,
And for her soul, my soul I’d give!

Above Trakhtemyriv, steep and lone,
A hut stands like an orphan’s moan,
As if to sink in Dnipro’s flow…
It gazes on the land below,
On Hetmanshchyna’s boundless round.
Beneath, a gray-haired grandsire’s found,
The sun sinks low o’er Dnipro’s stream.
He sits, he looks, lost in a dream,
And tears fall soft… “Alas, alas!”—
He speaks, his voice a mournful mass—
“You fools! You’ve wrecked God’s paradise!
O Hetmanshchyna!” His clouded brow
Falls heavy, darkened now…
</string>
    <string name="052">
Perhaps some heavy, grievous word
His heart had longed to speak, and stirred.
Yet silent stayed…
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
“I’ve wandered far through this wide world,
In peasant’s coat, in noble’s fur…
What need of grief beyond the Urals,
For Kirghiz folk? Yet even there,
By God, life’s sweeter, free from care,
Than ours on Ukraine’s burdened sod.
Perhaps because they know not God,
Nor Christ’s own creed?...
O Christ, what woe you’ve wrought!
And changed what? God’s own folk?
Our Cossack heads, for truth they rolled,
For Christian faith, their blood was sold,
They drank of foreign blood and ours!...
And did they mend? No, worse by far!
Without a blade or burning pyre,
They chained mankind in shackles dire
And torture still… O lords, O lords,
You Christian lords!”…
My gray-haired sage, by sorrow beat,
His wild old head sank low in defeat.
The evening sun lit groves with gold,
The Dnipro and fields in light enrolled,
Mazepa’s church gleams, pure and white,
Bohdan’s old grave dreams in the light,
By Kyiv’s path, bent willows sway,
Three ancient mounds in brotherhood lay.
With Trubailo, Alta joins hand,
Like brother, sister, bound by land.
And all this beauty cheers the eye,
Yet hearts still weep, and turn aside!
The bright sun bids the dark earth adieu,
The round moon rises, with starlight’s hue,
They step from clouds, the skies grow bright…
My old man looked, and tears took flight…
“I pray to you, O gracious Lord,
Great God above, my soul’s accord!
You spared my life from ruin’s sting,
O Heavenly King.
You gave me strength to bear my woe,
And led me, old, to hills that glow,
To live my lonely days in praise,
To sing your glory’s sacred rays,
</string>
    <string name="053">
And with your beauty, Let my heart rejoice…
And bury the one broken By human sins, Upon these lofty hills,
To soar above them…

He wiped away his warm tears, Though his youth had faded…
And recalled his years, The distant, blessed years…
Where, how, when—what had happened? What was real, what was dreamed?
What seas had he crossed?

The dark green grove, The young marigold, The moon shining with stars,
The nightingale on the viburnum— Now silent, now singing,
Praising the Holy God. And all of it, all of it - Ukraine!

The old man smiled… For perhaps, if truth be told,
There was a time of courtship, Yet they parted, never wed,
She left him to live alone, To grow old in his cottage…

My old man grew sorrowful again, Wandered long around his home,
Then prayed to God, And went inside to sleep. The moon veiled itself in clouds.

Such was the dream I had in exile! As if once more I was free,
Born anew into the world. Oh, grant me, Lord, someday, Even in old age,
To stand upon those stolen hills, In a humble little house.

Though my heart is weary, Worn by sorrow,
Let me bring it and lay it down Upon the hills of the Dnipro.
    </string>
    <string name="054">
Once the Swedes made great fame, Fleeing with Mazepa To Bender from Poltava.
And behind them, Gordienko…

A mother’s wisdom told them How to reap the wheat, How to take Poltava.

Oh, they would have reaped, Had they stood united,
Had they joined the Hetman With the colonel of Fastiv.

Spears would not have pierced The roof of Peter’s kin,
Nor would the noble sons Have fled from Khortytsia,
Nor would the cruel colonel Have stopped them in Pryluky…

The Mother of God Would not have wept in Crimea For Ukraine.

As they wandered day and night,
As the Cossacks abandoned The Great Meadow and Mother Sich,
They took the Mother of God, And nothing more,
Carrying her to the Khan in Crimea, To the new sorrow of Zaporizhzhia.

A black cloud overtook The white one, A wicked Tatar Oppressed the Cossacks.

Though the Khan allowed them To settle upon the sands, He forbade them
To build a church.

In a tent, they placed The image of the Holy One, And prayed in secret…
Oh, my God, with you!

My land, so splendid, rich, and fair! Who has not tormented you?
If one were to tell The true tale of a single magnate,
It would frighten even hell itself.

And our ruined noble Would astonish old Dante. And all this suffering,
They say, comes from God!

Does He truly delight In tormenting people? And especially my poor Ukraine.
What has she done? Why does she perish?
Why do her children Remain silent in chains?

The kobzars told us Of wars and strife, Of bitter hardship,
Of cruel punishments.
    </string>
    <string name="055">
The Poles inflicted suffering— They told us everything.
And what happened after the Swedes? Even they were afraid!

Struck dumb with terror, The blind wretches.

Thus did the voivodes, Peter’s hounds, Tear and gnaw at her…
And from afar, The Cossacks heard—

The bells tolling in Hlukhiv, The cannons roaring.
How they drove them to the marshes To build a city.
How the old mother wept For her lost children.

How the little ones dug trenches By the Orel,
And how in Finland’s snow They perished.

The Cossacks heard, From distant Crimea,
That the Hetmanate was fading, Dying unjustly.

They heard, they heard, But remained silent. For even in exile,
The Murzas tormented them.

The poor souls suffered, They wept, and with them
The Mother of God Wept holy tears.

She wept with mercy, As if for her son. And God beheld those tears,
Those pure tears!

He struck down Peter, Struck down the tyrant Upon the road of fate.

The Cossacks returned,
Bringing with them To the Hetmanate That wondrous image Of the Holy One.

They placed it in Irzhavytsia, Within a stone temple.
And there she still weeps, For the Cossacks.
    </string>
    <string name="056">
O thoughts of mine! O wicked glory!
For you, I'm tormented in a foreign land,
Suffering, but not repenting!
I love you like a faithful wife,
Like my unfortunate Ukraine!
Do what you will with me, dark one,
Just don't abandon me, I'll hobble with you to hell...

You welcomed Neron the fierce,
Sardanapalus, Herod, Cain, Christ, Socrates,
O depraved one! You loved the bloody Caesar
And the good Greek equally...
Because they paid...
What will I, a poor man, bring?
For what will you kiss me, a gray-haired man?
For my songs-thoughts?..
Oh forest, forest!
Even those not like me sing for nothing.
It's strange and dull, when I think about it,
That often heads roll for that wonder!
Like dogs, brothers fight with brothers,
And they don't come to their senses.
And that wonder, loved by all:
A covered girl in a tavern, and people drunk!
When we were Cossacks,
And Unia wasn't heard,
That's when we lived happily!
We fraternized with free Poles,
We were proud of the free steppes,
We loved in gardens, we bloomed,
Like lilies, girls.
A mother was proud of her sons,
Free sons... They grew,
Grew up sons and gladdened
Old sorrowful years...
Until with the name of Christ
Priests came and set fire
To our quiet paradise. And they spilled
A wide sea of tears and blood,
And orphans in Christ's name
Were tortured, crucified...
Cossack heads bowed,
Like trampled grass,
    </string>
    <string name="057">
Ukraine weeps, groans and weeps!
Head after head
Falls to the ground.
The executioner rages,
And the priest with a mad tongue
Shouts: "Te Deum! Alleluia!.."
That's how it is, Pole, friend, brother!
Insatiable priests, magnates
Divided us, led us apart,
And we would still live like that.
Give your hand to the Cossack
And give your pure heart!
And again in Christ's name
We'll renew our quiet paradise.
In Kyiv, on the Podil,
It was once... And never
Will what happened return,
Will not return... And I, brother,
Will still hope,
Will still look out,
Causing sorrow to the heart.
In Kyiv, on the Podil,
Our brotherly freedom
Without a serf and without a lord,
Herself in a sheepskin coat,
Unfurled joyfully,
Lays out paths with velvet,
And covers with silk,
And doesn't turn to anyone.
In Kyiv, on the Podil,
Cossacks are having fun.
    </string>
    <string name="058">
Like water poured from pail to bowl,
They spill the wine in streams that flow.
The cellars, taverns, barmaids bright,
With wines and meads in warm delight,
The Zaporozhians seize and drain,
And clink their mugs in loud refrain.
The music roars, it leaps, it plays,
And cheers the crowd through festive haze.
But from the Brotherhood, the bursaks stand,
Mute watchers from their scholar’s land.
No freedom for the school’s bare hall,
Or they’d join in and please them all…
Who’s that the throng, with music’s swell,
Encircles now? What tales to tell?
In crimson velvet breeches grand,
He sweeps the street with matron’s hand.
A Cossack strides—O years, O flight!
What have you wrought?—Yet for this night,
The old man stamps his heels with glee,
Till dust clouds rise for all to see!
And still he sings, this Cossack bold:
—“A crab crawls down the road, behold,
Let it be so, let it be so!
If young maids sowed the poppy’s glow,
I’d give my heels a wicked thrall,
I’d give my heels, and that’s not all,
Some spark would linger, passed along!
My heels, they’ve borne such grief and wrong,
I’d give my heels a wicked thrall,
I’d give my heels, and that’s not all,
Some spark would linger, passed along!”—
He danced till Mezhihirsky’s gate,
The gray-haired man, unbowed by fate,
And all his comrades, Kyiv’s throng,
Holy and whole, they danced along.
He reached the gate, and cried aloud:
—“Hoo-hoo! Hoo-hoo! Monks pure and proud,
Greet your old friend from Luh’s wide plain!”—
The holy gate swung wide amain,
They welcomed in the Cossack’s frame,
Then shut the gate, and sealed his name
Forevermore. Who was this man,
Who left the world in joy’s brief span?
Semen Paliy, Zaporozhian true,
Unbroken by the woes he knew.
The sun climbs high, then sinks to rest,
A monk in long black robes is dressed,
He paces slow through cloister’s cell.
</string>
    <string name="059">
The monk to Vyshhorod ascends,
To gaze on Kyiv’s ancient trends,
Or sit upon the hill’s high crest,
To mourn his heart’s unquiet rest.
The monk to Dzwonkowa’s deep vale
Goes down to drink, where waters sail,
And thinks on how, in worldly strife,
He bore the weight of bitter life.
The monk to cloister’s silent keep
Returns, where voiceless walls stand steep,
And dreams of youth, of years long flown,
When life was his, and his alone.
He takes the holy writ in hand,
And reads aloud, as truths expand…
Yet far his aged thoughts take flight.
God’s words grow still, and in the night,
As if the Sich’s old brotherhood
Revives, their glory understood.
A gray-haired hetman, owl-like, stares
Into his eyes with piercing glares.
Music and dance, Berdychiv’s cheer,
Then chains that clang, Moscow’s cold sneer,
The Bory woods, the snows, Yenisei…
And tears from weary eyes comply,
They fall upon his robe in streams…
Beat down your flesh with fervent dreams!
Read holy writ, let bells resound,
But shun your heart—it led you round,
To Siberia’s shore, it lured you far,
Deceived you through each lifelong scar.
Now lull it still, forsake its plea,
Your Borzna, Fastiv—let them be!
All fades, you’ll fade as well,
No trace remains, no tales will tell…
The old man wept, his spirit broke,
He ceased to read the words he spoke.
He paced the cell, he paced, then sank,
And grieved:—“Why was I born to thank
This world, to love my Ukraine’s shore?”—
The matin bell began to roar
From belfry’s call. My monk arose,
Donned hood and staff, his heart’s repose,
He crossed himself, took beads in hand…
And limped to pray for his dear land.
</string>
    <string name="060">
“Pray, old man, and bow down low,
While children, small, are driven so
To tread the swamps in deep despair:
All’s vanity, this world’s thin air.
Pray, and bow your head once more!”

The monk for Ukraine’s soul implored,
He carved a cross, a coffin made,
Yet death delayed, its call evaded…
Until the cannon’s roar awoke
From Hlukhiv, shaking Ukraine’s yoke.

The monk, half-crossed, could pray no more,
He gazed to heaven, his spirit sore,
Murmured low, a groan, a sigh,
And sent his soul to God on high,
Then wed the coffin’s silent keep.

The bells wailed loud, their tolling deep,
Kyiv’s hills with mourners thronged,
Monks bore Semen Paliy along,
Like a hetman laid to rest.
And still, my brothers, east and west,
Paliy’s strongholds stand on Fastiv’s ground;
In bogs and vales, old cannons sound—
For what? None come to claim their might:

The hills of Fastiv, gripped by blight,
Its folk now toil for foreign priests;
At times, they speak of that old feast,
But where his grave, what land, what shore?
They know not, nor have heard before!
Kyiv saw, yet Kyiv forgot.

So it came, O Cossack sire!
Your slothful heirs let fade the fire,
Your freedom, glory, all undone.
Moscow razed Poltava’s ramparts won,
Tore down the Sich, the Savior’s gate,
And o’er your grave, they pound the slate.
</string>
    <string name="061">
We ask each other, lost in thought,
Why did our mother bring us forth?
For good? For ill? What fate is wrought?
Why live? What dreams do we pursue?
We die, unanswered, passing through,
And leave behind our deeds, uncaught…
What deeds, my gracious God, will weigh
Against me on this earthly stage?
If only children ceased to stray,
Nor roused your holy wrath each day,
Born in chains, their shame to bear,
And cast disgrace upon your care.

It’s strange to me. Where can I flee?
What path to take, what work to start?
To curse mankind and fate’s cruel art
Is vain, by God. How then to live
Alone in exile’s cold reprieve?
What work to do, in bonds confined?
If I could gnaw these chains, I’d find
A way to bite them, bit by bit.
But these aren’t chains that yield to grit,
Not forged by smiths to break apart,
Nor tempered so a mortal heart
Could rend them free. Woe to us all!
To orphans, slaves, in steppes that call
Beyond the Urals, vast and drear.
</string>
    <string name="062">
O ribbon joined to ribbon fine,
I weave my lace through three nights’ time,
I weave, I stitch, with care I blend,
On Sunday, free, I’ll dance and mend.
O scarlet shawl, so bright, so bold,
Look, maidens, marvel, young and old,
Gaze, lads, and let your eyes admire,
You Cossacks of the Zaporizhian fire.
O look, and court, and play your part,
But wed with others, break no heart.
The proffered towels, love’s sweet sign…
Such are the ways of Cossacks fine!

There was a lass, Kateryna named,
An orphan, luckless, fate untamed,
She grew in service, toiled, and thrived,
Till with Ivan her heart contrived.
And Ivan, like a dove, was true,
To his Kateryna, love anew.
From star to star, in twilight’s gleam,
They supped at widow’s hearth, a dream,
They talked, they laughed, till dawn’s first ray,
Awaiting Mary’s holy day.
They waited, while from Chyhyryn

Across our glorious Ukraine’s kin,
The mighty bells began to peal,
For lads to saddle steeds of steel,
To sharpen swords and sabers bright…
And ride to wed with war’s fierce rite.
</string>
    <string name="063">
A kerchief stitched with silken thread,
To call her to his heart, though fled,
His own Kateryna, far away.
On Sunday morn, ere break of day,
Before the sun could light the sky,
To war’s far road, to strife and cry,
A mother sent her son away.
Kateryna led Ivan, her stay,
From stranger’s darkened house to roam,
She bore his gear, his saber’s home,
His golden blade, his studded mail.

A sister bade her brother sail,
And for the orphan, gray and lone,
She led his horse, to waters shown,
She drew from well till starlight’s end,
She brought his gear—his saber’s friend,
His rifle, hooked, to battle’s call.
She walked three fields, three miles in thrall,
And parted where the valley lay.
She gave a kerchief, stitched to say
He’d think of her in lands unknown.
O kerchief, woven, silken sown!
So finely laced, so dearly made,
Yet only fit to cloak a saddle’s trade.
She turned, she grieved, her eyes forlorn,
She watched the road, by dust adorned.
She decked herself, with hope arrayed,
Each day she waited, undismayed.
And every Sunday, up she’d climb
To watch the mound, through endless time.
</string>
    <string name="064">
One summer fades, another dies,
And on the third, with eager cries,
The glorious company rides again
To their beloved Ukraine’s domain.
One army marches, then a second,
But for the third—O luckless maiden,
Look not!—they bring a bitter load:
A painted coffin, grief’s abode,
Draped in silk, so fine, so frail.
Behind it walks, in somber trail,
The Sich’s own colonel, stern and wise,
A sorcerer with knowing eyes.
The esauls, with tears that fall,
Follow slow in mournful call,
Bearing arms of Cossack pride:
A battered breastplate, scarred and tried,
A golden saber, gleaming still,
Three hook-rifles, wrought with skill,
Three pistols, proud… yet stained and dry
With Cossack blood that once did cry.
They lead a raven steed, forlorn,
Its hooves all shattered, bruised, and torn…
Upon it lies a saddle small,
A kerchief spread, to cloak it all.
</string>
    <string name="065">
Long ago it was, in school’s dim shade,
Beneath the deacon-teacher’s blade,
I slyly stole a five-kopeck coin—
My rags were thin, my want my own—
And bought a sheet of paper fair,
To craft a booklet, small and rare.
With crosses, blooms, and patterns fine,
I traced each leaf in careful line,
And copied there Skovoroda,
Or “Three Kings with Gifts” bestowed.
Alone in weeds, where none could hear,
I sang my lines with silent tear.
And now, in age, I hide once more
With verses, weaving as before,
To stitch my books, to sing, to cry
In tangled grass where none pass by.
My tears are heavy, and I know not
Why God’s own wrath has cast my lot.
In school I suffered, grew, and grayed,
In school my hair to silver strayed,
In school they’ll bury this old fool.
All for that coin I stole at school,
That five-kopeck from deacon’s hand—
Thus God’s own justice makes its stand.
</string>
    <string name="066">
Listen, my dove, my Cossack eagle!
Hear how I waste in bondage’s vigil,
How I wander, wretched, through the world.
Listen, brother, and teach your children,
Teach them well, let no young heart
Begin to weave the poet’s art.
But if one hastens to that call,
Then softly, brother, in some stall,
Let them versify and weep alone,
So quiet God won’t hear their moan,
Nor you behold their secret pain,
Lest they, like me, in chains remain.
For I, in exile, bear my due,
My brother, suffering as I do.
Like a thief, on Sundays, past the ramparts,
I steal to fields where freedom starts.
Beyond the Urals, through the grass,
I roam the steppe, as free men pass.
My battered, aching heart takes flight,
Like fish that gleam in water’s light,
It smiles a moment, soft and shy,
And soars, a dove, through foreign sky.
I live again, in field, in air,
And climb a hill, to stand and stare,
I dream of Ukraine, yet dread to dream.
The steppes here stretch, like those that gleam,
But these are not my homeland’s own—
Red-rusted, harsh, with sand and stone,
No mound to whisper tales of yore,
As if no folk had lived before.
From time’s beginning to this day,
A desert hid from man’s survey,
Yet we, alas, its bounds have found.
We’ve built our forts on barren ground,
And graves will follow, mark my word!
O fate! O land! When shall I flee
This wasteland’s grip, to liberty?
Or will I perish here, God save,
And find no rest beyond the grave.
</string>
    <string name="067">
The scarlet field grows black with dread…
—“To barracks! Back to bondage led!”—
A voice seems shouting o’er my head.
I wake, and creep, with thief-like tread,
Beyond the Urals, past the wall,
A skulking shade, in exile’s thrall.
Thus, my friend, I mark the day,
The holy Sunday’s fleeting play.
And Monday? Brother, hear my plea:
Night falls, the stinking hut shuts me,
And thoughts descend, they rend, they break
My heart a hundred times, and take
My hope, and that I cannot name…
They drive all joy to ash and shame.
Night stalls. The hours, like ages, crawl,
Through centuries, deaf to my call.
With blood-red tears, I drench my bed,
I count the days, the years I’ve bled.
Whom did I love? Where? When? What good
Did I bestow? None, where I stood,
As if I wandered woods alone!
I had my will, my strength was stone,
But debts wore down my vigor’s flame,
My freedom, drunk, lost in the game,
Strayed to St. Nicholas, and swore
To revel never, evermore.
No help, dear God, as mortals say,
Repentance comes, but not the way.
I pray for dawn, for sun, for light,
As if for freedom’s boundless sight.
The cricket stills; the reveille sounds.
I pray for dusk, when shame abounds,
They march this old fool out to drill,
To teach me freedom’s worth, to fill
My soul with blows that fools endure.
Youth’s years are gone, fate’s path is sure,
Yet hope, in chains, still clings to me,
</string>
    <string name="068">
Once more, misfortune grips my soul,
It wounds my heart with bitter toll.
Yet might I see some good again?
Or weep away this endless pain?
Drink Dnipro’s waters, clear and free,
And gaze, my friend, on you and me.
In your quiet hut, we’d share
Our words, our dreams, in soft repair.
I fear to ask myself, I dread—
Will this hope bloom, or lie long dead?
Perhaps from heaven’s distant height
I’ll see Ukraine, her radiant sight,
And you, my friend, in tender gaze.
At times, no tears can mark my days;
I’d beg for death to end my strife…
Yet you, Ukraine, and Dnipro’s life,
Its rugged banks, my hope, my friend,
Forbid my heart to seek that end,
To pray to God for death’s release.

To Y. Kukharenko
—“Not worth, by God, to live this way!”…
—“Then drown yourself!”—But wife, child, stay?
See, that’s the truth, don’t weave a lie!
Sit down, my friend, and let us try
To write this tale… Perhaps you’ll see
A different end, my dear, for me.
Write thus: there was
A village fair.
No need to roam to lands elsewhere,
Write: here, upon Ukraine’s own ground.
A widow lived, her life hard-found,
With daughter dear and son of seven.
Her wealth was children, gift of heaven,
She praised her God in humble grace…
But for the widow, poor and base,
No joy was hers—her lot was grim,
They poured hot tar upon her skin,
She nearly perished in their spite.
She thought to join the nuns, or flight
To drown herself—but love’s sweet call
For her small children stayed her fall.
A mother’s heart, what more to say?
Perhaps she dreamed a son-in-law’s day,
For Katrusia bloomed with youth.
Would she let girlhood waste, forsooth,
Her brows grow dim for naught at all?
No, this lass was not so small!
</string>
    <string name="069">
And in that village, toiling true
(For orphans oft are deemed askew),
An orphan grew in hired hand,
As if his father’s heir to land.
By this and that, he earned his keep,
Saved coins where others spent them deep,
He bought a coat, a fine zhupan,
And with his orphan’s meager plan,
No kin to claim from near or far,
He bought a garden, hut, to star
His thanks for bread, for salt, for care,
To folk who taught him, kind and fair.
Then straight to widow’s door he sped,
With towels pledged, his heart to wed!
No haggling with the elders came
(As lords might play their lofty game),
The priest, unswayed by wealth or pride,
For three kopecks joined them wide,
A marvel on a weekday done!
The widow’s eyes, once wet, now shone.
So live, my friend, and joy will spring,
It’s worth to live when love takes wing.
Though some may say, my dear, take heed:
Love self, and God will meet your need.
And when the time to die draws near?
To sigh o’er coins? No, friend, forbear!
Love is God’s grace, a holy spark!
Love wife, love children, from your heart;
Share with the poor your hard-won gain,
And lighter will your toil remain.

        1
Let’s pause a while, and talk, my friend.
Your barley—has it sprouted yet?
2
What barley? None has come to set!
My fields still plow for rye, you see.
1
That’s why your life’s a mystery!
Since when, dear uncle, did you hear—
Or heard and forgot, in passing year—
They print a journal now, my friend…
1
…Te! Te! Te!
2
What, you think it’s Polish blend,
Or Moscow’s “Master” in the end?
Not so! A journal called “The Roar”!
Or “La Mode,” bought for Pasha’s store
Last year in Romny…
1
…Softly: So our own!
2
I swear, I’ve lived and never known.
2
In that same journal, Pasha read
How Germans sowed their grassy bed.

1 Was: That’s why your life’s a mystery
2 Was: …Softly: Like our own!

With sickles then they reaped it down!
All writ in verse, from town to town,
Not like our rhymes, so plain, so crass…
1
If you, my friend, just herded ass…
Forgive my word, I spoke too free.
2
As if not hearing: Hey, young lad!
He whistles low, then sings, not sad:
Young lad, so bold,
With eyes of brown,
Why take a wife—
A stone to drown?
</string>
    <string name="070">
1
Enough of singing, let it rest.
2
What, ready now to end our quest?
I thought, in truth, you’d linger still…
1
I think another thought, until
We drink, we sleep, and lose our way.
Sit down, my friend, and write, I say,
Let’s end this tale, with God’s good grace.

The orphans wed, and folk did trace
Their union with a wond’ring stare:
How would these luckless souls now fare?
A year went by, another passed,
Again the village stood aghast:
Where did these orphans find such store?
In barn, in yard, on threshing floor,
In fields, their wealth did grow and thrive,
Their children bloomed, like flowers alive,
They strode in zhupans, proud and free,
Black-browed, a sight for all to see.
They called the poor to share their bread,
While rich folk came, no summons led.
Yet selfish hearts, with envy stung,
Begrudged the alms the orphans flung:
“Why feed the poor with such fine fare?
Sell what might rot, for children’s care!”
Hear now what envy’s poison breeds,
And hunger’s unrelenting needs.
They prowled, they grieved, till in the night,
With spiteful hearts, they set alight
The orphans’ home! Had lords so grand,
Enlightened, struck with cruel hand,
It might not sting; but no, alas,
A peasant’s rag, a lowly class,
Could rage so fierce. How hard, my friend,
To know men’s hearts at life’s late end.
Yet worse, in youth, to love a snake,
Whose charm with brown eyes’ gleam does wake…
You fool, forgot the death behind,
That lurks where serpent’s gaze does bind.

All burned to ash, to stalk, to ember,
The children lost in fire’s cruel number.
The rich rejoiced, their wealth increased,
The poor were glad—now equal, least!
The rich grew richer, so they smiled,
The poor, now matched, no longer reviled.
</string>
    <string name="071">
They gathered round to mourn and sigh,
To heap their grief, to amplify.
“What pity, pity! Had we known,
We’d saved a coin, a seed we’d sown,
It might have turned out otherwise…
But now, Maksym (for so they named him),
Sell off your stock, your beasts, your plow,
Come work for me, as fate allows.
We’ll chumak once again, my friend,
Till we rise up where others bend,
And then…” Maksym gave thanks for care,
“I’ll see what lies in future’s glare;
If I can’t mend my broken way,
Then to your hire I’ll turn, I say…
Where’s my Kateryna, my dear,
My black-browed love, to counsel here?…”
But that last counsel, ever true,
Will block his path, his heart undo.
Your oxen, cows, all died in dust,
And Kateryna, with soldiers’ trust,
Has wandered off, to who knows where!
Now write it thus, my friend, take care.
Maksym reflected, grieved, and prayed,
Twice called to God:—“O Lord, my aid!”—
And spoke no more, his voice was stilled.
From tsarina came word to wield:
“Shave heads for service, take them all.”
“You spared the widow’s drowning fall,
You’ll not let me with beggar’s call”—
Maksym spoke, and left his land.
The widow’s son, by village hand,
Was carted off to join the ranks.
Such dark deeds thrive in secret flanks
Upon this world! You learned should cry,
And yet you wail: “O God, O my!
Not worth to live beneath this sky!”
Why don’t the simple raise that plea?
2
Do they live at all? Do they know,
As you have said, love’s holy glow?
1
What’s that? My ears can’t catch your word…
2
They vegetate, I say, unheard,
Like cabbage sprouting in the field.
1
So that’s your view! Enough, let’s yield,
Let them not live, as you decree…
</string>
    <string name="072">
Yet I’ll speak plain, as you desire.
You keep them bound, you quench their fire,
For you live only for your gain,
With learned eyes shut tight in vain.
2
If we keep writing in this strain,
We’ll never end by evening’s wane.
Where’s that luckless son-in-law?
The widow’s son came home once more,
But her betrothed joined Moscow’s call.
None mourned him in the village hall,
They laughed instead, with cruel disdain!
In truth, I know not, nor can say,
If Kateryna e’er returned,
Or if she wandered, lost, and spurned.
A rumor spoke: in Uman’s streets,
They led her, shorn, for thieving feats,
Then drowned herself, or so they say…
But people lie, they slay, they flay!
Perhaps it’s truth as pears on trees.
I only know they sang of these,
At dawn’s first light, the maidens’ choir:
“Rustle, rustle through the grove,
Lads lost caps in love’s sweet rove,
Only the hired hand stood true,
He loved the widow’s daughter too…”
A shameful song, let woe be hers!
The years slipped by, in quiet burrs,
Write thus—and for their sins, the Poles
Were judged by God, and Pugach’s tolls
Rang o’er the Urals, fierce and free.
Poets in odes praised war’s decree
And tsarina’s might. But we, thank God,
Sat silent, safe in humble sod.
After great winter’s icy breath,
Maksym returned, lame, touched by death.
In march, he says, he lost his limb,
Yet earned a silver cross to hymn!
—“Why did he limp back to this place?
No hut, no kin, no friendly face.
Why come at all?”—Who knows his aim!
They say it’s easier to claim
Your death on homeland’s scorched terrain
Than in a foreign palace’s reign.
—“Heard that before?”—No, never so.
Come, uncle, let’s write swift and go,
For sleep now calls both you and me.
The soldier-cripple grieved his lot,
Where could he turn, what refuge sought?
The widow’s son in pikemen’s band,
The widow gone to death’s far land!
To whom could he now bend his knee?
Where winter through, where find his plea?
</string>
    <string name="073">
Autumn nears, soon winter’s rage
Will storm with frost, an icy cage.
His fate is lost, it fled to fields!
He begged to winter where he’d yield,
In deacon’s school, to find his place.
For soldiers taught him, by their grace,
To read and write, and in their way,
They wore, back then, as tales relay,
Gray braids with curls, each man the same,
Dusted with flour—God knows the game!
Maksym, as learned, would lend his hand,
On choir with deacon, take his stand,
Read Psalms o’er graves with solemn air,
And bear the schoolboys’ burdens there.
In Advent’s fast, the wretch would roam,
For Christ’s sake begging, far from home!
Write true, let no false word arise,
No ill was spoke by others’ eyes.
—“Both luck and loss,” he’d say, “are sent
From God above, His will is meant.”
He never groaned, nor shed a tear,
Like a child, his heart was clear.
No dog would bite this Maksym’s tread.
On Sundays, holy days, he’d shed
His rags, and limp to widow’s plot,
To see the ruin time forgot.
He’d sit within her garden’s shade,
Recall the widow, prayers he’d made,
For her poor soul he’d read the Psalms,
Kateryna’s health he’d name in alms,
Softly spoken, with tender care!
He’d wipe his tears—“All’s God’s to bear”—
And grow content, his spirit light.
In Peter’s Fast or Savior’s rite,
He’d leave the school, no rest he’d take,
With spade and shovel, he’d forsake
The walls, and limp to fields afar…
Guess not what this lame soldier bore:
Beside the path, in valley’s keep,
A well he dug, so clear, so deep!
That summer, they blessed the spring,
</string>
    <string name="074">
On Maccabeus’ day, they came,
And planted there an oak to claim
A mark for travelers passing by.
Next summer, children’s searching eye
Found Maksym, lifeless, in the glen,
Beside his well—he’d come again
To see it one last time, poor soul.
The village gathered, took their toll,
And buried him where valley lay,
Naming the well and glen, they say,
“Moskal’s,” for memory’s gentle sake.
On Savior’s Day or Maccabeus’ wake,
They bless the water, even now,
The oak still greens with leafy bough.
Who walks or rides will pause to rest
Beneath its shade, with water blessed,
And drinking deep, they speak his name,
Maksym, whose life outshone his fame.
Live thus, you fools, and life won’t fade.

They say a dog, once trained to chase
A cart, will run when sleighs replace.
So I now write, with ink and page,
Wasting my paper’s fleeting stage…
But once—by God, I speak no lie!—
A sight, a thought, would catch my eye,
I’d weave such verse, I’d weep outright,
And soar, if just an hour, in flight
To Ukraine’s fields, to see her face,
As if some good I’d done for grace,
My heart would rest in joy’s embrace.
To say I love her not, or curse
The foes who chain me, would be worse—
By God, my brothers, I forgive,
And pray to mercy’s God to live,
That you recall no ill of me.
Though I’ve not wronged you, I was free
Among you once, and something stays.
</string>
    <string name="081">
        158
        154
    </string>
    <string name="082">
Let’s weave our verses once again,
In secret, soft, as whispers blend,
While new thread spins on olden base,
We’ll gild God’s ancient truths with grace.
Or rather… how to speak, not lie?
Let’s curse again both fate and sky.

Curse fate for watching, never sleeping, 1
Yet never guarding those it’s keeping.
Curse men for greetings they bestow, 2
Yet scorn the hearts they’ll never know.
After 11a How not to curse, when poetry
Fades without salt, a tasteless sea?
Like borscht turned slop, without its fire,
Poems, too, perish—curse their pyre!


1 Was: Curse fate for never sleeping
2 Was: Curse men for greetings they bestow /414/


While seas still roar
And gnaw the cliffs with ceaseless might,
Shall I not weave once more
Some quiet word, some gentle light,
Of goodness born, to soothe the night?
</string>
    <string name="083">
Behind God’s door, an axe lay still.
(While God with Peter roamed at will,
Working wonders through the land.)
A Kazakh, sly, with thieving hand,
In stealth and quiet, soft as air,
Stole that axe for mischief’s share.
He hauled it to the verdant grove,
Chose a tree, and struck with love—
The axe flew free from reckless grip,
And woods became a reaper’s script.
A fearful sight, a mournful scene,
Great oaks and trees, so tall, so green,
Fell like grass in meadows wide.
From valleys rose a fiery tide,
Its smoke eclipsed the holy sun,
And darkness reigned, from Ural’s run
To Tyngiz, Aral, waters boiled,
Villages burned, and towns were spoiled.
Men wept, beasts howled, and far away,
In Siberia’s snows, they hid from day.
Seven years the axe of God did hew,
The blaze unquenched, the terror grew,
Till God’s own world was lost in gloom.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
On the eighth year, one Sunday morn,
Like a doll in lilies, newly born,
The holy sun rose clear and bright.
The steppe lay black, a gypsy’s plight,
Where towns or villages once stood—
No ember glowed, no ash withstood,
The wind had swept all trace away.
Yet one lone tree survived the fray,
Swaying green in the barren plain.
Red clay and cliffs mark the domain,
With thorns and thistles, sparse and dry,
And here, in gullies, sedge does lie
Beneath the hills, in shadows cast.
</string>
    <string name="084">
At times a wild Kazakh will ride
His weary camel to the side
Of that high hill, in silent tread.
A strangeness stirs, as if the dead
Or steppe itself to God would speak.
The camel weeps, the Kazakh, meek,
Bows low his head, and gazes long
On steppe and Kara-Butak’s song,
Recalls Syngychagach’s old tale,
Then slips from hill to clay-pale vale,
And vanishes in barren land.
One tree alone, by valley’s hand,
Stands tall beside the road’s rough way,
By God forsaken, come what may.
Untouched by axe, unscarred by flame,
It whispers to the vale of fame
From days long past, in quiet tone.
Kazakhs bypass this tree alone,
They pause within the valley’s keep,
Marvel at its form, and weep,
They pray and offer gifts sincere,
That shoots might spring in their frontier.
        . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
Wandering in exile’s cruel embrace,
I met an old man, marked by grace,
A varnak, settled, scarred by fate,
Our tortured kin, our shared estate.
Like children, joyed, we met that day,
And on a Sunday, far away,
By Ural’s banks, through tangled grass,
We spoke of glory’s distant past…
He shared his tale, his truth, his pain:
All comes from God, man’s work is vain,
A fool can claim no deed his own.
</string>
    <string name="085">
I, too, have squandered life, I see,
In vain, in waste, my years set free,
And blame no other for my fall…
Much water’s flowed since days of old.
Beyond Uman, that village cold,
Where I was born to curse and woe,
Where I grew up in luckless throe,
To ruin bound. Our lady there
Saw me and claimed me for her lair,
To serve within her chambers grand.
Her sons, my peers, a noble band,
Grew up as toys for their delight,
While I, their jest, endured their slight.
They learned, and I, with foolish head,
Joined in their books, though tears I shed,
And blood it cost to learn that art!
Cheaper than dogs in master’s heart—
To teach us letters? Us, the least?
To pray to God, to plow, at best,
Was all our lot, our fate’s decree!
Such is the serf’s eternity…
I learned, I grew, and sought my way,
I begged for freedom—none would sway.
To soldiers? No, they’d not conscript!
What’s left to do in this world’s grip?
Back to the plow I turned once more,
While lords’ sons joined the guard’s proud corps.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
Hard years descended, cruel and long!
In that same village, poor and wronged,
An orphan girl grew soft and fair…
O God, my only, hear my prayer!
She was a child in those sad days!
Not ours to judge Your holy ways,
Great God of ours, we bow to Thee.
</string>
    <string name="086">
I barely gazed upon her face,
Yet dreamed of marriage, love’s embrace,
To live, to rejoice, with her by side,
And praise the Lord in joyful tide.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
We bought the goods, we brewed the ale,
But fate forbade us to prevail,
No cup was raised, no toast was said.
The cursed old lord, with greed unbred,
Cast her as outcast through the land,
Our life together never planned.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
No matter… gone… no use to sow
A garden where no blooms will grow.
I turned to scribe for village needs,
This way, that way, a year proceeds.
I write, I bond with folk around,
And quietly seek the lads I’ve found.
Another year, then lords’ sons came,
On third year’s summer, none the same
(They knew me not, as was their way),
Betrothed, awaiting wedding day.
Our village maids could find no peace,
The lords’ sons hounded, gave no ease.
No matter, let them; mothers beam,
Lords revel… but the lads, they scheme,
Awaiting, like God’s will, that feast.
On Whitsun’s holy day, at least,
They wedded both, in Polish style,
Within their chapel, rank and guile—
For they were Poles… No sight more fair
Has God beheld on earth, I swear,
Than those young two in love’s bright glow.
Yet I—I slew them! I confess,
And still I shudder to profess;
I fear to speak, lest you take fright.
That wedding night…
We came, a horde, with vengeance sworn,
Set white-walled halls to flame and scorn,
Great lords and small, we cut them down,
</string>
    <string name="087">
The old dame prayed
For those young lives, her hands upraised
To God in fervent plea… while we,
The lads, with brides in cruel decree,
Toyed till their breath was stilled in pain.
The fire died, dawn broke again,
We hid in groves, and planned our course.
What course? To kill without remorse,
To torment lords, the damned, the vile.
We marched… O brother, it’s a trial
To call such deeds to mind once more…
Our band grew daily, night and morn,
Beyond a hundred, vengeance born…
Blood flowed like swine’s, a gruesome flood—
I carved through all of noble blood,
Without mercy, without hate,
I slew, and yet I cannot state
What drove my heart, what end I sought!
Three years I roamed with knife in thought,
A butcher, hardened to the core,
To tears, to blood, to fire’s roar—
I grew accustomed, numb to all.
A babe I’d roast on spear’s cruel call,
Or nail a black-browed maid, unclad,
To horse, and loose her, raving mad,
Across the steppe—such things I did…
Till all grew dull, my soul was rid
Of zeal. I wearied of the den,
Thought to turn knife upon my ken,
To end my wanderings, bleak and grim.
I would have done it… but a hymn,
A miracle, o’er me was cast…
At dawn’s first light, my blade held fast
Within my boot, from Brovary’s wood
I stepped, to spill my wretched blood.
I looked—and saw, as if in dream,
Great Kyiv’s holy spires gleam,
A miracle, they shone divine,
As if with God they spoke in sign.
</string>
    <string name="088">
I gazed, and trembled, faint with awe,
As soft bells rang, like heaven’s call,
In Kyiv’s air, from skies above…
O gracious God, my only love!
For the first time, my heart did break,
Till noon I wept, for mercy’s sake.
Such joy I felt, no trace remained
Of that old ennui, my soul unchained—
As if reborn, I stood anew.
I looked around, my heart was true,
I crossed myself, and softly trod
To Kyiv, not to pray to God,
But seek men’s judgment, just and fair.

O let me look, let me but stare
Upon the steppe, the field’s wide grace;
Will God not grant, in age’s space,
A taste of freedom, sweet and free?
I’d walk to Ukraine, home to be,
Where folk would greet this old man’s frame,
Rejoice to see me, call my name;
There I’d rest, if only brief,
And pray to God to ease my grief.
But vain the thought—’twill never be.
How live in chains, with hope set free?
Teach me, good folk, or I’ll go mad…
</string>
    <string name="089">
And spare, O Lord, all souls from this,
My wretched fate, an old man’s bliss
In exile’s cage, to waste away,
To squander years in vain dismay.
I’d roam the steppe, the meadow’s green,
To soothe the sorrow I’ve foreseen.
“Don’t go,” they say, “stay in this cell,
They’ll not allow your heart to dwell.”

O ninth of Apollo’s sisters fair,
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
If you’d but leave, for one brief hour,
Parnassus’ peak, its lofty tower,
And limp to steppes (unless you’re bound
In service, or in taverns found,
With drunken chumaks, wasting time?),
With ancient tales in sacred rhyme,
You’d whisper soft to me, alone,
Of tsars, or kings on gilded throne,
Their barons, princes, passions high—
For peasants’ tales grow dull, and I
Tire of luckless maids, defiled.
Of grief and sorrow, I’m beguiled…
No more, my paper’s pity spent.
</string>
    <string name="090">
What’s worse upon this weary earth
Than printed boredom’s lifeless birth?
Of wasted years, of foes with eyes
As clear as heaven’s azure skies…
Dear friends, write for your heart’s own sake,
But spare the press, for mercy’s take!
Dusk fell around.
I looked, and saw, with halting tread,
On crutches, sack in hand, a head
Of gray—an old dame, drunk, no less!
—“Good evening, son!” she slurred, a mess.
—“Good evening, auntie!” I replied.
—“Oh, I’ll surely perish,” she sighed,
“Is Parnassus far? My feet are sore,
I’m weary to my very core!
My youth, my wings, where have they flown?
Lost, like bards of old, unknown,
Who spun their odes in glory’s day…”
—“Hold on, old dame!” I dared to say,
“Are you truly from Parnassus’ height?”
—“Indeed, old man!” she grinned, alight,
“I rushed to you, but paused en route,
Met a merry bard, a hoot,
We shared a dram, a rest, a cheer…
What’s your wish, my dove, my dear?”
—“You know my heart,” I softly said.
—“By truth, I’ve clean forgot!” she pled,
“A hex, perhaps, or fever’s spell?
We’ll whisper charms… Or do you dwell
On some young black-brow’s charm, old fool?”
—“Away, you snake, you wretched ghoul!
Vile hag, you filth, is this your aid?
So much for muses from Parnassus’ glade!
A plague, a farce, and nothing more!”
</string>
    <string name="091">
No soul is seen in Jerusalem,
Its gates are barred, as if a plague
Has seized the city, God’s own gem,
Yet no pestilence makes it vague.
A darker hour, a fiercer woe,
Casts Israel in grief’s grim throe—
A war more cruel than death’s own hand!
The king’s own lords, his gathered band,
His youths, his folk, with sacred ark
Locked fast within the city’s mark,
Have marched to seek their graves afar,
Left babes, and wives, and loves that are
Their concubines… Barefoot, undone,
Disheveled, wild, with hair unspun,
They sit in chambers, locked, alone,
And weep in anguish, hearts of stone,
Deface their beauty, grand and rare,
In sorrow’s willful, bleak despair.
On streets, the tears, the wails resound,
Beyond, the shouts, the clash of ground,
The people fall, their blood is shed
For covenant, for ark, for head
Of their prophetic king. And he,
That holy king, with hands on hips,
In crimson robes, on cedar’s keep,
Strides o’er the palace, smiles, and sips
The view below, where gardens green
Unfold their shade. Amid the scene,
A marble bath, through leaves, does gleam,
And there, no mermaid of a dream,
But Bathsheba, a living Eve,
The wife of Uriah, does weave
Her spell, a slave to kingly whim,
</string>
    <string name="092">
And bathes in peace, with God her guide,
Her snow-white breast in water’s glide,
While fooling her anointed king!
Night falls, and darkness wraps its wing
O’er grieving, silent Jerusalem.
In cedar halls, like one condemned,
King David paces, lost in thought,
With impure dreams his mind is fraught…
—“I am the king of God’s own land!
A god myself, I rule, command,
I am all!” Yet soon, his will
Demands a feast to sate his thrill.
He calls for wine, for Bathsheba’s grace
To join his meal in private space.
Well done, O prophet of the Lord!
She comes… Did Uriah dream, ignored,
That not his gold or wealth was lost,
But his dear Bathsheba, the cost
Of royal theft? The king, to hide
His sin, sent Uriah to die,
Then wept before the crowd, ash-crowned,
His head in grief, his guilt profound!
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
So live the holy kings of old!
And common folk? I cannot tell…
I bid you never seek, nor dwell
On such dark truths, lest they unfold
And haunt your days with tales retold!
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
</string>
    <string name="093">
David, the prophet-king, revered,
Was far from saintly, as it’s clear.
His daughter Tamar, son Amnon,
No marvel—children come to some,
Even to saints, though not the same
As those of common folk’s acclaim! Here’s how they were:
Amnon, the blest
(Firstborn, his father’s pride confessed),
Lies ill, or so he claims to be!
David weeps, wails in agony,
Tears scarlet robes in frantic show,
And scatters ashes, head bent low:
“Without you, son, I’d not endure
A single day, my child most pure!”
He stumbles, sobbing, to his side.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
But in the cedar chamber grand,
Amnon, hale as a bull, does stand,
Mocks his father’s tears, and pleads…
While David mourns and loudly grieves.
“My cherished father, king divine,
Bid Tamar, sister sweet of mine,
To bake a cake with her own hand,
And bring it here, where I now stand.
Her touch will raise me from this bed.”
At dawn, fair Tamar, as was said,
Arrived with poppy-seed cake in tow.
Amnon seized her hand, and lo,
He led her to a darkened room,
And laid her on his bed of doom.
She suffered torments, poor heart’s cry,
“Serpent! Viper!” she screamed, “Not I!
Amnon, my brother, I’m your kin,
Your only sister—such a sin!
Where shall I hide? They’ll curse your name!”
No plea availed to halt his shame.
So live the sons of kings, in jest,
Upon this earth, unchecked, unblessed!
Behold, dear children, such is their way!
</string>
    <string name="094">
And David lived long years on earth,
Grew frail, and age dimmed royal mirth.
They draped him thick in robes to warm,
Yet youths devised a cunning form
To heat their king (his wolfish ways
They knew too well from younger days):
Maidens fair, of beauty rare,
Surpassing princesses, they’d bear
To warm his blood with youth’s sweet fire,
Then locked the doors, as they’d retire.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
The old rogue licked his lips with glee,
His slobber gleamed in lechery…
With trembling hand, he reached to claim
The Shunammite, of fairest fame,
For she outshone all others there
In loveliness beyond compare…
And she, to warm old David’s frame,
Gave of herself… How did she tame
That ancient fire? We cannot know…
He basked beside her, yet, so slow,
He knew her not, in truth or deed!
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
They marvel that the grizzled cat
No longer stirred to seize the fat,
But, poor old wretch, his teeth were gone!
</string>
    <string name="095">
Across the courtyard, soft and slow,
Old Rognvald strides, with cheerful glow,
His wife, his youths, his folk around
In golden splendor do abound.
A feast awaits, they watch the way
For Lithuania’s prince this day.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
Before the gods of Lel and Lada,
Rogneda kindled sacred flame,
With precious oil she fed its claim,
And lavish incense strewed with care.
Like Valkyries, in dance so fair,
The maidens twirl and sport around
. . . . . . . . . . . . . and sing their sound!
Hoi-hoya-hoya,
New chambers rise,
Let’s deck with blooms,
Await our prize…
Beyond the walls, a cloud of dust
Swells dark as storm. The warriors rush,
The youths, the lords, with eager feet,
The prince from Lithuania to greet.
Rogneda, with Rognvald, joins the throng,
Their hearts alight, their steps so strong.
No prince from Lithuania comes,
No longed-for friend with joyful drums,
But Kyiv’s Vladimir, a boar, a beast,
With Kyiv’s men, storms in to feast.
They ringed the town, set fires high,
Prince Vladimir, before all eyes,
Slew old Rognvald where he stood,
Shed blood of folk, as tyrants would,
Seized the princess, claimed his due,
And marched to lands his fathers knew.
With clamor went… He shamed her there,
Then cast her off to bleak despair,
A princess, wandering, lone, and torn…
So live the saints, in glory born!
</string>
    <string name="096">
Blest is he who has a home,
Where sister or mother’s love may roam,
A kindness true, a heart sincere—
Such good, in truth, I’ve never known,
Yet somehow lived, year by year.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
Once, in a far-off foreign land,
I wept, with no kin to lend a hand,
No refuge found, no hearth to claim!
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
We languished long upon the sea,
At Darya dropped anchor, we were free.
From shore, our crew brought letters dear,
Each read in silence, soft and clear.
I and a comrade lay to rest,
And spoke of things that stirred the breast.
I mused where I might find such grace—
A letter, mother, in this place.
—“Have you such ties?”—“A wife, a child,
A home, a mother, sister mild,
But letters? None to call my own.”
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
Curse those kings, and saints no less,
Who plague us with their wretchedness!
Like fools, we circle round their lore,
Unsure which path to tread before.
Where freedom’s gone, as wise men say,
No good will bloom, no light of day,
No use to dull the pencil’s might.
Let’s seek the villages, where light
Of human hearts may yet abide—
Where people dwell, good will reside.
But spare them lessons from your pen;
You’ll teach no soul, but learn again
From them, who teach you in their turn.
</string>
    <string name="097">
They’ll call me fool, a witless scribe,
And toss my book for children’s play,
No more than that, no praise ascribe…
>
—“I know not how the Poles now fare
With brothers free in freedom’s glare:
We once joined hands with Polish kin,
Till Sigismund the Third, with sin,
And his accursed priests, did rend
Our bond asunder.” So it ends,
That woe befell us, hand in hand.

>In the name of Christ our Lord,
And His holy Mother’s grace,
The Poles with war did us embrace;
Our sacred towns, by God’s accord,
Mad priests defiled with vile disgrace.
The Cossack land was set ablaze,
And blood, my son, in rivers flowed,
While graves, like mountains, rose and grew
Upon our land, our home so true.

>I dwelt upon a humble farm;
Old, frail, I sent what strength I had:
My herd of horses to the band,
A cannon, hook-guns—two carts clad,
</string>
    <string name="098">
The wheat, the millet, all I’d gained,
I gave to Ukraine, poor, enchained,
My every scrap, my heart’s own store…
And three sons to the Cossack war.
“Let them,” I mused, a sinner’s plea,
“Though but a humble gift from me,
Fight for our church, our folk, our land,
While I, in prayer, at home will stand.”
For I, my son, too weak to rise,
To lift my hand ‘gainst foes’ guise.
With me remained, hear now my tale,
My servant Danylo, frail as I,
And Prysia, daughter, bloom of May!
She’d only just begun to grow,
A cherry sweet, in youth’s soft glow…
For sins, for heavy sins, I know,
The Lord withheld from these old eyes
The joy to see her fully rise.

>No priests roamed free in villages,
But peasants hauled them, bound in rage,
From town to town, in that cruel age!
One night, those cursed ones reached my door,
With drunken mob and dragoons’ roar.
O God, grant me, if but once more,
To rise from grave and see Thy light,
I’d burn that noble brood in spite!
They—not my child, fear not, my son!—
They dragged my Prysia, every one,
Into my hut, and locked the gate,
I saw their drunken, vile estate.
Their rabble sprawled on straw to sleep,
Dragoons as well. With Danylo’s keep,
We piled the straw in entryway,
And set the barn to fiery play…
They’ll rise no more, those cursed, to slay
Our Cossack children, come what may!
</string>
    <string name="099">
They burned, each one, to ash and bone!
And Prysia, my poor child, alone,
Was lost in flames with those accursed!
On that scorched ground, with hearts that burst,
Danylo and I raised a cross,
We prayed, we wept for all our loss…
Then rode to join the camp’s grim band,
Found all three sons, and hand in hand,
In righteous hour, we fell as one!
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
For what we fought, for what we died,
And piled these graves where tears abide?
If you should live, my friend, you’ll know,
For glory shouts where our heads lie low…
Perhaps, with God’s own beggars, still,
A mournful song, of truth’s own will,
Roams village paths, of graves and us.

>With form so lithe, with beauty’s grace,
A purity in youth’s young face,
You cheer these old and weary eyes.
I gaze, at times, and marvel rise,
As if before a saint I stand,
I bow in prayer with trembling hand.
Yet pity stirs, my heart grows sore,
For beauty such as yours, no more—
Where will it lead you in this world?
Who’ll guard your soul, with wings unfurled?
Who’ll shield you from the wicked’s spite,
Or warm your heart with love’s pure light?
</string>
    <string name="100">
An orphan, lone, with none to call,
Save righteous God, who sees your fall.
Pray, dear heart, and I’ll pray too.
A prophet’s voice now pierces through,
It haunts my eyes, and I no more
Can pray to God, or you adore.
I dreamed you’re now a mother, worn,
Not draped in velvet, not in scorn,
Your hungry child in rags does cry…
You fade, as fleeting days pass by,
They steal all good, your hope they take,
And leave you lone, for sorrow’s sake.
Your child, your only joy, does grow,
In fetters bound, its wings brought low,
It fledges, flies—and you remain,
Old, frail, amidst a world of pain.
You beg from folk, unkind, unknown,
For Christ’s sake stretch your hands alone
Before their bolted doors, in vain.

>So, at times, with you, my dear,
Your youthful heart, so pure, so clear,
I cheer these old and weary eyes.
I gaze, at times, and soft arise
A prayer for you, your graceful form.
For you, I whisper, “God, keep warm”—
Pray too, beneath the holy sky,
</string>
    <string name="101">
No fate, nor fortune, good or ill,
Has dawned upon you, heart, to fill.

Fires blaze, the music wails and cries,
It weeps, it howls to starlit skies;
With diamonds bright, so dear, so clear,
Young eyes in youthful joy appear.
Hope and delight in glances play,
In eyes untainted, glad today.
All laugh, all dance, in mirth they blend,
Yet I, as if by curse confined,
Stand watching, weeping, heart resigned.
Why do I weep? Perhaps I grieve
That youth, like storm without reprieve,
Has passed me by, no mark to leave.
</string>
    <string name="102">
Is it misfortune, or the chain
Of bondage, or the years’ swift wane,
That broke my soul? Or did I never
Live with her truly, but forever
In filth with men, defiled my heart,
My once-pure spirit torn apart?
Yet people (laughing, as they do)
Call her young, and holy too,
Unspoiled, and more… O foes, you lie!
Cruel, fierce, you stole my treasure high,
My diamond pure, in mire you cast,
And mock me now. Unchristian, base!
Was it among you, vile and low,
I stained myself, that I don’t know
If ever I was clean before?
You plucked me from heaven’s sacred shore,
Taught me to pen foul verse in shame.
You laid a stone to block my aim,
And shattered, fearing God’s own light,
My small, poor heart, once just and right!
Now pathless, lost, I roam astray,
While you, amazed, see me decay,
Curse fate, curse you, and weep in pain,
Like you, I shun, in deep disdain,
My wretched, sinful soul’s remains!
</string>
    <string name="103">
I waste my days, my pen, my page,
On devil’s work, in futile rage!
At times, I weep, too much, too sore,
Not for the world, its deeds, or lore,
But like a graybeard, drunk and old,
Who sobs, an orphan, lone and cold.

Still in my dreams: beneath the hill,
By willows, where the water’s still,
A whitewashed cottage softly gleams.
There sits, as ever in my dreams,
A gray old man, who gently plays
With his sweet, curly grandchild’s ways.
And still I see, from cottage door,
The mother steps, with laughter’s store,
She kisses child and grandsire thrice,
Embraces babe with joy precise,
And bears it off to sleep’s soft keep.
The old man smiles, and murmurs deep,
Softly to himself: “Where’s the woe?”
</string>
    <string name="104">
God granted me to live and see
This joy at last. The old man, free,
Crosses himself, reads “Our Father” low,
Through willows, sunlight’s gentle glow
Fades quietly. The day is done,
All rests, and he, the aged one,
Enters his hut to take his ease.
</string>
    <string name="105">
At times, an old man, unaware,
Finds joy, though why, he cannot swear,
As if he’s young again, he sings
With what poor skill his voice still brings.
Hope, like an angel pure and bright,
Illumes his path with holy light,
His youth, a star, above him gleams,
And dances joyful in his dreams.
What stirs this old man’s heart to cheer?
Why this delight? Because, my dear,
He thinks to do some good, some grace.
And if he does? A blessed place
To live, for he whose soul and mind
Have learned to love the good, the kind!
Oft such a heart finds joy anew,
Oft blooms with periwinkle’s hue.
So too, at times, in darkest pit,
The holy sun will cast its wit,
And in that gloom, as if by chance,
Green grass will grow, and life advance.
</string>
    <string name="106">
Perhaps I ought to write alone
A letter to myself, my own,
And tell it all, the truth entire,
What’s needed, useless, all desire.
For holy writ, that sacred word,
I’ll never hear from friend or lord,
No truth divine from any hand.
It seems I’ve waited long, yet stand
Empty, though time should bring it near:
Ten summers passed since “Kobzar” here
I gave to folk, yet none reply,
As if my voice did never cry,
No bark, no curse, no word at all,
As if I never lived to call.
No praise I seek, O people, none!
Without it, I’ll endure, press on,
But counsel, guidance, that I crave!
Yet to the grave, with Moscow’s knave,
I’ll go, unheeded, unadvised.
My heart, O God, once yearned, surmised,
For one wise word to light my way,
To know for whom I write, and why
I love Ukraine, or if she’s worth
The holy fire that fuels my verse?
Though I grow old in this pursuit,
I know not yet what I dispute.
I write to fill the sacred hour,
Lest time be lost to idle power,
Yet oft the old, gray Cossack, bold,
With sinful mustache, fierce and old,
Rides up on raven steed to taunt
My will with freedom’s fleeting haunt!
No more I know, though for this cause
I perish now in foreign laws.
Did fate decree this bitter end?
Or did my mother’s prayers not bend
To God when she bore me? Am I
A serpent fierce, that, crushed, does lie
In steppe, awaiting sunset’s close?
So I endure, and death I chose
To seek in exile’s barren plain,
</string>
    <string name="107">
And why, by God, I cannot say!
Yet still I love her, come what may,
My Ukraine, wide and boundless free,
Though lone (no mate I found, you see),
I’ve wandered to my ruin’s door.
No matter, friend, grieve nevermore!
Clad yourself in armor strong,
Pray to God, and hum a song,
Spit on crowds, their cabbage heads!
Yet, brother, judge as your heart treads,
You’re no fool, so think it through.
          15.
My youthful fate stirs no regret,
But sometimes sorrow’s weight is set
Upon my soul, and tears will flow.
More so when, in a village low,
I see a boy, so small, so frail,
Like fruit torn from a branch’s sail,
Alone beneath a fence, in rags.
It seems that’s me, my youth that drags,
As if I never knew the light
Of freedom’s holy, sacred might,
That his best years will vainly flee,
He’ll find no place in liberty’s decree,
And roam this wide, free world in vain,
To toil for hire, and then, in chain,
They’ll send him off to soldier’s strife,
To still his tears, his grieving life.
</string>
    <string name="108">
We grew together, side by side,
As children, love our hearts did guide.
Our mothers watched, and softly planned
To join us one day, hand in hand.
They guessed amiss. They passed too soon,
And we, still young, were torn, strewn,
Never to meet again, alas.
Through will and force, my paths did pass
To every corner, till, at last,
Old age brought me to home’s faint cast.
That merry village, once so bright,
Now seems to me, in aged sight,
A dark and silent, mournful place,
As old and weary as my face.
It feels as if, in this poor town,
Nothing has grown, nor tumbled down,
All stays as once it used to be:
The ravine, the field, the poplar tree,
The willow bending o’er the well,
As grief in distant bondage fell.
The pond, the dam, the windmill’s wave
From grove’s edge, like a Cossack brave,
The green oak strides beneath the hill.
The orchard shades the summit still,
And there, in cool and quiet keep,
My parents lie, as if asleep,
In Eden’s rest. Their oaken crosses lean,
The words by rain are washed unseen…
No wisdom in those words, I muse!
—“But, brother, tell me, what’s the news
Of dark-haired Oksanochka, so fair,
Who played with us in childhood’s air?”
—“The curly widow, you recall?
I scarce know how to tell it all.
She followed soldiers, wandered wide,
Returned, her hair shorn, broken pride,
In tattered coat, her spirit spent,
Half-mad, it seems, and off she went,
Lost to some cruel and reckless play!
She’d sit, and preen, and softly pray
‘Our Father,’ like a schoolboy’s chant,
Unbraiding hair that once did enchant.
To nuns in Chyhyryn, they say,
She went, but such a wretch, no way
Would they accept her, worthless, low.
And yet, what beauty did she show!
A queenly grace, not poor by birth,
Yet God denied her fortune’s worth!
</string>
    <string name="109">
All’s ready! Sails unfurl to breeze,
We glide on waves, through reeds with ease,
In skiff and barge to Syr-Darya’s flow.
Farewell, poor Kos-Aral, I go.
Two years you eased my cursed despair,
My thanks, dear friend, for your kind care;
Boast that men found you, knew your worth,
And shaped some good from your bare earth.
Farewell, my friend! No praise I weave,
Nor blame, for your vast steppe I leave;
In other lands, perhaps I’ll sing
Of bygone sorrows’ bitter sting!
</string>
    <string name="110">
In autumn, we, in fleeting grace,
Resemble God’s own image, trace—
Not all, of course, but some, a few.
A steep ravine, like gypsy’s hue,
Stands bare, or slain, or sleeps in shade.
Across the valley, in parade,
A tumbleweed, like lambkin small,
Rolls to the streamlet’s gentle call,
To drink, but that small brook, too swift,
Bears it to Dnipro’s mighty drift,
To world’s end, lost. And pity stirs
For that small blade, so frail, so hers.
You walk, in sorrow, through the grove,
The whispering boughs, the bending wove
Of willows by the path’s rough way,
Your thoughts weigh heavy, tears give sway.
You long to confess, to bare your soul,
To speak your heart, to make it whole…
O gracious God, how deep the plea
To live, to love, on earth to be,
To cherish all, to hold them near!
Blest is he whose home is dear,
Whose hearth holds one with whom to share.
A child, though small, can sense the air
Of joyful thoughts, and God’s own voice
Speaks through their lips, a holy choice.
</string>
    <string name="111">
But you, my only friend, alone,
Luckless, in exile’s barren zone,
Who’ll speak with you, or soothe your pain?
</string>
    <string name="112">
        220
        221
    </string>
    <string name="113">
        222
        223
        1849
    </string>
    <string name="114">
Like chumaks trudging through the steppe
In autumn, slow, with weary step,
So pass my years, and I don’t care.
I weave my little books, prepare
To fill them with my verses’ flow,
And soothe my foolish mind’s dull woe,
While forging fetters for my hand
(If masters learn, they’ll make their stand).
Let them crucify me, I say,
Without my verse, I’d waste away.
Two years I’ve spun this poet’s thread,
And now a third, with zeal, I’ll tread.
</string>
    <string name="115">
In Ohlav… Who’d mark this white-roofed place?
A tale, though brief, to save from jest,
Lest pity turn to mocking’s trace.
Near Boryspil, or so it’s guessed,
It stands as fair as Boryspil’s grace,
A row of poplars, green and tall,
Upon the common, still embrace
The air, like maidens at a call,
From Ohlav’s fields, to greet a band.
Long years have passed—behind the fence,
Where beans once climbed with twining hand,
A window opened, summer’s sense,
To orchard shade. A cottage stood,
The captain’s home, of wealth and good.
This captain, rich, as tales attest,
Raised as his own a child not his,
Perhaps a bastard, or, in quest,
An orphan girl he took to bliss,
To nurture in his quiet keep,
A чужа дочка, flower to reap.
His wife had died, but left a son,
Sent off to Kyiv’s school to learn,
While he awaited, one by one,
The fostered Nastia’s heart to turn—
Not for his son to wed, oh no,
But old man’s folly, base and low,
To claim her for himself, a bride.
He kept his scheme from all beside,
Yet women sniffed it, sharp as hounds,
And mocked his secret on their rounds.
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
</string>
    <string name="116">
The captain sits by cottage wall,
His thoughts in silent scheming fall,
While Nastia, like a bird, does glide
Through orchard’s shade, with playful stride.
She sits by him, his hand she’ll kiss,
Or teases whiskers, white as this,
Like child to grandsire, fond and free.
But he craves more, in secrecy,
His aged flesh seeks sinful play…
With fingers gnarled, he weaves her braid,
Like serpents twined, in tight array,
Then looses them, around her laid,
Thrice round her neck, a twisted band.
Yet she, my dove, does not understand,
Plays like a kitten, pure and blind,
With old tomcat of lecher’s kind…

[Captain]
“Enough, you madcap, let me be!
Look at your hair, all wild and free,
Like some rusalka’s tangled mane…
Why don’t you weave, as gifts ordain,
Those ribbons from your aunt’s bequest?”

[Nastia]
“If you’d let me join the dance’s zest,
I’d braid those ribbons, bright and fine,
Wear yellow shoes, a skirt divine,
And deck my hair with periwinkle’s hue!”

[Captain]
“Hold on, you barehead, silly crew!
Where’d you find periwinkle for your crown?”

[Nastia]
“By the fence! It grows, so green, so round,
With blue, oh blue, and cross-shaped bloom!”

[Captain]
“You’ll not stay maiden long, I’ll vow.”
</string>
    <string name="117">
[Nastia]
“What, shall I die then?”

[Captain]
“No, not so.
Last autumn, in a dream’s soft glow,
When grafts we set… it came to me,
If they take root, by fall’s decree,
You’ll wed.”

[Nastia]
“Wake up, you jest!
I’ll break your grafts in righteous zest!”

[Captain]
“When periwinkle blooms take flight…”

[Nastia]
“I’ll tear them all by morning light!”

[Captain]
“From wedding vows you’ll not escape!”

[Nastia]
“Oh, yes, I will, and weep for sake!”
(She weeps.)

[Captain]
“Foolish Nastia, as I see,
You’ll not let me jest with thee…
Can’t you tell I tease, my dear?
Fetch the fiddle, bring it here,
And dance away our cares tonight,
While I play with all my might.”

[Nastia]
“Yes, father dear!”
(She skips, all cheer, into the house.)

[Captain]
“No, I must wait a little yet.
It’s not so simple, brother, fret:
Years won’t pause, they fly too fast,
This cursed thought, like shadow cast,
Clings to my heart… You’ve brought the bow?
What tune shall we strike up, and how?”

[Nastia]
“No, wait, no playing, I decree!
I’ll not dance till I’m decked, you see,
With periwinkle’s crown I’ll weave.
I’ll fetch it now, it’s near, believe!”
She steps to gather blooms nearby, adorns herself, and sings. The captain tunes his fiddle.

[Captain]
“One string’s already snapped, alas.
Hold on, I’ll break another, fast…”

[Nastia]
(Returns adorned, singing)
“Had I but wings, oh wings to soar,
Like falcon’s flight, I’d seek my lore,
I’d fly to my love, my heart’s own friend,
To greenwood’s shade, where dreams don’t end,
I’d fly, dark-browed, to Danube’s stream.”
Meanwhile, as she sings her dream,
A young man steps through orchard’s gate,
In straw hat, short coat, youth’s estate,
</string>
    <string name="118">
P[etro]
Good day, this blessed morn! God’s grace be yours!

N[astia]
Father! Father! Petro’s here! From Kyiv’s shores!

C[aptain]
Well, sight to see, and voice to hear! By choice or chain?

P[etro]
By choice, dear father, and a scholar’s name I’ve gained…

N[astia]
A scholar?! Oh, how grand and strange!

C[aptain]
Foolish girl, what’s there to fear? (He nears his son, blesses and kisses him.) God’s blessing, child, my heart’s own flame! Nastia, take him to the rooms, and feed him well—he’s yet to dine, I tell.

P[etro]
Indeed, I’ve not.

(He goes with Nastia to the house.)

C[aptain]
(alone)
What gift has God bestowed on me,
A son so fine, such progeny!
A scholar now, with wisdom’s crown. (He muses.) Yet why this thought weighs down?
To priesthood, then, if he’ll agree,
Or else the Sich, where he’ll be free.
That lad won’t perish, foe or friend.
But now, to home… One task to mend:
This scholar mustn’t idle here,
I’ll bid him teach Nastia, make clear
The commandments, lest we hire
Another clerk, as once for her
Who’s gone… I know Father Khoma
Won’t wed without it. I’ll go say,
Lest I forget…

(He enters the house.)
To live, to praise the Lord above,
To cherish children, bask in love,
Yet no, I’d fool myself, it seems,
And chase a wretched, selfish dream,
</string>
    <string name="119">
To wed, an old man, such a child!
Take heed, don’t wed, or you’ll defile
Her life, and yours, a laughingstock
Within your home, your heart to mock.
You’ll curse that wedding evermore,
And weep, with none to soothe your score,
No hand to wipe your aged tears.
Enough, this folly’s out of gears!
Behold: a paradise around,
Your children bloom, like flowers found.
Why would you slay their youth so bright?
No, this old dandy primps for spite,
A sight too vile to contemplate!
Yet Nastia, with the scholar’s gait,
Learns commandments in the shade.
Look there: they stroll, as if to wade
Through orchard’s peace, like doves they glide.
With father gone, they’ve naught to hide,
And play in freedom’s gentle air.
See, by the poplar, standing there,
They gaze, each on the other’s face,
Like angels rapt in holy grace,
As if they see their God above,
So pure their look, so soft their love.

P[etro]
Why, Nastia, won’t you read, I pray?
At least one commandment, try today.

N[astia]
Am I a schoolboy? No, I’ll not, and that’s my say!

P[etro]
Just one small verse, the fifth, no more.

N[astia]
Not fifth, nor sixth, nor any lore!

P[etro]
Without them, no priest will wed you, mark my word.

N[astia]
No matter, let him shun me, I’m not stirred.

P[etro]
Not even with me?
</string>
    <string name="120">
N[astia]
With you? Well… no, let him wed us, I decree!

P[etro]
Then read, or else…

N[astia]
Or what, pray tell?

P[etro]
I’ll kiss you, see, and break the spell!

N[astia]
Kiss as you like, I’ll still not read a single line!

P[etro]
(Kisses her, saying)
Here’s one! And two, for you, divine!

The captain peers from o’er the fence, then slips inside, unseen.

N[astia]
(Struggling)
Enough, enough! Father’s near, we must read, I fear.

P[etro]
Now you’ll read, you sly one, eh?

C[aptain]
(Comes from the house)
Children, enough of lessons’ play. Isn’t it time to dine today?

P[etro] and N[astia] go silently into the house.

C[aptain]
(alone)
Well taught, I’d say, no more, no less!
This child! No, Nastia, I’ll address
You now, my swan, in sterner tone!
She won’t read till kissed a hundredfold!
And that bursak, that rogue so bold!
Dog’s son, you know the taste too well.
I’ll drill you, not as school’s soft spell,
But with a broom, till you’re clean gone!
The world is wide, you’ll not be lost!
Look at him, the scholar’s boast,
Stealing from his father! Fine match, indeed!
What wicked folk this world does breed!
What’s stirring in the house, I wonder?
My little ones, again, I ponder,
Reading there… I’ll scatter their game.
Such fathers live, to their own shame,
Before God’s eyes, a mockery made.
Yet “Honor, cherish,” we’re bade,
</string>
    <string name="121">
Respect him, children,
For he is a gray-haired father!
A wise father! Blessed are those
Orphans who have no fathers,
For they do not sin.

**Настуся**
(rushes out of the house, crying)
He won’t even let me eat,
Drives me to Kyiv.
Oh, merciful God,
What shall I do?
I will set out! (Looks inside.)
He’s determined!
Oh! How angry he is!
But he won’t strike me…
And I will go to Kyiv with Petrus,
No matter what!
I am not afraid,
I will set out in the night.
Will the witch frighten me?!
No, she won’t. (Peers inside again.)
Poor thing!
He packs his books
Into his bag and takes his hat.
Farewell, my love,
My heart!..
This evening?..
Beyond the village?.. I’ll be there!
I’ll be there early! Here, catch!
(Throws a flower over the fence.)
Do you hear? Wait for me!

**С[отник]** enters. Настуся sings.
*"Do not come, do not plead, do not woo,
Do not ask, I will not go, do not hope."*

**С[отник]**
She doesn’t care! As if she doesn’t know!
Like a magpie, she jumps around.
Настуся! Why don’t you cry?
Petrus is gone.

**Н[астуся]**
Look at this sorrow!
Then cry if you grieve…

**С[отник]**
I don’t care.

**Н[астуся]**
And I care even less,
He was never mine.
And I already know
All the commandments!

**С[отник]**
All of them?

**Н[астуся]**
Let Father Khoma
Confess me right now!
</string>
    <string name="122">
**С[отник]**
Shall we wed on Sunday?

**Н[астуся]**
Of course! But we haven’t fasted yet;
Once we do, then we shall.

**С[отник]**
(kisses her)
My dove with gray wings!
My little berry!..
(Dances and chants.)
*"In the peas,
Four of us,
Walked at night.
At night,
Wandering,
Lost my necklace."*

**Н[астуся]**
Enough with that necklace already.
Go quickly to Father Khoma and seek advice!

**С[отник]**
True, true, my little flower!
I’ll run quickly,
And you, my love,
Stay here, walk quietly,
And adorn yourself.
But don’t wait for me,
For I may stay for evening prayers.
(Kisses her and leaves.)

**Н[астуся]**
Fine, fine, I won’t wait.
I won’t wait, I won’t wait,
I’ll dress in my coat,
I’ll wear my necklace,
I’ll chase after Petrus.
We’ll embrace, we’ll kiss,
We’ll hold hands,
And walk together to Kyiv.
I must adorn myself—
Perhaps for the last time,
For he said we’d wed in Brovary.
(Adorns herself and sings.)
*"Oh, I will go not by the shore,
I will meet my unwed love.
Greetings, greetings, unwed friend!
We loved each other dearly.
We loved, but did not wed,
Only sorrow filled our hearts."*

Oh, what a song I remembered!
Away with it, such a sad one!
I must hurry.
Farewell, my tall poplars,
And my winding periwinkle.
(Leaves.)

At night, the drunken **С[отник]** returns home,
Talking to himself cheerfully:
*"Let people know about us!
Let them see, gray-haired and hunchbacked,
But we!.. ha! ha! we are married!
We!.."*
Barely making it inside,
He lies down quietly to sleep,
So as not to wake Настуся
And cause embarrassment.
</string>
    <string name="123">
The bells have rung *"Dostoino"*,
People are heading home—
But Настуся does not come,
She is nowhere to be heard!

They barely wake **С[отник]**,
And tell him what happened.
He crosses himself,
Saddles his finest horse,
And gallops to Kyiv.

In Brovary,
His young Настуся
Is already wed and celebrating!

**С[отник]** returns home,
For three days and nights,
He does not rise,
He speaks to no one,
He does not complain.

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

He works, he earns,
Yet does not know
That in old age,
He will lose his mind
And abandon everything.

So it was with **С[отник]**,
With my foolish one,
He scattered his children across the world,
Yet his wealth remained,
With no one to share it.

He had to squander it alone,
To waste it all,
To do no good for anyone,
Not even a penny’s worth.

And to become a tale
For good people,
To sigh in a cold house,
Under a coat,
With no one to light the fire,
To sweep the floor…

To wander through the dust,
To grieve,
Until the owl above the roof
Howls into the window,
And the maid,
Covers his cold corpse
With an old coat,
And steals the key
From his belt.

Such was the fate
Of **С[отник]**.

Less than a year had passed,
Since Настуся was gone,
And already,
Nothing remained in the yard,
Pigs and calves
Roamed freely…
And the periwinkle!
The winding periwinkle!
</string>
    <string name="124">
Trampled down, by the fence,
It withers, fades away!
And the sotnyk, in his coat,
Swollen, wretched,
Wanders near the barn.

The stacks lie uncovered,
The chambers unplastered,
The beams unwashed,
No servants at home,
No cattle remain,
And the maid, ragged,
Even she scorns
The old master…

So it should be:
Do not drive away your children,
Gray-haired fool!
The drunken sotnyk
Did not live long
On his earnings.

Summer passed,
And in autumn,
On the street,
The sotnyk was slain!

Or perhaps he died,
Returning from the tavern?
No one cared to ask.

Good people took his rags,
And buried him well
In the meadow.
No cross was placed
Above him.

A pity—he was wealthy,
Had kin, had children,
Yet none to set a cross.

The sotnyk died,
His chambers rotted,
Collapsed,
All was lost,
All perished,
Only the poplars remained,
Standing on the outskirts,
Like maidens
Waiting for their warriors
To return from the fields.
</string>
    <string name="125">
A cloud drifts after the sun,
Spreading crimson folds,
Calling the sun to sleep
In the blue sea,
Covering it
With a red veil,
Like a mother her child.

The eyes rejoice.
For a moment,
A brief moment,
The heart seems to rest,
To speak with God…

But the mist, like an enemy,
Veils the sea—
And once again, darkness,
And you do not know
Where to turn in the world.

The night is dark,
Black,
And long until dawn…

Not heading home at night
From a godmother’s house,
Not lying down to sleep,
Remember me, brother.

And when sorrow visits,
Settles for the night,
Then, my friend,
Call upon me for counsel.

Then, in the wilderness,
Far beyond the sea,
Remember your joyful friend,
How he battles grief.

How he hides his thoughts,
His poor heart,
Wanders alone,
Prays to God,
Remembers Ukraine,
And you, my friend.

And sometimes he grieves—
Not much,
Just a little.

Outside, you see,
A holiday approaches…
</string>
    <string name="126">
It is hard, my friend,
To greet the day alone
In the wilderness.

Tomorrow morning,
The bells will ring
In Ukraine;
Tomorrow morning,
People will go to church
To pray…

Tomorrow morning,
A hungry beast
Will howl in the wilderness,
A cold hurricane
Will blow.

Sand and snow
Will bury my hut.
Thus shall I greet
The holiday!

What can be done?
Trouble exists
To be fought.

And you, my only friend,
If you must grieve,
Read this letter
And know
That in this world,
The hardest thing
Is to live in exile,
In captivity.

Yet even there,
Though poorly,
People live.

What else can I do?
I should die.
But hope,
Brother,
Never dies.

If I must grieve,
Burden others,
I will wander the world—
Whatever will be, will be.

I will find fortune,
I will marry,
If not, I will drown,
But I will not sell myself,
I will not serve.

I set out into the world,
Fortune hid away;
And freedom,
Good people
Did not trade,
But cast away
Into distant captivity…

So that such weeds
Would never grow
In our fields.
</string>
    <string name="127">
Cossack fate—
Why should I take it on?
The young Cossacks will mock me,
Saying I married, yet remain
Hungry and bare,
A fool who squandered
His youthful freedom.

And they are right.
What should I do?
Teach me, people—
Should I go into service?
Would that be fitting?

No, I will not herd
Another’s cattle,
Nor bow to a mother-in-law
In a stranger’s house.

I will shine instead,
In a blue coat,
On a black steed,
Before the Cossacks.

I will find my dark-browed love
In the steppe, by the valley—
A tall grave mound
In that Ukraine.

For the wedding,
My comrades will gather,
Bringing muskets,
Rolling out the cannon.

As they carry their comrade
To his new chamber,
The muskets will thunder,
The arquebuses will roar.

As they lay the ataman
To sleep in his new home,
The cannon will wail,
Like a grieving mother.

It will echo, cry out
For more than an hour,
And spread his glory
Across all Ukraine.
</string>

    <string name="128">
Not so much glory,
Not so much fame,
As the rumor—
That a Cossack from Sich
Visited the widow’s yard.

They dined in the chamber,
Drank honey-wine,
And in the room, upon the bed,
They lay to rest.

That glory did not fade,
It did not vanish.
The widow, in the meat days,
Bore a son.

She raised the little one,
Sent him to school.
And from school,
She took him,
Bought him a horse,
And for the horse,
She embroidered a saddle
With silk,
Trimmed it with gold.

She dressed him in red,
A costly coat,
Set him upon the steed…
"Look, enemies!
Behold!"

And led the horse
Through the village,
Brought him to the camp,
Gave him to the army…

And she herself
Went on a pilgrimage to Kyiv,
Took the veil.
</string>

    <string name="129">
If you were to rule over us,
You would know, brother,
How to name them—
Those unfortunate girls,
The ones cast aside.

But instead, you babble nonsense,
Thinking: "We shall show them!
We shall teach them
To respect vile lords!"

A waste of effort!
As long as villages stand,
As long as lords remain,
The forsaken ones
Will wander merrily,
Drinking with soldiers,
And do not trouble yourself, brother.

"Fine," I say.
"But still,
Here is one last tale,
Listen, gentlemen."
</string>

    <string name="130">
The girls raked hay in the meadow,
The lads stacked the piles,
Glancing at the sun,
Chattering nonsense—
As boys do.

And the girls,
Like magpies,
Chattered away,
Ran often to the well,
To stroll in the ravine.

The fairest of the village
Had long gone to the ravine,
Carrying a jug—
And did not return.

The overseer did not search,
As if he did not see.
Not new, this sly overseer,
An old dog, beaten before.

A cry arose in the valley,
The boys ran to help.
There, a crazed noble,
A youth,
Tormented the poor girl.

She screamed.
The boys arrived,
But did not intervene,
Fearing the lord.

One, the youngest,
Looked around,
And with a pitchfork,
Struck the noble,
Like a frog.

The wretch groaned,
Then stiffened.
They conferred,
Sent word to the city.

The court arrived,
Inspected,
Drank heartily,
The judges.

They shackled
The young lad,
Locked him in prison…
And that was all.

On the highway,
By the field,
A tavern stood beneath a willow.

A convoy from the city
Stopped by the tavern,
To rest in the shade,
To drink water,
If given—
For sometimes,
It must be carried far,
And one must forgive!
</string>

    <string name="131">
And meanwhile,
Three carriages arrived,
Bells jingling,
Music playing,
People murmuring,
Singing wedding songs—
For there was a wedding.

The bride was being taken
To the estate,
And so they stopped
By the tavern.

The poor horses,
See, they were weary!
How they snorted!

What had happened?
The bride ceased weeping.
She recognized,
In chains,
That young lad—
The one who slew the noble.

And she told no one.
The drunken guests
Did not recognize him,
Did not see
How the bride trembled.

She spoke with him,
And gave him
Her ring.

The guests saw nothing!

This was the same bride
Whom this unfortunate one
Had saved with his pitchfork.

And now he bore chains,
To Siberia,
For her sake…

Had they at least loved?
Then his suffering
Would not be in vain.

But it happened
In a moment of fury—
And that was all.

The young ones
Departed home,
And the convoy
Rattled its chains,
Prayed to God
For the bride,
For she had
Feasted them all.

They arrived—
Sang, danced
Until evening.

And in the evening,
They searched for the bride!
But they did not find her,
Did not know
Where she had gone!

And tears washed away
The joyous wedding!

The groom, alone,
Slept in the storeroom,
While the bride
Traveled with the convoy,
To Siberia.
</string>
    <string name="132">
The paths have grown over
With thorns to that land,
Perhaps I have left it forever,
Forever abandoned.

Perhaps I shall never return
Home again?
Perhaps I must read
These thoughts alone?

Oh, merciful God!
It is hard to live!
I have a heart so vast—
Yet no one to share it with!

You did not grant me fortune,
Youthful fortune!
You never gave it,
Never! Never!

You did not let my young heart
Join with a maiden’s heart.
My days and nights
Passed without joy,
Passed in exile.

No one to share my heart,
And now,
No one even to speak with!

Oh, merciful God,
It is hard to bear
These thoughts alone,
To share them with no one,
To speak no sacred word,
To bring no joy to my poor soul,
To neither bless nor curse
A wicked man.

And to die!..
Oh Lord!
Grant me at least a glimpse
Of that beaten people,
Of that Ukraine!
</string>
    <string name="133">
In the valley,
The red viburnum bloomed,
As if a young girl
Had laughed.

Sweet, so sweet—
The bird rejoiced,
And sang its song.

The girl heard,
And in a white coat,
From a white house,
She stepped out to wander
Into the grove, the valley.

And from the green grove,
A young Cossack came to her;
He kissed her, greeted her,
And they walked the valley,
Singing as they went.

Like two children,
They sat beneath the viburnum,
And kissed.

What paradise
Do we ask of God?
Paradise enters our hearts,
Yet we go to church,
Eyes shut—
We do not want this one.

I would tell the truth,
But what would come of it?
It would hinder me,
And to priests and people,
It would make no difference.
</string>
    <string name="134">
In our paradise on earth,
There is nothing more beautiful
Than a young mother
With her little child.

Sometimes, I watch,
I marvel at the wonder,
And sorrow grips my soul;
I pity her,
And I grieve,
And I pray before her,
As before a sacred image—
That Holy Mother
Who brought God into our world…

Now she lives in joy.
She rises in the night,
Guards her treasure,
Waits for the dawn,
To gaze upon it again,
To speak to it—
"This is mine!
Mine!"

She looks upon it,
Prays for it,
And walks the street,
Prouder than a queen,
To show the people
Her treasure—
"Look!
Mine is the finest of all!"

And if another glances,
She is joyful,
Oh, my God!
She carries her Ivan home.

And she believes
The whole village
Watched him all day,
That he was the only wonder,
That nothing else existed.

Happy one!
Years pass.
The children grow,
And they leave—
To labor, to the army.

And you remain, poor woman,
And none remain
With you at home.
No clothes
To cover your old body.
</string>
    <string name="135">
No firewood
To warm the house in winter.
And you are too weak to rise,
To even light the fire.

In the cold,
You pray for them,
For your children.

And you,
Martyr!
You pass the villages,
Weeping at night.

Through fields and steppes,
You hide your son.
For even the birds
Sometimes recognize,
And chirp:
"Look, a bastard child,
Carried by a fallen woman."

Wretched one!
Where has your beauty gone,
That once amazed all?
It is lost,
Gone!

The child took everything,
Drove you from your home,
And you stepped beyond the village,
As if torn from the cross.

The beggars shun you,
As if you were a plague.
And the child—so small,
It cannot even crawl.

And when will it play,
And say
The word "mother"?
That great,
Most beautiful word!

You will rejoice,
And tell the child
The truth
Of the deceitful noble,
And you will be happy.

But not for long.
For the child
Will not grow,
It will lead a blind man,
And leave you behind,
A cripple at the crossroads,
To taunt the dogs,
And curse you—
For giving it life.

And for loving it
So fiercely.

And you will love it,
Poor woman,
Until you perish
Among the dogs,
Frozen,
Somewhere beneath a fence.
</string>
    <string name="136">
That is why I pity
The poor mother,
Who loves him so,
Who perishes for him,
For that wretched child,
Squandering in this world
Her greatest treasure—
Her youthful years.

And yet, sometimes,
He amounts to nothing.
Or worse—
A heartless fiend!

Never will a mother
Find a good child
From a bastard,
Even if she is wealthy!

It is easy for the lords,
They know nothing,
They do not see
How their children grow.
For they have no mothers,
Only hired nurses.

On Easter, upon the straw,
Against the sun,
Children played with dyed eggs,
Boasting of their new clothes.

One had a shirt
Embroidered for the holiday,
Another a ribbon,
Another a sash.

One had a fur cap,
Another leather boots,
Another a coat.

Only one sat without new clothes,
A little orphan,
Hiding her hands in her sleeves.

"My mother bought mine."
"My father gifted mine."
"My godmother embroidered mine."
"And I dined at the priest’s house,"
Said the orphan.
</string>
    <string name="137">
Whether I worked,
Or wandered,
Or prayed to God,
I always thought of him,
And feared something.

I was foolish, young—
I kept watching,
Waiting for him to send for the wedding towels…
And never suspected
That he deceived me,
Though my heart ached,
As if it knew,
Yet could not say.

Had it spoken,
I would not have loved him,
Perhaps I would not have gone
To the well in the grove.

But morning and evening,
I walked, I wandered…
Until I wandered too far,
And remained,
Forever remained
A maiden.

It is hard for me,
Growing old
In my mother’s house,
Never to have my own!

And still, whether I work,
Or simply wander,
I always think of him,
And I do not know why.

Why did I go to that grove?
And why did I love him
So long,
So painfully?

Like a tax collector,
Loneliness and autumn
Have surrounded me in exile.

Oh, merciful God,
Where can I hide?
What can I do?

I wander this Aral,
I write.
I compose in secret,
I sin.

I sift through
Old memories,
And write them down,
So that sorrow
Does not force its way,
Like a soldier,
Into my lonely soul.

A cruel thief
Pushes in,
And will not relent.
</string>
    <string name="138">
It is no pity for the wicked,
For fame stands guard beside them.
But it is sorrowful for the good,
Who can deceive even glory.

Still, I feel unease
When I recall
The Gothic house with its clock,
The ragged village around it,
And the peasant
Removing his cap
At the sight of the flag.

It means the lord
Is feasting with his retinue.

That fattened hog!
That wretch!
A true noble,
Descendant of a foolish hetman,
And a fervent patriot—
And a Christian, no less.

He travels to Kyiv every year,
Wears a peasant coat among nobles,
Drinks vodka with the villagers,
And philosophizes in the tavern.

There he is,
In full—
Print him if you wish.

And in his village,
He picks through the girls,
Casually fathers
A dozen bastards a year,
Just enough to baptize.

And that is all.
A disgrace!

Why do they not call him by his true name?
Why do they not spit upon him?
Why do they not trample him?

Oh, people, people!
For a piece of rotten sausage,
You would even sell your mother.

It is no pity for him,
For drunken, crippled Petro.
But great sorrow for the people,
For those foolish children!
</string>
    <string name="139">
There is no greater sorrow
Than recalling freedom
While in captivity.

And I, my freedom,
Remember you now.
Never before
Did you seem so young,
So beautiful,
As you do now,
In exile,
In bondage.

Oh fate! Oh fate!
My sung freedom!
At least glance at me
From beyond the Dnipro,
At least smile at me
From afar…

And you, my only one,
Rise beyond the sea,
Beyond the mist,
Obedient,
Rosy dawn!

And you, my only one,
Lead behind you
My youthful years,
And before me,
Like a sea,
Spread wide villages,
Cherry orchards,
And joyful people.

And those people,
And that village,
Where once, like a brother,
They welcomed me.

Mother!
Old mother!
Do merry guests
Still gather
At the old woman’s house,
To celebrate simply,
As in the old days,
From dusk till dawn?

And you, my dark-haired children,
Joyful maidens,
Do you still dance
At the old woman’s house?

And you, fate!
And you, my peace!
My dark-browed holiday,
Do you still walk among them,
Quietly, splendidly?

And with those eyes,
So dark—so blue,
Do you still enchant
</string>
    <string name="140">
Human souls?
Do they still marvel,
In vain,
At your graceful form?

My holiday!
My only holiday!

When the children,
The maidens,
Surround you, fate,
And chirp
In their good custom,
Perhaps,
By chance,
They will remember me.

Perhaps one
Will speak of my sorrow.

Smile, my heart,
Softly, quietly,
So that no one sees…
And nothing more.

And I, fate,
In captivity,
Will pray to God.

If we met again,
Would you be afraid?
Or not?

What quiet word
Would you speak to me then?

None.
You would not recognize me.

Or perhaps,
Later,
You would remember,
Saying:
"It was a fool’s dream."

And I would rejoice,
My wonder!
My dark-browed fate!

If I saw you,
I would recall
The joyful,
The youthful,
The once bitter past.

I would weep,
I would weep!

And I would pray,
That it was not real,
But a deceitful dream,
Dissolved in tears.
</string>
    <string name="141">
Like a nail
Driven into my heart,
I carry this Marina.

Long ago,
I would have written
Her wild tale,
But what then?

They would say I lie,
That I am bitter at the lords,
That I write only
Of their vile customs…

They would say simply—
"A fool rants
Because he is a serf,
An uneducated wretch."

Not true!
By God, I do not rant.

I do not grieve
That I am no lord,
But I grieve,
And grieve deeply,
For the enlightened Christians.

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

Even a wild beast
Would not do
What you,
Bowing in prayer,
Do to your brothers…

The laws,
Written by tyrants
For you,
Mean nothing to you.

You travel to Kyiv
Every year,
Confess,
Without fail,
To the monk!

And yet,
Why do I trouble myself?

Neither good nor evil
Will I hear anymore.

And if one does not hear,
Then one does not care.

Fly to me from Ukraine,
My only friend,
My pure thought,
My faithful companion,

And tell me,
My star,
Of that Marina,
How she suffered
At the hands of a cruel lord,
And why.

But whisper,
So that none hear,
None discover.

Or they will say
That we commit robbery
Upon the road.
</string>
    <string name="142">
And further still,
They will drive us away.
We will perish together…

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

Not long ago,
A wedding passed through the village,
And the lord rode from the church—
Or rather, the steward, not the lord.

Amid the laughter and chatter,
No one noticed
How that steward,
That wretched Pole,
Passed by.

But he saw well,
Especially the young bride.

Why does the Lord favor
Such wicked creatures
As this steward?

Two years now,
Since he arrived,
Bare and penniless,
With German plows,
Settling in this corner.

And how many poor women
He cast into the world
With their bastard children—
Yet nothing came of it!

And he is married,
With two children,
Like little angels.

Look,
The young lady steps out,
Like a queen,
With her two little ones.

The lord climbs from his carriage,
Sends for the groom.

Then greets the children,
And his young wife,
Kissing her thrice,
The poor woman.

And speaking,
They walk to their chambers…

Soon,
They bring the groom.

The next day,
They take him to the city,
Shave his head,
Send him to the army!

Thus, by our custom,
Without thought,
They end it!

And the bride?
Perhaps,
She was fated
To bear her beauty,
Her youth,
Alone…

Like a spell,
It scattered,
It dissolved.
</string>
    <string name="143">
And again,
She must beg for work?

No, not again—
She is now a lady’s maid,
Called Marysia,
Not Marina!

Most of all,
They do not let her cry.
She hides,
And weeps.

Foolish girl,
She mourns the peasant,
She pities the poor wretch.

But look around—
There is no better paradise!

Whatever you desire,
They will give,
And more!

You say,
"Give me a home!"
Better not ask—
For that…
You know well yourself…

Look,
The lord himself
Circles around you,
Like a stallion.

Whether good or wicked,
You will be of noble kin—
Unless you hang yourself!

Her mother came,
To plead with the lord.

He ordered
She not be let in,
And if she came,
To beat her.

What could she do?

She left,
Weeping,
Returned to the village.

She had only one child—
And even that was lost.

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

Like a raven,
Cawing of storms,
I cry of sorrow,
Of grief,
Of those wretched bastards.

Though no one pities them,
I tell their tale,
And I weep.

I pity them!

Oh, merciful God,
Grant my words
Sacred power—

To pierce human hearts,
To shed human tears,
That mercy may touch their souls,
That quiet sorrow
May fall upon their eyes,
That they may pity
My maidens,
That they may learn
To walk righteous paths,
To love the Holy Lord,
</string>
    <string name="144">
And to cherish their brothers…

She barely reached home,
Looked around—

Flowers before the sacred image,
Flowers upon the window,
Crosses painted on the walls,
Like a beautiful picture.

Marina!
All Marina,
All herself!

Only Marina herself
Was gone.

She barely stepped from the house,
Climbed the hill,
To gaze upon
The cursed palace.

Then walked
To the palace,
Sat beneath the fence,
And sat all night,
Weeping.

The village leaders
Drove their herd,
And the mother wept,
She sobbed.

The sun had risen,
The sun had set,
Dusk had fallen—

Yet she did not return
To the village.

She sat by the fence.

They drove her away,
Even set dogs upon her—
Yet she did not leave.

And Marina,
In a white dress,
Like a dove,
Prayed to God,
And wept,
Locked in the chamber.

None entered,
Save the lord.

He brought her food,
He pleaded,
Begged her
To look at him,
To wipe her tears…

She would not look,
She would not eat.

The wretched Pole
Tormented himself,
Not knowing what to do.

And Marina
Wasted away,
Withered,
In the white palace.

Summer had passed,
Winter was at the door,
Yet Marina sat,
Silent,
No longer speaking,
No longer weeping…

Thus,
That steward
Destroyed her,
Poor soul.
</string>
    <string name="145">
Nothing will change,
Even if you slay her—
She was born this way.

One winter evening,
Marina gazed
At the black forest,
And beyond it,
The red moon,
Rising like a vat.

"I was once young…"
She whispered,
Lost in thought,
Then began to sing:

*"A house upon the scaffold,
The guests have arrived,
Unbraiding my hair,
Removing my ribbons.
The lord asks for lard,
The devil asks for food.
White geese, white geese,
Fly to the warm lands,
The gray ones to the sea!"*

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

The dogs howled outside,
The huntsmen laughed,
And the lord, red as fire,
Walked into Marina’s chamber,
Like drunken Kyrik…

As if in the house,
In the cold,
Her poor mother
Sat beneath the fence.

The old woman seemed mad.
The frost raged,
Cracking the air,
The red glow paled,
And the guard called out,
Fearful to wake the wicked lord.

Then—
The palace caught fire.

Fire! Fire!

And where did these people come from?
As if born from the earth,
As if they had grown here,
Like waves,
They surged forward,
Marveling at the blaze.

And there was wonder indeed!

Marina, naked,
Danced before the house,
With her mother!

And terror—
A bloodied knife in her hand,
And she sang…
</string>
    <string name="146">
*"Is this not the gossiping woman,
Who tucked up her skirts?
When I was a lady,
In a new coat,
The young lords courted me,
Kissed my hand!"*

(To her mother)
"And you have come to my wedding
From the other world?
They have already unbraided my hair,
But the lord arrived…

Shoo! Shoo!
Are those geese,
Or lords?
Look, they fly to the warm lands,
Away! Shoo!
To the devil’s feast!

Do you hear? Do you hear?
All the bells in Kyiv ring.
Do you see? The fire burns,
And the lord lies,
Reading,
And asks for a drink…

And do you know?
I killed him…

Look, his head,
Stands upon the chimney.

Why, why do you stare at it?
That is mother! Mother!
Do not look!
Or you will devour her.

Here, take this, choke on it!"

(She gives a mocking gesture and sings.)

*"I loved a soldier,
And grinned my teeth!
Soldiers! Soldiers!
Brought scarves,
Young lords,
Brought gold coins,
And the priest’s son,
Brought necklaces!

Ring, bell, ring,
Break the clouds,
Let the storm fall
Upon the Tatars,
And the sun upon the Christians,
Ring, bell, ring!"*

**Mother**
"Marinochka, let’s go to sleep!"

**Marina**
"Let’s go to sleep,
For tomorrow morning,
We will go to church.

Look, the wretch
Creeps to kiss me.
Here, take this!"

**Mother**
"Let’s go to sleep."
</string>
    <string name="147">
(To the people)
"Baptized folk, help me!"

**Marina**
"Take me! Take me, bind me,
Lead me to the lord’s chamber!

And will you go,
To see
What kind of lady Marina
Sits locked away?

She withers, fades,
Perishes, perishes—
Your only child,
Your Marinochka…"

(She sings.)

*"Oh, shoo, shoo, gray geese,
Shoo to the Danube.
I have tied my headscarf,
Now sit and ponder."*

Even birds have freedom,
In the open field,
Even birds fly in joy.

And I have wilted in captivity.

(She weeps.)

"If only I had a necklace,
I would hang myself…

But now,
I regret it…
Perhaps I should drown instead!

Why do you weep,
My mother?
Do not cry, my dove,
Look,
It is I,
Your Marinochka!

Look,
A black serpent
Crawls through the snow…

I will flee,
I will fly again
To the warm lands,
For I have become a cuckoo…

Did he not come to visit?
Was he killed in battle?

Do you know,
I dreamed—
By day,
The moon rose,
And we wandered by the sea,
Together.

I looked—
The stars fell,
Like into the water,
Only one remained,
One alone in the sky.

And I,
Like a madwoman,
Searched for a ford in the Danube,
Wandered, disheveled,
With my bastard child.

People laughed at me,
Called me a fallen woman,
A fool.

And you laughed,
And I wept—
No,
Not wept,
I laughed aloud…

Look,
Watch me fly,
For I am an owl…"

(She flapped her arms like wings,
And leapt across the yard,
Into the field,
Howling like a beast.)
</string>
    <string name="148">
The old mother hobbled,
Chasing after her Marina.

The lords, every one,
Burned like fattened piglets,
The white palace turned to ash,
And the people quietly dispersed.

Marina and her mother were gone.

In spring, as they plowed,
Two bodies were found in the field,
And buried upon the mound.

Like righteous children,
The Lord, loving those people,
Sent them a prophet—
To proclaim His love!
To reveal His holy truth!

Like our wide Dnipro,
His words flowed,
Poured deep into hearts!

An invisible fire burned
Frozen souls.

They loved that prophet,
Followed him everywhere,
And wept,
The learned and the cunning alike!

But they defiled
The Lord’s holy glory…
They sacrificed to foreign gods!
They became abominable!

And the holy man…
Woe to you!
Upon the streets,
They stoned him.

And rightly,
The great Lord,
As upon wild, savage beasts,
</string>
    <string name="149">
Commanded chains be forged,
Deep prisons be dug.

And, oh cruel, ruthless people!
Instead of a gentle prophet…
He gave you a king!

At night, upon the wheat fields,
Upon the open plains,
The owls gathered,
Slowly,
To jest,
To ponder,
To defend the poor birds,
To drown the eagle’s kingdom,
To burn it all,
To hang the eagle upon a stake,
And at such an hour,
To make a republic!

And all would seem well?
Ah, no—
So that the crops were not trampled…

It would not be strange,
Had another set the snare,
But look!
A naked peasant,
Set it gladly.

Then went to sleep in the haystacks,
And in the morning,
Without washing,
Came to check his guests…

"Such wretched ones!"
</string>
    <string name="150">
All owls,
Every one—
What a feast to cook and bake!

Rather than bring such spoils home,
He slew them,
And gave the rest to play,
Tamed,
To the crows,
And told no one.

Among the cliffs,
Like a thief,
Along the Dniester,
A Cossack walks at night.

He gazes, as he walks,
Upon the murky, dark waters,
As if into an enemy’s eyes,
As if he wishes to say:

"Dniester, murky waters,
Carry me to freedom!
Or drown me,
If such is my fate."

He undressed upon the stone,
Leapt into the water,
Swam,
As the blue waves roared.

And roaring,
They carried the Cossack
To the shore.

He shook himself—
Naked, barefoot,
But free,
And asked nothing more
Of God.

Wait, brother—
Perhaps, upon foreign soil,
You will ask
For fortune,
For fate.
</string>
    <string name="151">
He walked through the dark ravine,
Singing as he went:

*"Oh, from beneath the hill,
From beneath the cliff,
The carts creaked along.
And behind them,
Walked the dark-haired one,
Weeping, sobbing, as she went."*

Say what you will,
Curse me,
Or do not curse,
Do not read.

It matters not…
I do not ask.

I write for myself, brother,
Spending ink once more,
And perhaps,
God willing,
I will weep,
And that will be enough…

Now again—

He left his mother,
His home,
Left his wife,
Grief, and that was all.

To Bessarabia he went,
Driven by sorrow,
To drink the sea.

Though they say:
"As long as profit is in hand,
A peasant, like an ox,
Can be yoked to the plow,
Hungry."

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

A little, perhaps?
Or not?

Since childhood,
With his old mother,
This Cossack wandered with a sack,
Thus he grew,
An orphan,
A servant—
A ragged one.

And so he married,
Took a good woman,
But poor,
A simple maid.

And the lord!
(And misfortune,
And fortune,
As people say,
All from God.)

The cursed lord watched!
His noble eyes!

And sent gifts.

But she would not take them,
Would not love the lord!

What could be done?

For her husband,
Shorten his life…
And the woman,
Could be welcomed.

It nearly happened so.

To the last thread,
My Cossack was reduced,
All upon cursed serfdom,
Though once,
He was a master…

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

And he loved his wife,
Oh, Lord Almighty!

Like a lady,
Like a child,
He adorned her with necklaces!

But the poor soul weakened…
</string>
    <string name="152">
Sell the house,
Go into service—
That cursed lord
Has tormented him well.

And his wife,
As if unaware,
Wanders the garden,
Adorned in fine necklaces—
Like a queen!

What is there to do?
The poor man ponders.

Leave them and flee?
But who will feed them?
Who will care for them?

One—old,
Too weak to rise.
The other—young,
Thinking only of pleasure!

What now?
What to do?
Oh, my sorrow! My sorrow!

And so he left,
Took his sack,
Crossed the blue sea,
Seeking fortune.

He thought to return,
At least to take his wife…

His old mother
Would remain,
Living out her days
At home.

Thus it happens in this world—
He thought to live,
To prosper,
To praise God,

But in exile,
He found only tears!

Nothing more.

He grew weary
Upon foreign soil!

He gained much,
A laborer,
Yet found no fortune!

No sacred fate…

God’s world was bitter,
He grew weary in exile,
Even wealth lost its taste!

He longed,
At least to see
His beloved land!

The high mounds!
The wide steppes!
The garden!
His wife,
His dark-eyed queen!

And so he sailed the Dniester,
Leaving freedom behind,
A wanderer…

Oh, my God!
What a field you are!
My own field!
How vast you are…
How wide!

Like freedom…
</string>
    <string name="153">
He returned home at night.

His mother groaned upon the stove,
His wife slept in the storeroom
(For the lord was unwell).

She rose,
Clung to him like a leech,
And wept,
Her tears falling like peas.

And so it happens among us—
A knife pressed to the heart,
Yet kisses follow!

My poor young wife revived!

And where, oh Lord,
Did such delicacies come from?

She herself,
Like a lifeless thing,
Fell upon his shoulders…

She gave him drink,
She fed him,
And laid him to sleep,
Joyful,
In the storeroom!

The poor man lay,
Thinking,
Wondering,
How they would wander,
And quietly dozed…

But the young wife
Ran to the lord,
Told him everything—
Just so,
Just so.

Sweetly, lovingly,
They came,
Took the poor man,
And carried him from home—
A vagabond,
A wanderer…

Straight to the reception.

And there,
Fortune did not abandon him.

He served,
Earned rank,
Then returned to his village,
And left service behind.

His mother was buried
By the people,
The lord had died,
And his wife—
A beggar,
Wandered everywhere,
Among Jews,
Among lords,
Barefoot…

He found her,
Looked upon her…

And, gray-haired,
Raised his crippled hands
To the holy God,
Wept like a child…
And forgave the poor woman!
</string>
    <string name="154">
Thus, people,
Learn to forgive your enemies,
As this simple man did!

Where, oh sinners,
Shall we find such goodness?

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

The sky is unwashed,
The waves drowsy;

And along the shore,
Far, far away,
Like a drunken man,
The reeds bend
Without wind.

Oh, merciful God!

How long must I remain
In this open prison,
Beside this worthless sea,
Weary of the world?

It does not speak,
It is silent,
It bends,
Like living,
Yellowed grass in the steppe.

It does not wish to tell the truth,
And there is no one else to ask.
</string>
    <string name="155">
I grew up in exile,
And I grow gray in a foreign land.

To me, alone,
It seems—
There is nothing greater
In God’s world
Than the Dnipro
And our glorious land…

Yet I see—
There is only goodness
Where we are not.

In a dark hour,
Not long ago,
I happened to visit Ukraine,
That finest village…

The one where my mother
Once swaddled me,
Where, at night,
She earned a candle for God,
Bowing deeply,
Praying to the Virgin,
That good fortune
Would love her child…

Good, mother,
That you lay to rest early,
Or you would have cursed God
For my fate.

Oh, how wretched
That fine village has become!

Darker than black earth,
The people wander,
The green orchards have withered,
The white houses have rotted,
Collapsed,
The ponds overgrown with weeds.

The village seems burned,
The people seem mad,
Mute,
They go to serfdom,
Leading their children!

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

And I,
Weeping,
Returned again to exile.

And not in that village alone,
But everywhere,
Across glorious Ukraine,
The people have been yoked
By cunning lords…

They perish!
They perish!

In bondage,
The sons of knights,
While the vile lords
Sell them,
To their good brothers,
The Jews…
</string>
    <string name="156">
The last ones sell their trousers…
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

It is terrible, truly terrible!
To perish in this wasteland.
Yet even worse, in Ukraine,
To watch, to weep—and remain silent!

But if one does not see that sorrow,
Then everywhere seems peaceful, quiet,
And Ukraine appears good.

Between the mountains,
The old Dnipro,
Like a child in milk,
Shines, rejoices,
Across all Ukraine.

And above it,
Wide villages green,
And in those cheerful villages,
Joyful people.

Perhaps it would have been so,
Had no trace of the lords remained
In Ukraine.

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

Not for the people,
Not for glory,
Do I weave these verses,
Curled and adorned.

For myself, my brothers!

It eases my burden in captivity,
As I compose them,
Like words flying
From the distant Dnipro.

They settle upon the paper,
Weeping, laughing,
Like children.

And they bring joy
To my lonely,
Poor soul.

It is sweet to me,
Sweet to be with them,
Like a wealthy father
With his little children.

And I am glad,
And I rejoice,
And I pray to God,

That He does not take my children
In a distant land.

And sometimes…
I remember
My Ukraine.
</string>
    <string name="157">
And I weep…
Oh, merciful God!

Let me perish
In this cursed wasteland,
But do not let my unfortunate children
Be lost in the vast desert.

Let them return home,
My dear children,
To where I once lived.

And in a joyful family,
Quietly,
Sadly,
They will read—
I would have loved him.

By the grove,
In the open field,
Upon the very mound,
Two tall poplars
Lean toward each other.

And without wind,
They sway,
As if struggling in the field.

Those are the enchanted sisters—
Those poplars.

Both fell in love
With one Ivan;
And Ivan,
A simple Cossack,
Did not scorn either,
But courted one,
Then the other,
Sweetly…

Until one evening,
In the ravine,
Beneath the green oak,
All three met.

"So, you wretch!
You mock the sisters…"
</string>
    <string name="158">
And they went searching
For poison-herbs,
To kill Ivan
The next day.

They found the herbs,
Dug them up,
And began to brew.

They wept,
They sobbed…
But there was no escape,
They had to brew.

They brewed,
Poisoned Ivan,
And buried him
By the grove,
In the field,
Upon the mound.

And did it matter?
No, not much.

For the sisters came,
Every morning,
To weep over Ivan,
Until they themselves
Were poisoned
By that wicked herb.

And God,
As a lesson to the people,
Set them in the field,
Upon the mound,
As poplars.

And those poplars,
Above Ivan’s grave,
By that grove,
Sway without wind,
And the wind sways them.
</string>
    <string name="159">
If only I had shoes,
I would go to the music…

Oh, my sorrow!
No shoes,
Yet the music plays!
Plays!
Bringing grief!

Oh, I will go barefoot through the field,
Seeking my fortune…

Oh, my fate!
Look upon me, dark-browed,
My false fate…
I am unfortunate!

The girls at the music,
In red shoes…
And I wander the world.

Without luxury, without love,
I wear away my dark brows,
I wear them away in servitude!

And I am rich,
And I am beautiful,
Yet I have no match,
I am unfortunate.

It is hard, hard to live in this world,
And love no one,
To wear velvet coats
Alone.

I would love,
I would marry
A dark-browed orphan,
But it is not my will!

Father, mother do not sleep,
They stand guard,
They do not let me
Wander the garden alone.

And if they let me,
It is with him,
That wretched old man,
My unloved, wealthy one,
My cruel enemy!
</string>
    <string name="160">
I loved,
I married
An unfortunate orphan—
Such is my fate!

Proud, wicked people
Separated us,
Took him away,
Sent him to the army!

And I,
A soldier’s wife,
Alone,
Grow old in a stranger’s house—
Such is my fate!

My mother bore me
In high palaces,
Wrapped me in silk.

In gold, in velvet,
Like a hidden flower,
I grew, I grew.

And I grew into a wonder,
Dark-eyed, black-browed,
Fair-faced.

I loved a poor man,
My mother did not let me marry,
And I remained,
In high palaces,
A maiden all my life—
Such is my misfortune.

Like a blade of grass in the valley,
In lonely solitude,
I grow old.

I do not gaze upon God’s world,
I do not reach for anyone…
</string>
    <string name="161">
And my old mother…
Forgive me, my mother!
I will curse you
Until I die.

Oh, I sent my husband
On the road,
And from tavern to tavern,
I trod the path.

I stopped by my godmother’s
To borrow millet,
To feed the children
In the cold, unheated house.

I fed them,
I laid them to sleep,
Then went to the deacon
To earn a coin,
And spent the night there.

And from Crimea,
My husband barely dragged himself home.

The oxen had died,
The carts had broken,
The traders, with their whips,
Returned home.

He entered the house,
Struck the threshold…
</string>
    <string name="162">
The children crawled in the corner,
Hungry and naked.

"Where is your mother, children?"
The poor man asked.

"Father! Father!
Our mother
Is drinking in the tavern."

Oh, I will sharpen my knife,
Slip it into my boot,
And go searching for justice,
And for glory.

I will not walk the meadows,
Nor the shores,
I will not take the roads,
But walk beside them.

I will ask the Jew,
The wealthy lord,
The vile noble,
In his wretched coat,
And the monk,
If I meet him—
Let him not wander,
But read the Holy Scripture,
Teach the people,

That brother should not slay brother,
Nor rob him,
Nor send the widow’s son
To the army.
</string>
    <string name="163">
The wind blows through the street,
Snow drifts along.

Along the street,
By the fences,
A widow hobbles,
Toward the bell tower,
Stretching her hands
To the same wealthy men
Who sent her son to the soldiers
Two years ago.

She had hoped to live…
At least in old age,
To rest in comfort
With her daughter-in-law.

It was not to be.

She begged
For a single coin…
And placed a candle
Before the Virgin,
For her son.

Oh, I will sit by the house,
Gaze upon the street,
Watch the girls
Playing without my Hanna,
Without my little Hanna,
Playing tag.

And they play joylessly,
And they do not sing
As they once did.

The girls play,
But my dove is gone.

She coos somewhere
At her mother-in-law’s,
Watching for me.
</string>
    <string name="164">
The cuckoo called
In the green grove,
The maiden wept—
Her friend was gone.

And youthful, maiden years,
Joyful years,
Like flowers upon the water,
Drift away from this world.

If only there were father, mother,
If only they were wealthy,
There would be someone to love,
Someone to wed.

But there is none,
And as an orphan,
I will perish,
A maiden,
Alone,
Somewhere beneath a fence.
</string>
    <string name="165">
In Perepyat,
The Haidamakas
Spent the night in secret.

Before sunrise,
In Fastiv,
The lads made merry.

Come forth from Mezhyhirya,
Our glorious Paliy,
Look upon Shvachka,
See what he does to the Poles
In your Fastiv,
In your famed city.

Heads rolled,
Not a hundred,
Not two hundred,
But thousands,
And noble blood
Turned red
The town halls,
The churches,
Flooded everything.

Only one thing
Was left untouched—
The holy church.

There,
Shvachka and the Cossacks
Sang "Alleluia."

They praised the Lord,
Joyful,
And ordered the saddling
Of his black steed—
To ride to Bykhov,
To revel there.

He would revel
In Bykhov,
In the famed city,
With Levchenko beside him,
To trample
The Jewish and noble corpses.
</string>
    <string name="166">
Oh, the beer and mead
Are not drunk,
Nor is the water.

Misfortune struck
A trader in the steppe.

His head ached,
His stomach pained,
He fell beside his cart,
Fell and lay still.

From glorious Odesa,
They brought the plague,
His comrades abandoned him—
Woe to him.

His oxen stood
Beside the cart,
Gloomy,
And from the steppe,
The ravens
Flew toward him.

"Oh, do not peck,
Ravens,
At the trader’s corpse,
For if you feast,
You will perish
Beside me together."

Oh, fly,
Ravens,
My gray-winged ones,
To my father,
Tell him
To hold a service,
To read the Psalms
For my sinful soul.

And to the young maiden,
Tell her
Not to wait for me.
</string>
    <string name="167">
On the street,
All is joyless,
At home,
Father scolds,
And to the widow’s house,
At dawn,
Mother does not let me go.

What shall I do?
Where shall I go?

Should I love another?
Or should I drown myself?

Oh, I will wear earrings,
And a fine necklace,
And I will go to the fair,
On Sunday,
To the city.

I will tell him:
"Wed me,
Or leave me be!"

For if I remain
With my mother…
It is better to drown.
</string>
    <string name="168">
The second was impaled
In Kozlov.

The third, Ivan Yaroshenko,
A famed orphan’s son,
From cruel captivity,
From Bakhchisarai,
Rescued his brother.

The doors creaked open
Early in the great house.

"Rise, rise, Kateryna,
To greet your brother."

Kateryna looked,
Then cried aloud:

"This is not my brother,
This is my beloved,
I deceived you…"

"Deceived me!"

And Kateryna’s head
Rolled to the ground…

"Come, brother,
Let us leave this wretched house."

The Cossacks rode away,
Chasing the wind.

They buried dark-browed Kateryna
In the field,
And the noble Cossacks
Became blood brothers
In the steppe.
</string>
    <string name="169">
Beyond the grove,
The sun rises,
Beyond the grove,
It sets.

Through the valley,
In the evening,
A sorrowful Cossack walks.

He walks an hour,
He walks another.

The dark-browed maiden
Does not emerge
From the shadowed meadow,
Does not come forth,
The treacherous one…

And from the ravine,
From the forest,
With dogs and huntsmen,
A lordly reveler rides.

They set the dogs upon him,
Twist his arms behind him,
Inflict upon the Cossack
Mortal torment.

The lord locks him,
Young and strong,
In the cellar…

And the maiden,
Branded,
Is cast into the world.
</string>
    <string name="170">
Oh, I went to the ravine for water,
And there my beloved
Rejoiced with another.

And that other,
That wicked temptress,
A wealthy neighbor,
A young widow.

And yesterday,
With her,
With that serpent,
I gathered flax in the field,
And told her everything—

How he loves me,
How he will wed me,
And even invited
That vile bitch
To my dowry.

Ivan, my Ivan,
My dear beloved,
May God’s wrath
Strike you
Upon the open road.

Not so much the enemies,
As the good people—
They will rob you,
Mourn for you,
Weep,
Then condemn you.

They will invite you into their house,
Greet you warmly,
Ask about you,
Only to mock you later,
To laugh at you,
To destroy you.

Without enemies,
One can live in this world,
Somehow.

But these good people
Will find you everywhere,
And even in the next world,
They will not forget you.
</string>
    <string name="171">
Oh, hush, hush, my child,
Day and night.

You will walk, my son,
Through Ukraine,
Cursing us.

My son, my son,
Do not curse your father,
Do not remember him.

Curse me, the damned one,
I am your mother,
Curse me.

When I am gone,
Do not go among people,
Go into the grove,
The grove will not ask,
Will not see,
There, you may wander.

If you find the viburnum
In the grove,
Then embrace it,
For I once loved it,
My child.

If you go to the villages,
To those houses,
Do not grieve.

And if you see a mother
With her children,
Do not look.
</string>
    <string name="172">
Fog, fog through the valley,
It is good to live with family.

But even better beyond the mountain,
With a young wife.

Oh, I will go through the dark grove,
Seeking my beloved.

Where are you? Where are you?
Call out to me!
Come, my heart,
Embrace me.

Come, my love,
Let us court,
Let us ride to wed,
So that father and mother
Do not know
Where we will spend the night.

I married,
I hid away,
Would that I had never loved!

It would have been easier
To live alone,
Than to struggle with you
In this world.

On Sunday,
On the holy day,
At dawn,
In the famed, glorious
City of Chyhyryn,

The bells rang,
The cannons fired,
The revered congregation
Was gathered together.

With sacred banners,
With images of the Virgin,
The people,
With priests,
From all the churches,
Climbed the hill,
Buzzing like God’s bees.

From the holy monastery,
In gold,
Shining,
The archimandrite emerged,
Read the Akathist,
Bowed in prayer.

Solemnly, quietly,
In the early hour,
Upon the high hill…
</string>
    <string name="173">
The colonels gathered,
And the army, like the sea,
With banners, with standards,
Marched forth from the Meadow,
Trumpets playing.

Upon the hill,
They stood together.

The cannons fell silent,
The bells ceased ringing,
And the people bowed
To the earth.

The archimandrite himself
Led the prayer upon the hill,
Praising, pleading to the Holy God,
That He grant them wisdom,
That they choose a worthy hetman.

And unanimously,
With one voice,
The people chose their leader—
The glorious Ivan Loboda,
An old knight,
A brother of the army.

The trumpets sounded,
The bells rang,
The cannons fired,
Banners and standards
Covered the hetman.

The old hetman wept,
Raised his hands to God,
Bowed three times
Before the great assembly,
And, like a bell,
He spoke:

"Thank you, noble warriors,
Glorious Cossacks,
For the honor, the glory, the respect
You have bestowed upon me.

Yet you would have done better
Had you chosen,
Instead of an old man,
A young, bold warrior,
A glorious Cossack,
Pavlo Kravchenko-Nalyvaiko.

I am old,
Too weak to rise,
I will give him counsel,
Teach him as a father,
</string>
    <string name="174">
How to stand against the Poles.

Now is a cruel time
Upon our glorious Ukraine.

It is not for me, brothers,
To lead you against the Poles.
It is not for me,
An old man,
To bear the mace.

Let Nalyvaiko bear it,
For the glory of the Cossacks,
That the vile Poles
May tremble in their Warsaw."

The people buzzed like bees,
The bells rang,
The cannons roared,
And the standards covered
The glorious Cossack,
Pavlo Kravchenko-Nalyvaiko.

She walked through the thicket
For walnuts,
Loved the miller
For pleasure.

The miller grinds,
Turns,
Kisses her
For pleasure.

She walked through the thicket
For mushrooms,
Loved the saddler,
Young and fair.

The saddler sews the bridle,
Holds her close,
Embraces her,
Young and fair.

She walked through the thicket
For firewood,
Loved the cooper,
Dark-browed.
</string>
    <string name="175">
The cooper binds the barrels,
Holds her close,
Embraces her,
Dark-browed.

If you wish to know,
My mother,
Whom you will first
Call your son-in-law—

All of them, all of them,
My mother,
On Sunday,
You will call them sons-in-law.

On Sunday, early,
Before the sun had risen,
I, young and fair,
Went to the road,
To the path,
Joyless.

I went beyond the grove,
Into the valley,
So that my mother
Would not see me,
To meet my young trader
Returning from the road.

Oh, I met him
Beyond the willows,
With the traders’ carts.

His oxen walked,
Gray oxen,
Walked,
Chewing their cud,
But my young trader
Was not among them.
</string>
    <string name="176">
Oh, they dug for him,
In the steppe,
By the roadside,
A grave with stakes.

They wrapped him
In a coarse mat,
And lowered Ivan
Into that deep grave,
Upon the high mound.

Oh, merciful God!
Merciful, compassionate!
And I loved him so.

It is not the tall poplar
That the wind bends,
It is the lonely maiden
Who curses her fate.

"May you, fate,
Drown in the sea,
For you have not given me,
Even now,
Someone to love.

How the girls kiss,
How they are embraced,
And what they feel then—
I still do not know.

And I will never know.

Oh, mother,
It is frightening to remain a maiden,
To live my whole life
Without love."
</string>
    <string name="177">
I have trodden a path
Through the ravine,
Over the hill, my dear,
To the market.

I sold bagels
To the Cossacks,
Earned, my dear,
A five-kopeck piece.

I drank away
Two kopecks,
Hired a piper
For a single coin.

Play for me, piper,
On your pipe,
Let me forget
My sorrow.

Such a girl am I,
Such am I!
Woo me, my dear,
I will go with you.

The wide valley,
The high mound,
The evening hour,
And all that was dreamed,
All that was spoken—
I will not forget.

But what of it?
We did not wed,
We parted,
As if we had never known each other.

And meanwhile,
Those precious,
Youthful years
Passed in vain.

We both faded—
I in captivity,
You a widow.

We do not live,
We merely walk,
And recall those days,
When once we lived.
</string>
    <string name="178">
By the ford,
Near the garden,
The periwinkle does not bloom.

For some reason,
The maiden
No longer goes to the ford
For water.

By the garden,
Near the fence,
The green hops wither
Upon the stake.

The maiden
No longer steps
From her house.

By the ford,
Near the garden,
The willow has bent low.

The dark-browed maiden
Has sorrowed,
Deeply sorrowed.

She weeps,
She sobs,
She struggles like a fish…

And above her,
Young and fair,
The wretch laughs.

If only, mother,
I had a necklace,
I would go tomorrow
To the city.

And in the city,
Mother, in the city,
The music plays,
The lively music.

And the girls,
With the lads,
Court each other.

Mother! Mother!
I am unfortunate!

Oh, I will go,
I will pray to God,
Then I will go,
I will hire myself out.

I will buy, mother,
Shoes,
I will hire,
A lively band.

Let the people not marvel,
When I, mother,
Dance.

Oh, my fate!
Do not let me remain a maiden,
Braiding and unbraiding my hair,
</string>
    <string name="179">
Wearing away my brows at home,
Living out my days in solitude.

And while I labor,
My dark brows fade.

I am unfortunate!

"I do not wish to marry,
I do not wish to wed,
I do not wish to sit by the hearth,
Feeding children.

I do not wish,
My mother,
To walk behind the plow,
To wear velvet coats
Upon the fields.

I will go,
I will wed
My faithful friend,
My noble father,
The Zaporizhian host,
And the Great Meadow.

Upon Khortytsia,
With my mother,
I will live well,
I will walk in velvet,
Drink mead and wine."

The foolish Cossack
Went seeking glory,
</string>
    <string name="180">
And his old mother
Was left an orphan.

Oh, she remembered,
On Sunday,
As she sat to eat:

"My son Ivan is gone,
And there is no word of him."

Not after two,
Not three years,
Not after four—

Our Cossack returned,
Like a wraith,
A wraith,

Tattered, patched,
A cripple,
Into the house.

This is your Zaporizhian glory,
And your poor mother!

No one to greet him,
No one to mourn with him,
He should have wed,
When he was young.

His youthful,
Joyful years
Have passed.

No one to warm
His cold heart.

No one to meet him,
To light the hearth,
No one to bring water
To the cripple.
</string>
    <string name="181">
The plague walked with a shovel,
Dug graves,
Filled them with corpses,
And did not sing with the saints.

Through the city,
Through the village,
It swept like a broom.

Spring came,
The orchards bloomed;
Like a white cloth,
Covered,
Washed with God’s dew,
They gleamed.

The earth rejoiced,
Blossomed,
Adorned with flowers,
With dark orchards,
With meadows.

But the poor people,
In the village,
Like frightened lambs,
Locked themselves in their houses,
And died.

Through the streets,
The oxen bellowed,
Hungry,
In the gardens,
The horses grazed,
No one came forth
To drive them,
To feed them,
As if the people
Were asleep.

They had fallen asleep,
Deeply,
Forgotten the holy Sunday,
For the bells
Had long been silent.

The chimneys mourned,
Without smoke,
And beyond the gardens,
Beyond the fences,
Black graves grew.

Beneath the houses,
Among the orchards,
Wrapped in hides,
In tar,
The grave-diggers,
In the village,
Dragged corpses with chains,
Beyond the village—
And buried them
Without coffins.

Days passed,
Months passed—
The village
Fell silent forever,
Grew mute,
And was overgrown with nettles.

The grave-diggers walked,
And they too
Lay beneath the houses.

No one emerged
In the morning,
To bury them,
Poor souls.

Beneath the houses,
They rotted.
</string>
    <string name="182">
Like an oasis,
In the open field,
The village gleams green.

No one enters,
Only the wind blows,
Scattering yellow leaves
Across the yellow field.

Long it remained green,
Until the people,
From the fields,
Set fire to the ruins,
Burned the village down.

It burned,
It crumbled,
The wind scattered its ashes,
And no trace remained.

Such was the sorrow
The plague brought upon the people.

And again,
The post brought me nothing
From Ukraine…

For my sinful deeds, perhaps,
I suffer in this wasteland,
Punished by an angry God.

It is not for me
To know why I suffer,
Nor do I wish to know.

But my heart weeps,
When I recall
Even the sorrowful moments,
Even the sorrowful days,
That once passed over me
In my Ukraine…

Once, they swore,
They pledged,
They became brothers,
They became sisters to me,
Until, like a cloud,
They dispersed,
Without tears,
Without that sacred dew.

And again,
I was left alone in old age…

No, no,
They perished from cholera,
Or else they would have sent
At least a scrap of paper…
</string>
    <string name="183">
Oh, from grief,
From sorrow,
So that I do not see
How they read those letters,
I will wander,
I will wander by the sea,
Ease my sorrow,
Recall Ukraine,
Sing a song.

People will speak,
People will betray.

But she will console me,
She will comfort me,
She will tell me the truth.

In captivity,
In solitude,
There is no one
To share my heart with.

So I search,
For someone
To speak with.

I seek God,
And I find
Something
I dare not even name.

Such is what the years
Have made of me,
Such is what misfortune has done,
And also,
That my sacred summer
Passed under clouds,
That there is not
A single moment
Worthy of remembrance.

Yet the soul
Must be consoled,
For it longs,
It pleads
For even a quiet word;
But none is heard,
And it is as if,
In the field,
Snow buries
A body
Still warm.
</string>
    <string name="184">
Oh, my old father has died,
And my old mother too,
And there is no one
To give me
True counsel.

What shall I do
In this world,
An orphan?

Should I go among people,
To live?
Or remain at home,
To grieve?

Oh, I will go
Into the green grove,
I will plant rue.

If my rue grows,
I will stay here,
My beloved will come
To my house,
To be its master.

But if not,
I will go
Seeking my fate.

The rue sprouted,
It greens in the grove.

But the orphaned maiden
Wastes away in servitude.
</string>
    <string name="185">
1850
</string>
    <string name="186">
I count the days and nights
In captivity,
And lose count.

Oh Lord,
How heavy
These days pass.

And the years
Flow between them,
Flow quietly,
Taking with them
Both good and evil!

They take,
They do not return,
Never anything!

And do not plead,
For the prayer
Will be lost before God.

And the fourth year passes,
Softly, slowly,
And I begin
The fourth book
In captivity.
</string>
    <string name="187">
I weave it—
I weave it
With blood and tears,
My sorrow in exile,
For sorrow
Cannot be told
To anyone,
Ever, ever,
Anywhere in the world!

There are no words
In distant captivity!

There are no words,
No tears,
Nothing.

Not even around you,
The great God!

There is nothing to see,
No one to speak with.

One does not wish
To live in this world,
Yet one must.

I must, I must—
But for what?

To save my soul?

It is not worth
Such sorrow.

That is why
I must live,
Drag my chains
In captivity!

Perhaps,
I will yet see
My Ukraine…

Perhaps,
I will yet share
Words and tears
With the green groves!
With the dark meadows!

For I have no kin
In all Ukraine,
Yet still,
They are not the same
As those in this foreign land!

I would wander
By the Dnipro,
Through the joyful villages,
And sing my songs,
Soft, sorrowful.

Let me live,
Let me see,
Oh, my merciful God!

The green fields,
The sacred mounds!
</string>
    <string name="188">
And if You do not grant it,
Then carry my tears
To my land,
For, oh God,
I perish for her!

Perhaps, in exile,
I will rest easier,
If sometimes, in Ukraine,
They remember me!

Carry them,
Oh merciful God!
Or at least send hope
Into my soul…

For I can do nothing,
Nothing at all,
With my poor mind,
For my heart grows cold,
When I think
That perhaps,
They will bury me
In exile,
And these thoughts
Will be buried with me!

And no one in Ukraine
Will remember me!

But perhaps,
Softly, over the years,
My words,
Woven with tears,
Will someday reach Ukraine…

And they will fall,
Like dew upon the earth,
Upon a pure, young heart,
They will fall,
Softly, as tears!

And it will bow its head,
And it will weep with me,
And perhaps, oh Lord,
It will remember me
In its prayer!

Let it be as it will be.
Whether to sail,
Whether to wade.

Even if I must be crucified!
Yet still,
I will weave
These quiet, white pages.
</string>
    <string name="189">
We sang,
We parted,
Without tears,
Without words.

Will we meet again?
Will we ever sing again?

And if we do…
Where?
As whom?

And what will we sing?

Not here,
And surely,
Not as we are now!

And we will not sing
The same song!

Even here,
We sang joylessly,
For even here,
It was joyless.

Yet still,
We lived,
At least,
We sorrowed together,
Remembering
That joyful land,
And the mighty,
Steep-banked Dnipro,
And that youthful sorrow!

And that young,
Sinful paradise!
</string>
    <string name="190">
**The Cottage**

She did not pray for me,
She did not bow for me,
My mother;
She simply swaddled me,
Singing—

"Let him grow,
Let him be healthy!"

And I grew,
Thank God,
Yet I did not rise
Among people.

It would have been better
Not to be born,
Or to be drowned,
Than to live in captivity,
Angering the Lord.

And I asked so little,
So little,
Of God—
Only a cottage,
A single cottage in the grove,
Two poplars beside it,
And my unfortunate one,
My Oksana.

That with her,
Together,
We might gaze from the hill
Upon the wide Dnipro,
Upon the ravines,
Upon the golden fields,
Upon the high mounds.

To look,
To ponder,
To wonder—
When were they raised?
Whom did the people bury there?

And together,
Softly,
To sing
That sorrowful,
Ancient song,
Of that knight,
That hetman,
Whom the Poles burned in fire.

And then,
We would descend from the hill,
Wander by the Dnipro,
Through the dark grove,
Until dusk,
Until God’s world
Fell asleep,
Until,
With the evening star,
The moon rose above the hill,
And the mist
Did not yet drive it from the fields.

We would look,
We would pray,
And speaking,
We would go
To supper,
In our cottage.

You grant,
Oh Lord Almighty,
Gardens to the lords,
In Your paradise,
You grant them
High palaces.

And the lords,
Greedy,
Bloated,
Spit upon Your paradise,
Oh Lord,
And do not let us gaze upon it,
From our poor,
Little cottage.

I asked only
For a cottage
In that paradise,
And still,
I ask—

That I might at least
Die by the Dnipro,
Upon a tiny hill.
</string>
    <string name="191">
There were lords
Upon the farmstead,
A lord,
A lady,
Not wealthy.

And their daughter grew,
She had risen tall.

And a general
Courted her,
For she was
Strikingly beautiful,
And the general
Was strikingly rich.

Thus, fortune
Was sent by the Lord
To the poor farmstead,
They pleaded
With the Heavenly King!

They took her,
Dressed her finely,
And on Sunday,
They wed her,
And called her
A general’s wife,
And carried her
By carriage
To Kyiv.

There was,
Upon the farmstead,
A wretched,
Little bastard,
Who herded swine,
Called Petrus.

And as part of her dowry,
He followed the lady,
To the general’s estate,
To herd swine,
Unfortunate one.

Ball after ball,
At the general’s,
A great gathering
Of lords and noblemen,
And the general’s wife,
At night,
Began to weep softly.

"My mother
Has ruined me.
My beauty,
My youth,
Will wither in vain,
In these palaces."

"You, my dear,
Are crying?"

"Who, me?
No, I am not crying…"

"You know, Mania,
The Armenians
Are in the city now,
Buy yourself,
Mama,
A shawl."

"I do not need
That shawl."

"Do not grieve,
Do not sadden
Your heart!
Buy it, my dove!
Do not sorrow
My heart!

And in spring,
We will go to Paris,
Together,
Or we will go
To the estate,
If you wish,
My heart."

Softly, softly,
Winter passed,
Misfortune crept,
And settled
In the very heart
Of the young general’s wife.

They went to the estate
In spring,
And in the estate,
The banquets roared.
</string>
    <string name="192">
The general’s wife weeps,
She weeps,
But the general does not see.

Yet all in the village
Have seen.

From sorrow,
She wandered from the courtyard,
Lost in thought,
Walked beyond the village,
And saw—

A small boy,
Herding lambs
Among the stubble.

"Oh, sorrow,
My sorrow!
What shall I do in this world?

Is that you, Petrus?"

"Yes, it is I."

"Come with me,
We will live,
As we once lived
On the farmstead."

And she bowed her head,
Her eyes fixed upon Petrus.

She had grown alone,
Had lived as a maiden,
And for an old general,
She had been ruined,
Sold!

And together,
They drank away the money…

And she wept,
She wept bitterly.

"Come, my dear,
Let us walk!
Come, Petrus,
To the garden,
To the palace."

"But who will watch over them?
Who will herd my lambs?"

"Let whoever wishes!"

And she led him
To the palace.

In the palace,
She adorned him,
Dressed him,
Then sent him to school.

And she was glad.

Let her rejoice,
While hope
Warms her heart,
While from that seed
Grows either tares
Or wheat.

For we do not know
What happens
In His realm.

And He may know,
But He does not tell us.

If only
Your mother had known
Your sorrow,
Would she have given
Her only child
To the general?

She would not have…

But then,
I do not know…

For all kinds of mothers exist.

The days pass,
Slowly,
Petrus goes to school,
Returns from school,
Carries books,
Grows.

She herself
Seems to grow younger,
And the general rejoices,
That together,
They have done
A holy deed.

They have freed Petrus,
</string>
    <string name="193">
They took the boy to Kyiv,
And there,
They sent him to school,
And there,
He studied much.

Petrus returned from Kyiv,
Already Petro,
Already a young nobleman,
Already his black mustache
Had grown.

Already…
But this will not flee,
We will tell,
Someday,
The dreams
That Petro dreamed there…

Before the image
Of the Holy Virgin,
The lamp burns at night.

Bowing deeply,
She prayed…
She wept bitter,
Unholy tears.

She pleaded
With the Most Holy,
That she protect her,
That she save her,
That she not let her
Lose her mind,
Oh, Most Pure One!

And in vain…
Her prayer
Did not help her!

She, poor soul,
Had fallen in love
With her Petrus,
It was heavy upon her.

Upon her innocent,
Young soul!

But what could she do?
She had no strength left,
The poor woman
Lost her mind at once!

And how,
How could one,
Alone,
Live out
Her youthful years?

They will not return!

No matter what,
They say,
Misfortune must be overcome!

Not God will judge,
But people.

They,
They will condemn you,
With their unjust judgment!

Petrus!
Good child!

You do not yet know,
You are innocent,
How heavy it is
To love in this world!

To love…
And in vain…
In vain to perish,
To perish,
Never to live out your years!

She is your holy mother,
Your only sister!

For her,
You would gladly die,
Three times a day,
Gladly give up
</string>
    <string name="194">
Your youthful paradise!

But you can give
Nothing more…

For the heart
Cannot give her sin!

She is your poor mother!

Like a fierce serpent,
Sinful love
Has sunk its fangs
Into her heart…

Not paradise,
But cruel hell
Has spread
Through her sinful blood!

And she does not know,
She does not know
What to do.

What should she do
With herself?

Should she hide
Beneath the water?
Should she
Break her head?

"I will go to Kyiv,
I will pray…

Perhaps prayer
Will drive away
The devil…

Petrus!
Prayer
Will not save me!

I will drown myself
In the Dnipro!"

Pray to the Lord,
Maidens!

Pray to the Lord,
That your mother
Does not sell you so!

Pray to God,
That in spring,
The Lord
Sends someone to love,
Then you will live
In joy!

That love
Will be youthful,
And pure…
Like a child’s dream
At dawn!

But in autumn,
To love is sin!

That is not love,
That is hell,
And they will mock,
They will condemn,
And the righteous God
Will punish!

For dark-browed Petro…

She went to Kyiv,
She prayed,
Even in Pochaiv!

The holy power
Did not help!

The poor woman
Returned to the village,
Brought with her
Her serpent,
Even fiercer…

And a drop
Of some poison.

She did not eat
For three days,
Did not drink,
Did not sleep
For three days,
Three nights!

Her lips dried,
Her eyes sank…

She no longer prays
At night,
She whispers something,
Laughing!

For a week,
The sinful one
Suffered,
She did not know
What to do!
</string>
    <string name="195">
Then she brewed poison,
And gave it to the general,
So he would know
How to love a maiden.

Now I will bury the old man,
Welcome the young one,
And live,
Oh, I will live!

And in the morning,
The bells tolled
For the general’s soul…

People whispered ill words,
As they walked behind the coffin.

Oh, the Lord’s punishment
Will not pass!
It will fall
Like thunder
Upon the sinful head!

Like storm clouds,
The people gathered,
Buzzing,
Whispering of poison,
As if waiting for someone…

And all fell silent
For a moment.

The court arrived…
They took knives,
Opened the general!

They found poison
In his stomach!

And upon the Lord’s cross,
The entire assembly swore,
They swore…

The court asked:
"Now confess, Christians!
Who poisoned the lord?"

A murmur,
Like soft bells…

"The lady! The lady!"

The people roared together.

And punishment fell…

Petrus stepped onto the porch,
And spoke to the crowd:

"Your words are false,
I did it!
I poisoned the general!

And why,
I know well,
But I will not tell you,
Wicked people,
Perhaps,
I will confess before God."

They took young Petrus,
And immediately
Sent him to Kyiv.

Petrus was not tormented long
In the deep prison…

In good time,
They shackled him well,
Shaved his head for good measure…

And Petrus dragged his chains
All the way to Siberia…
</string>
    <string name="196">
It seems to me,
I do not know,
But people do not truly die,

They crawl into another form,
A pig, perhaps,
And live on,
Bathing in the mire,
As they once bathed in sin.

And truly so.

I care not
For the simple,
Gray wretches,
They are forgotten
Even by God.

So why should I
Warm myself over them?

But where are those others?

Are they truly
Raised in pens,
Fed for slaughter?

Perhaps so?

They did much good
Upon the earth,
They shed tears
Like rivers,
And blood
Like seas.

People know
Whom they feed,
Whom they tend.

And what will you say?

Did they spill
Seas of blood
For glory?

Or for themselves?

No,
For us!

For us,
Poor souls,
They burned the world!

Until they were locked
In pens.

Had it not been so,
Surely,
A swineherd
Would have grazed them
In the meadow.

Cursed! Cursed!

Where is your glory?

In words!

Where is your gold,
Your palaces?

Where is your great power?

In tombs,
In tombs,
Whitewashed by executioners,
The same as you.

You lived
As fierce beasts,
And became swine!

Where are you?

Holy martyr?

Prophet of God?

You are among us,
You,
Ever-present,
Dwell among us,
Like a holy angel.

You, dear friend,
Speak softly,
Softly…

Of love,
Of misfortune,
Of sorrow,
Or of God,
Or of the sea,
Or of blood,
Spilled in vain
By great executioners.
</string>
    <string name="197">
You weep bitterly
Before us,
And we weep…

The poet’s holy soul
Lives,
Lives in his sacred words,
And we,
Reading,
Come alive,
And feel God
In the heavens.

Thank you,
My poor friend!

You, I know,
Shared your only offering,
Before God,
You have earned much,
Brother!

You sent me,
In captivity,
Our poet…

You opened the door
To freedom for me!

Thank you,
Friend!

I will read,
Even a little…
I will revive…
I will welcome hope
Into my heart,
Softly, softly,
I will sing,
And call God
By His name.
</string>
    <string name="198">
**6.**

If you knew,
Young lords,
Where people weep
As they live,

You would not write elegies,
You would not praise God in vain,
Laughing at our tears.

Why,
I do not know,
Do they call
A cottage in the grove
A quiet paradise?

I suffered in that house once,
My tears were shed there,
My first tears;
I do not know,
If there is
A cruel evil in God!

What did not live
In that house?

Yet they call it paradise!

I do not call it paradise,
That cottage in the grove,
By the clear pond,
At the edge of the village.

There,
My mother swaddled me,
And, swaddling,
Sang,
Poured her sorrow
Into her child…

In that grove,
In that cottage,
In that paradise,
I saw hell…

There, captivity,
Heavy labor,
Never even
Allowed prayer.

There,
My good mother,
Still young,
Was laid in the grave
By hardship and toil.

There,
My father,
Weeping with his children
(And we were small,
And naked),
Could not endure
His cruel fate,
Died in servitude!

And we
Scattered among people,
Like mice.

I went to school—
To carry water
For the students.

My brothers
Went to servitude,
Until their heads
Were shaved!

And my sisters!
My sisters!
Woe to you,
My young doves,
For whom
Do you live in this world?

You grew up
In servitude,
Strangers,
In servitude,
Your hair will turn white,
In servitude,
Sisters,
You will die!

It frightens me,
Even to remember
That cottage
At the edge of the village!
</string>
    <string name="199">
What happens there,
In that paradise?

Surely, joy and praise!
To You, the only,
The holy,
For Your wondrous deeds?

Ah, but no!

There is no one to praise,
Only blood,
Only tears,
Only blasphemy,
Blasphemy against all!

No, no,
There is nothing holy
Upon this earth…

It seems to me,
That even You,
Have been cursed
By mankind!
</string>
    <string name="200">
**7.**

Sometimes,
In captivity,
I recall
My distant past,
I search,
I search,
For something
To boast of,
That I, too,
Have lived,
That I, too,
Once praised God!

I search,
I search…

Oh Lord,
I would wish
To remember
Even something!

But then,
I stumble
Upon such filth,
That I fall asleep,
Without praying…

And I dreamt…

Falling asleep
Like a swine,
Naturally,
Such a dream
Would come…

As if,
By a grave,
I herd lambs,
And I am still small.

I look,
The grave
Seems to open,
And from it,
Emerges a Cossack,
Already gray-haired,
Poor soul,
And he walks toward me…

I shrink,
Like a pup
Beneath a fence,
Small,
And I am afraid.

He takes me,
As if in his arms,
Carries me
Into the grave,
And the black grave
Opens even wider.

I look,
In the grave,
All are Cossacks:

One without a head,
One without an arm,
One cut at the knees—

They lie,
Like in a warm house.

"Look, child,
These are Cossacks,"
(As if he tells me),
"Across all Ukraine,
High mounds rise,
Look, child,
All those mounds,
All are the same.

Filled with our noble corpses,
Filled tightly.

Here, freedom sleeps!

She lay down gloriously,
She lay down together
With us,
The Cossacks!

See how she lies—
As if swaddled!

There is no lord here,
We all lived equally,
In freedom!

We all lay down equally,
For freedom,
We all will rise,
But God alone knows,
</string>
    <string name="201">
When that will be.

Look well, child!
Look closely—
And I will tell you,
Why Ukraine
Began to perish,
Why I, too,
Lie among them
In the grave.

You will tell the people,
When you grow,
My son.

Listen, child."

And then,
I dreamt of lambs,
In the rye,
The overseer ran,
Struck me hard,
And as if cursed,
Tore my coat.

It still aches,
When I recall that dream.

And when I recall
The Cossack in the grave,
I still do not know,
Was it real,
Or was it
Some phantom?

That Cossack
Told me this…
</string>
    <string name="202">
**Tytaryvna**

On Sunday,
In the village,
In the tavern,
Upon the table,
The minstrels sat,
Played,
A coin per dance.

Dust rose all around.

The girls danced,
And the lads…

"Enough!
Play another!"

"This one is good!"

And again,
The lyres roared,
And again,
The girls,
Like magpies,
And the lads,
Hands on their hips,
Squatted low.

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

The finest lad,
Mykyta,
Stood upon the bench,
In a gray coat,
The finest boy,
Yet a bastard,
A bastard,
And poor,

So no one
Cared for him.

He stood,
Like a post…

Shoulders pressed
Against the ceiling,
He stared,
And froze,
At Tytaryvna…

And she,
Adorned in flowers,
Like painted,
Stood alone,
And glanced,
At Mykyta…

He burns!
He burns,
In his gray coat!

He pulls a coin,
And for the last dance,
He hires the music,
And invites
The noble Tytaryvna
To dance!

"Leave me be,
Vagabond!"

And she laughed.

Tytaryvna laughed,
At poor Mykyta.

She laughed,
Before the people,
That he wore
A gray coat!

It will come to you,
Tytaryvna!

You will weep,
Poor soul,
For that laughter!

Where is Mykyta?

He went
On a long journey,
And was never heard from again…

Since then,
Something happened
To Tytaryvna!

She came home,
Weeping,
Lay down to sleep,
Weeping,
Did not eat supper!

She did not sleep,
As she lay,
So she rose,
As she had lain,
As if mad!

What to do?

She does not know!

And Mykyta,
Like an owl,
In his gray coat,
Stands before her eyes!

A phantom,
And nothing more!

Tytaryvna!

At an ill hour,
From that nobleman,
You laughed…

Now,
You pity him…

Sorrow, grief,
And shame
Have surrounded her soul.
</string>
    <string name="203">
And you wept!
Why?

Because you had loved
Poor Mykyta
So deeply!

A strange wonder,
What happens
With the heart!

In the evening,
It shuns,
In the morning,
It desires!

And so fiercely
It desires,
That it would go
To the ends of the earth
To seek him…

And now,
She does not know
Where to go,
Tytaryvna…

Even into the water,
If only to reach Mykyta…

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

Beware, maidens,
Of laughing
At the lowly,

Lest you suffer
As Tytaryvna did!

Like a blade of grass,
She withered,
And her father,
Her mother,
Worried,
Took her to Kyiv,
On a pilgrimage.

They fed her
Holy herbs,
And still,
They did not help!

She trod a path
To the grave,
Always looking for him.

And the path
Began to overgrow,
For she no longer
Had the strength to rise.

Such is what laughter
Has wrought!

And he vanished,
Disappeared,
He was forgotten,
Did he ever exist?

Year after year,
Three years passed.

On the fourth year,
On Sunday,
In the tavern,
In the village,
Upon the wide table,
Blind minstrels sat;

They took a coin,
And played the same tune,
As the year before.

The girls danced,
Just as finely,
As the year before.
</string>
    <string name="204">
Bold,
In a blue cap,
In a coat,
In red trousers,
Like viburnum,

A Cossack leaps,
Squatting low,
And sings:

*"Thank you, father,
Thank you, mother,
For raising us!

As they raised us,
They scattered grain,
At night, upon the stove…"*

"Vodka! Mead!
Where is the leader?
The people?
The constable?

Wretched,
Miserable,
Pitiful lads,
Come, let us fight!
Or wrestle,
For I am a wrestler!"

Not for a week,
Not for two,
Not for three,
Not for four!

Like a sore,
Like an illness,
The people indulged
That wrestler…

He capriciously
Demanded,
Like a nobleman…

And where
Had such a wretch
Come from?

The entire village
Could not satisfy
The cursed one.

And he wandered,
Drank,
Tormented the lads,
With the maidens.

The maidens
Fell ill for him.

So fine,
So wealthy!

He no longer
Fought anyone,
But simply wandered,
And in the evenings,
Visited the priest’s garden.

And Tytaryvna
Met him,
Sang,
Spoke:

*"Is this not Mykyta,
Whose coat has flaps?"*

It is he,
It is he,
Whom you mocked
In the village,
Once.

And now,
You go to him,
To the garden,
Yourself,

You serve him,
A bastard,
Like a nobleman!

Not for a day,
Not for two,
Tytaryvna
Went to the garden,
</string>
    <string name="205">
Not for a day,
Not for two,
She served Mykyta,
Like a nobleman!

She served,
She served,
Until the very end.

And she did not notice!

Days passed,
Months passed,
Summer passed,
Autumn passed,
The seventh month passed,
The eighth,
The ninth
Was coming.

Your sorrow
Will come!

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

In the priest’s garden,
In the ravine,
A well
Beneath the willow…

To the well,
Not to drink,
Tytaryvna
Barely walks,
To grieve a little,
To weep,
To ponder,
How she will remain a maiden?

Where can she go,
From shame?
Where can she hide?

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

One evening,
In winter,
In a single coat,
Barefoot,
Tytaryvna walks,
Carrying a child.

She approaches the well,
Then steps back.

And from the viburnum,
Like a serpent,
The bastard peers!

She placed her son
Upon the well’s edge,
And ran…

And Mykyta
Crawled from the viburnum,
And threw him
Into the well,
Like a pup!

And he walked away,
Singing,
To tell the constable,
To bring the people,
To search for the child!

On Sunday morning,
The people gathered,
They drained the well,
They searched for the child.
</string>
    <string name="206">
They found,
They found your son,
Tytaryvna,
In the marsh.

Oh, they took
The unfortunate one,
Bound her in chains,
Confessed her,
Gave her communion,
Cursed her father,
Cursed her mother,
Judged her as a people,
And laid her,
Still alive,
In the coffin!

And her son with her!

Then buried them
Beneath the earth!

They built
A tall pillar,
So that people
Would know of her,
Would teach their children,
Would teach their daughters,
If their father,
If their mother,
Did not.

That wrestler
Was no longer
In the village;

But in Poland,
People met
A nobleman,
Who asked,

"Is she alive,
Tytaryvna?
Does she still
Mock the lowly?"

It was he!

The Lord
Punished him
For his great sin,
Not with death—
He would live,
And as a devil-man,
He would wander the world,
And deceive you,
Maidens,
Forever.
</string>
    <string name="207">
What are words,
One might say?

Words and voice—
Nothing more.

Yet the heart beats—
It comes alive,
When it hears them!

Surely,
From God,
That voice,
Those words,
Come among people!

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

Leaning,
Not deeply sorrowed,
But simply standing
Upon the deck,
Gazing straight
At the sea,
As if at Judas…

From the mist,
As they say,
Appeared
The red-faced Diana…

And I had thought
To lie down to sleep,
But I stood,
To look a little
At the round-faced woman,
Or rather…
The maiden!

A sailor,
A countryman of ours,
From Ostrovna,
Standing watch,
Sorrowed to himself,
And sang—
Softly,
So the captain
Would not hear,
For he was cruel,
Though a countryman.

The sailor sang,
Like a Cossack,
Who grew up
An orphan in servitude,
And went to serve
In the army!

Long ago,
Long ago,
I heard,
Standing beneath the willow,
A maiden
Singing softly,
And I,
A child,
Felt sorrow
For that gray orphan,
Who had grown weary,
Leaning upon the fence.

People said,
People spoke:
"Perhaps,
He is drunk."

And I wept,
A child,
For the orphan.

. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

Why do you weep now?

Why now,
Old man,
In this captivity,
Do you sorrow—
</string>
    <string name="208">
That the world
Is bound,
Is closed!

That you yourself
Are now a soldier,
That your heart
Is torn,
Is broken,
And all that was
Good,
All that was dear,
Has spilled away,
That this
Is how life
Has turned out—

Is it so,
Little swan?!

Indeed…
</string>
    <string name="209">
In Vilnius,
That famed city,
This happened
Not long ago.

Then,
They made
A grand hospital
Of it,
And drove out
The scholars,
For they did not
Bow their heads
At the Sharp Gate.

A fool
Is known
By his ways.

Yet to name him,
By God,
I do not know how,
That student,
What shall we do?

He was the son
Of a proud
Lithuanian countess,
And fine,
And wealthy,
And an only child,
And he studied,
Not as a nobleman,
And he removed his cap
At the Sharp Gate.

It was well,
But misfortune
Befell him!
</string>
    <string name="210">
He fell in love,
Poor soul,
He was young,
With a Jewish maiden,
And he thought,
With her,
That his mother
Would not know,
To wed,
For there was
No other way,
For she was
Cursed!

Like painted,
She sat,
Until night,
By the window,
Wiping
Her tearful eyes,
For she, too,
Had loved—
And oh,
How she had loved!

She walked
Upon the boulevard,
She went
To school—
Always with her father,
So there was
No way.

And a banker,
From Lublin,
Courted
The Jewish maiden.

What was there
To do in this world?

He might as well
Drown himself
In Zakret,
He did not wish
To live
Without the Jewish maiden,
The student.

And the old Jew,
As if he knew—
Locked his only daughter
In the house,
When he went
To the shops
In the morning,
And hired
A guard,
Old Rukhlya.

No,
Poor soul,
Rukhlya
Would not help.

Where had she,
In this world,
Read such a romance,
With a silk ladder—
And Rukhlya
Did not know.

Perhaps,
She guessed herself.

Only,
She set to work,
And wove
One for herself,
And at night,
She descended
To the student,
Into the street.

And where
Should they flee?

But they—
Naturally,
Children—
Lovingly kissed,
By the gate.

And the Jew,
From the courtyard,
Like a madman,
Ran out.
</string>
    <string name="211">
With an axe!
Woe!

Woe to you,
Old mother,
Your son is gone,
Upon the street,
Lies the slain child,
Slain by the Jew,
Woe to you, mother.

The Jewish maiden…
Where did such strength
Come to the child?

She seized the axe,
And into her father’s chest,
She drove it,
To the hilt.

Such a wonder,
In that famed city,
In Vilnius,
Occurred.

People marveled long,
Where had she hidden,
That serpent of a maiden,
Who slew her father?

And she,
At night,
Softly,
Drowned herself
In the Vilija,

For they found her
In Zakret,
And buried her there.

And the countess,
Without her child,
Poor soul,
Remained.

She went to Rome,
They say,
And somewhere,
She ended up,
And with some
Bare marquis,
They say,
She wed.

Perhaps,
They lie,
For, naturally,
That is what people do,
And they will not forget
The widow,
And they will condemn her too!
</string>
    <string name="212">
A black cloud
Covered
The white cloud.

From beyond the estuary,
With the Turks,
The Tatars emerged.

From Polissia,
The nobles crept,
And the hetman-priest’s son,
From beyond the Dnipro,
Pressed forward—
Foolish Samoilovych.

With Romodan,
Like a flock of jackdaws,
They covered Ukraine,
And pecked
As much as they could…

And you, Chyhyryn!

And you,
Old Doroshenko,
Brother of the Zaporizhians!

Are you unwell,
Or do you fear
To stand against the enemy?

"I do not fear,
Captains,
But I grieve for Ukraine,"

And Doroshenko wept,
Like a child!

"We will not scatter
The enemy’s force,
I will not rise again!

Take my hetman’s
Regalia,
Gentlemen,
And carry them
To the Muscovite,
Let Moscow know,
That Hetman Doroshenko
No longer exists.

And I,
Brothers,
Zaporizhians,
Will take the monk’s robe,
And go to bow
In Mezhyhirya,
Before the Savior."

The bells rang,
The cannon roared.

In two ranks,
The Dnipro men
Stood with the Muscovites,
A mile long—
Between the ranks,
They carried the regalia…

Enough, Petro,
Of drinking
Tiasmyn’s water.

They laid
Those regalia
At Popovych’s feet.
</string>
    <string name="213">
Go, Petro,
To Mezhyhirya,
To pray to God.

They did not let
Doroshenko go,
They recognized him
In his robe,
Bound him in chains,
Sent him to Sosnytsia.

And from Sosnytsia,
To Yaropolche,
To live out his days.

Thus,
It came to you,
Brother Zaporizhian!

The sun rose
Above Chyhyryn,
From behind the clouds,
The Tatars,
With the Turks,
Returned to their uluses.

And the Poles,
With their Charnetsky,
With vile Stepan,
Burned the church of God,
And the bones of Bohdan,
And Tymish,
In Subotiv,
They burned well,
Then went to Poland,
As if they had done well.

And the Muscovites,
With Romodan,
On Sunday morning,
Went with Popovych,
Along Romodan’s road.

Like a tamed eagle,
Without wings,
Without freedom,
The glorious Doroshenko
Wasted away in captivity,
And died of sorrow.

He grew weary
Of dragging his chains.

And in Ukraine,
They forgot
The glorious hetman.

Only you,
Saint Rostov,
Remembered,
In the dungeon,
Your great friend,
And ordered a chapel
Built above the hetman,
And prayers to be said
For the hetman,
A requiem
For Petro.
</string>
    <string name="214">
And still,
Every year,
When that day comes,
They go to hold
A requiem
For our hetman
In Yaropolche.

**425**

Oh, though I may winnow,
I will not cease,
Yet I will not winnow away
What God has given.

**__________**

Ru-dudu, ru-dudu,
Born into misfortune,
To heat with straw,
To carry water in a pot.
</string>
    <string name="217">
**Tytaryvna**

Long ago,
This happened once,
When wrestlers
Still roamed among us,
Deceiving maidens,
Mocking the people,
Beating the lads,
And ruling the village,
Like hussars
At their post.

Back in the days
Of the holy hetmanate,
Long ago,
This happened once.

On Sunday,
In the village…
</string>

</resources>